<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE wetgeving SYSTEM "http://wetten.overheid.nl/dtd/bwb-plus-meta-1_61w.dtd">
<wetgeving bwb-id="BWBV0004749" dtdversie="2.0" id="10000042239" verdragnummer="008552" soort="verdrag"> 
  
  
  <intitule>Notawisseling tussen de Nederlandse en de Japanse Regering houdende een overeenkomst inzake de afschaffing van visa voor diplomatieke en dienstpaspoorten</intitule>
  
  <verdrag status="goed" tekst="authentiek" xml:lang="en"><verdragtekst>
<kop>
<label>Nr.</label>
<nr status="officieel">I</nr>

</kop><vrije-tekst><tekst status="goed"><al>ROYAL NETHERLANDS EMBASSY</al><al>No. 1645</al><al>Tokio, September 9th, 1957.</al><al>Monsieur le Ministre,</al><al>With reference to the exchange of notes on May 16th, 1956, between Your Excellency's predecessor and myself concerning the exemption of visa requirements for the nationals of Japan and The Netherlands, I have the honour to state that the following is the further understanding of the Government of The Netherlands in this matter:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>1.</li.nr><al>Japanese and Netherlands nationals holding valid diplomatic, official or service passports issued by the country of which they are nationals shall be free to travel from any place whatever to The Netherlands (territory in Europe) and Japan respectively without the necessity of obtaining a visa irrespective of the duration of stay in The Netherlands and Japan respectively.</al></li><li><li.nr>2.</li.nr><al>Either Party may at any time give to the other Party written notice of its desire to terminate the present Arrangement. The present Arrangement shall be terminated one month after the date of such notice.</al></li><li><li.nr>3.</li.nr><al>After the approval constitutionally required in The Netherlands has been obtained, the present Arrangement shall enter into force on the date ten days after receipt by the Japanese Government of a relevant notification from the Netherlands Government.</al></li></lijst><al>I have further the honour to request Your Excellency to be good enough to confirm on behalf of Your Government that this is also the understanding of the Government of Japan.</al><al>I avail myself of this opportunity to renew to Your Excellency, Monsieur le Ministre, the assurance of my highest consideration.</al><al>(sd.) O. REUCHLIN</al><al><nadruk type="cur">His Excellency</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur"> Mr. Aiichiro Fujiyama,</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur">Minister for Foreign Affairs</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur">of Japan.</nadruk></al></tekst></vrije-tekst></verdragtekst>
<verdragtekst>
<kop>
<label>Nr.</label>
<nr status="officieel">II</nr>
</kop><vrije-tekst><tekst status="goed"><al><nadruk type="cur">Translation</nadruk><noot><noot.nr>1)</noot.nr><noot.al>[Red: Deze vertaling, vervaardigd door de Regering van Japan, was gevoegd bij de originele, in de Japanse taal gestelde nota.]</noot.al></noot></al><al> THE GAIMUSHO</al><al>No. 52/EA1</al><al>Tokyo, September 20, 1957.</al><al>Monsieur l'Ambassadeur,</al><al>I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of Your Excellency's Note of September 9th, 1957, addressed to Foreign Minister Fujiyama, which reads as follows:</al><al><redactie type="extra">(zoals in nr. I)</redactie></al><al>I have further the honour to confirm on behalf of the Government of Japan that this is also the understanding of the Government of Japan.</al><al>I avail myself of this opportunity to renew to Your Excellency, Monsieur l'Ambassadeur, the assurance of my highest consideration.</al><al>(sd.) NOBUSUKE KISHI</al><al>the Prime Minister</al><al>Minister for Foreign Affairs</al><al>ad interim</al><al><nadruk type="cur">His Excellency</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur"> Jonkheer O. Reuchlin,</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur">Ambassador Extraordinary and</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur">Plenipotentiary of the Netherlands,</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur">Tokyo.</nadruk></al></tekst></vrije-tekst></verdragtekst></verdrag></wetgeving>
  	