<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE wetgeving SYSTEM "http://wetten.overheid.nl/dtd/bwb-plus-meta-1_61w.dtd">
<wetgeving bwb-id="BWBV0004187" dtdversie="2.0" id="10000036619" sleutel="V3378" verdragnummer="003036" soort="verdrag"> 
  
  
  <intitule>Briefwisseling tussen de Regering van het Koninkrijk der Nederlanden en het Algemeen Hoofdkwartier van de Geallieerde Mogendheden in Europa (SHAPE) betreffende het functioneren in Nederland van het Hoofdkwartier van de Geallieerde strijdkrachten in Centraal-Europa (AFCENT)</intitule> 
   
  <verdrag tekst="authentiek" xml:lang="en"><verdragtekst>
<kop>
<label>Nr.</label>
<nr status="officieel">I</nr>
</kop><vrije-tekst><tekst status="goed"><al>Brussels, May 26, 1969.</al><al>My dear General,</al><al>By your letter dated 12th December, 1966 you proposed a number of items which, in connection with the move of the Headquarters of the Allied Forces in Central Europe (AFCENT) to the Netherlands, should be added to the Agreement between the Kingdom of the Netherlands and SHAPE of 25th May, 1964 or alternatively be agreed by exchange of letters.</al><al>Those items concerned which affect existing Netherlands legislation and which, accordingly, have to be submitted for parliamentary approval, are dealt with in a separate exchange of notes of today's date.</al><al>With regard to the remaining items proposed by you, my Government suggests the following arrangements:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>1.</li.nr><al><nadruk type="cur">Registration of vehicles.</nadruk></al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>Motor vehicles of the AFCENT Headquarters shall be registered and licensed by the Headquarters. They will bear a clearly recognizable sign indicating that they belong to AFCENT. The distinctive plate RC will continue to be used.</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>Private motor vehicles of AFCENT-members and their dependents imported free of duty and/or tax shall be registered and licensed by AFCENT in accordance with a procedure to be agreed with the competent Netherlands authorities.</al></li></lijst></li><li><li.nr>2.</li.nr><al><nadruk type="cur">Concession agreements with Netherlands business firms.</nadruk></al><al>AFCENT is authorized to grant, within its premises, concessions relating to the establishment of barber and beauty shops, laundry and dry cleaning pick-up points, banking and travel facilities and other concessions as appropriate, provided that the firms concerned are qualified in accordance with relevant Netherlands legal and statutory regulations.</al></li><li><li.nr>3.</li.nr><al><nadruk type="cur">Exemptions and privileges accorded to non-host country commercial entreprises.</nadruk></al><al>Pursuant to article XI, paragraph 4 of the Status of Forces Agreement as further extended to Allied Headquarters by article 8 of the Protocol of 28th August, 1952, the kinds and quantities of goods which entitled persons may procure free of duty and/or tax will be determined in agreement with the competent Netherlands authorities. AFCENT shall cooperate closely with the competent Netherlands authorities to prevent unauthorized re-sales on the local market of such goods, or other abuses of the privileges and immunities granted.</al></li><li><li.nr>4.</li.nr><al><nadruk type="cur">Identification of civilian personnel, exempt from entering in the population registers.</nadruk></al><al>In the personal identity card issued, in conformity with article 5 of the Protocol, to civilian personnel, shall be specified whether the person concerned enjoys international status.</al></li><li><li.nr>5.</li.nr><al><nadruk type="cur">Information.</nadruk></al><al>In connection with the implementation of certain privileges and immunities AFCENT shall provide the Netherlands authorities with relevant information.</al></li><li><li.nr>6.</li.nr><al><nadruk type="cur">National elements.</nadruk></al><al>The various benefits and privileges accorded to AFCENT will also be accorded to personnel, both military and civilian and their dependents, of national elements serving in the Netherlands in support of AFCENT. The personnel concerned shall be provided the identity cards mentioned in article 5 of the Protocol.</al></li><li><li.nr>7.</li.nr><al><nadruk type="cur">International Military Police.</nadruk></al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(i)</li.nr><al>The international military police of AFCENT shall have the right to police the premises of the Headquarters and shall be responsible therein for the maintenance of order and security and discipline. For this purpose, the term &#x201C;the premises of the Headquarters&#x201D; includes shopping area.</al></li><li><li.nr>(ii)</li.nr><al>The international military police may be employed outside the premises of the Headquarters in places to which the public has access only for the purpose of taking action with respect to AFCENT personnel as is necessary to maintain order and discipline, such employment to be subject to specific arrangements between AFCENT and the competent Netherlands authorities.</al></li><li><li.nr>(iii)</li.nr><al>The operation of international military police vehicles carrying a distinguishing police sign recognizable as such in the Netherlands is authorized.</al></li><li><li.nr>(iv)</li.nr><al>A suitable channel for the operation of police very high frequency radio network shall be allocated by the qualified Netherlands authorities.</al></li></lijst></li><li><li.nr>8.</li.nr><al><nadruk type="cur">Medical.</nadruk></al><al>AFCENT may install and use medical and dental facilities for its personnel and their dependents.</al></li><li><li.nr>9.</li.nr><al><nadruk type="cur">Recruiting of Civilian Personnel.</nadruk></al><al>AFCENT may recruit directly the categories of civilian personnel mentioned in article 3, paragraph 1 <nadruk type="cur">(b) (ii)</nadruk> of the Protocol.</al></li></lijst><al>AFCENT may also recruit directly and employ in the Netherlands the civilian labour it requires, subject to the provision of article X of the Agreement of 25th May, 1964.</al><al>I propose that, if the foregoing provisions are acceptable to you, this letter and your affirmative reply will be considered to constitute an arrangement to that effect between the Netherlands Government and SHAPE.</al><al>Please accept, my dear General, the assurances of my highest consideration.</al><al>(sd.) H. N. BOON,</al><al>Permanent Representative of the</al><al> Netherlands to the North</al><al>Atlantic Council.</al><al><nadruk type="cur">To: General Lyman L. Lemnitzer</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur">Supreme Allied Commander Europe</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur">Casteau</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur">Belgium</nadruk></al></tekst></vrije-tekst></verdragtekst>
<verdragtekst>
<kop>
<label>Nr.</label>
<nr status="officieel">II</nr>

</kop><vrije-tekst><tekst status="goed"><tussenkop kopopmaak="cur">SUPREME ALLIED COMMANDER EUROPE</tussenkop><al>17 June 1969</al><al> Dear Mr. Ambassador,</al><al>I have the honor to acknowledge receipt of your Note of 26 May 1969 reading as follows:</al><al><redactie type="extra">(zoals in Nr. I)</redactie></al><al>I have the honor to inform you that the provisions set forth in the above mentioned Note are acceptable to SHAPE, so that the said Note and the present reply constitute a supplementary agreement between the Netherlands Government and SHAPE.</al><al>Sincerely,</al><al>(sd.) L. L. LEMNITZER</al><al> General, U. S. Army</al><al> Supreme Allied Commander</al>
<al><nadruk type="cur">His Excellency Dr. H. N. Boon</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur">Netherlands Permanent Representative</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur"> to the North Atlantic Council</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur"> Boulevard Leopold 111</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur">Brussels 39</nadruk></al></tekst></vrije-tekst></verdragtekst></verdrag> 
</wetgeving>
  	