<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE wetgeving SYSTEM "http://wetten.overheid.nl/dtd/bwb-plus-meta-1_61w.dtd">
<wetgeving bwb-id="BWBV0001222" id="10000004709" verdragnummer="007152" soort="verdrag">
  <intitule>Briefwisseling tussen de Regering van het Koninkrijk der Nederlanden
    en de Verenigde Naties houdende een verdrag inzake de toepassing van het
    tussen Partijen gesloten Verdrag betreffende de zetel van het Internationaal
    Tribunaal voor het voormalige Joegoslavi&#xEB;, op de werkzaamheden en
    handelingen van het Internationaal Tribunaal voor Ruanda</intitule>
  
  <verdrag tekst="authentiek" xml:lang="en">
    <verdragtekst>
      
      <kop>
        <label>Nr.</label><nr>I</nr>
      <titel>UNITED NATIONS &#x2013; NATIONS UNIES</titel></kop>
      <vrije-tekst>
        <tekst status="goed">
          
          
          <al>22 April 1996 </al>
          <al>Sir,</al>
          <al>As you know, by resolution 955 (1994) of 8 November 1994 the
            Security Council of the United Nations, acting under Chapter VII of
            the Charter of the United Nations, established an International
            Tribunal for the sole purpose of prosecuting persons responsible for
            genocide and other serious violations of international humanitarian
            law committed in the territory of Rwanda and Rwandan citizens
            responsible for genocide and other such violations committed in the
            territory of neigboring States, between 1 January 1994 and 31
            December 1994 (hereinafter referred to as &#x201C;the International
            Tribunal for Rwanda&#x201D;). By the same resolution the Security
            Council adopted the Statute of the International Tribunal for Rwanda
            (hereinafter referred to as &#x201C;the Statute&#x201D;).</al>
          <al>Although the International Tribunal for Rwanda is a separate
            entity from the International Tribunal for the Former Yugoslavia,
            there are nevertheless certain institutional links between the two
            Tribunals which have been formalized in the Statute. I refer, in
            particular, to the common Appeals Chamber and the common Prosecutor.</al>
          <al>While the Security Council has designated Arusha as the seat of
            the International Tribunal for Rwanda and decided that an Office of
            the Prosecutor should be in Kigali, given the institutional links
            between the two Tribunals, it is evident that certain activities and
            proceedings of the International Tribunal for Rwanda may be
            undertaken in The Hague from time to time.</al>
          <al>In order to facilitate such activities and proceedings of the
            International Tribunal for Rwanda as may take place in The Hague, I
            have the honour to propose that the pertinent provisions of the
            Agreement between the United Nations and the Kingdom of the
            Netherlands concerning the Headquarters of the International
            Tribunal for the Former Yugoslavia, concluded on 24 July 1994, be
            applicable, mutatis mutandis, to the activities and proceedings of
            the International Tribunal for Rwanda in the territory of the
            Kingdom of the Netherlands, in particular:</al>
          <al>The judges of the Appeals Chamber and the Prosecutor residing in
            The Hague will enjoy the privileges and immunities as mentioned in
            Article XIV of the Agreement;</al>
          <al>Staff of the liaison office in The Hague will enjoy the privileges
            and immunities mentioned in Article XV of the Agreement;</al>
          <al>Staff and persons performing missions for the Rwanda Tribunal not
            forming part of the liaison office in The Hague, shall enjoy the
            privileges and immunities mentioned in Article XVII of the Agreement.</al>
          <al>I further propose that upon receipt of your confirmation in
            writing of the above, this exchange of letters shall constitute an
            agreement between the United Nations and the Kingdom of the
            Netherlands regarding the applicability of the above-referenced
            Headquarters Agreement to the activities and proceedings of the
            International Tribunal for Rwanda in the territory of the Kingdom of
            the Netherlands, which will enter into force on the first day of the
            second month following the date of receipt of your confirmation.</al>
          <al>Please accept, Sir, the assurances of my highest consideration.</al>
          <al>(sd.) H. CORELL</al>
          <al>Hans Corell  </al>
          <al>Under-Secretary-General for Legal Affairs  </al>
          <al>The Legal Counsel</al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">His Excellency  </nadruk>
          </al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">Mr. Nicolaas H. Biegman  </nadruk>
          </al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">Permanent Representative of the</nadruk>
          </al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">Kingdom of the Netherlands  </nadruk>
          </al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">to the United Nations  </nadruk>
          </al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">New York</nadruk>
          </al>
          </tekst>
      </vrije-tekst>
    </verdragtekst>
  <verdragtekst><kop><label>Nr.</label><nr>II</nr><titel>PERMANENT MISSION OF THE KINGDOM OF THE NETHERLANDS TO THE
            UNITED NATIONS</titel></kop><vrije-tekst><tekst status="goed">
          
          <al>New York, 24 April 1996 </al>
          <al>No. nyv-2653</al>
          <al>Excellency,</al>
          <al>I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your
            Excellency's letter of 22 April 1996, which reads as follows:</al>
          <al><redactie type="extra">(Zoals in Nr. I)</redactie></al>
          <al>On behalf of the Government of the Kingdom of the Netherlands, I
            have further the honour to inform your Excellency that the foregoing
            proposals are acceptable and to confirm that this exchange of
            letters shall constitute an agreement between the Kingdom of the
            Netherlands and the United Nations regarding the applicability of
            the Agreement to the activities and proceedings of the International
            Tribunal for Rwanda in the territory of the Kingdom of the
            Netherlands, which will enter into force on the first day of the
            second month following the date of receipt of this confirmation.</al>
          <al>Accept, Excellency, the assurances of my highest consideration.</al>
          <al>Yours sincerely,</al>
          <al>(sd.) N. H. BIEGMAN</al>
          <al>Dr. N. H. Biegman  </al>
          <al>Ambassador  </al>
          <al>Permanent Representative</al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">H.E. Mr. Hans Corell  </nadruk>
          </al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">Under-Secretary-General for Legal Affairs  </nadruk>
          </al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">The Legal Counsel  </nadruk>
          </al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">United Nations  </nadruk>
          </al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">S-3427A </nadruk>
          </al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">New York, N.Y. 10017</nadruk>
          </al>
        </tekst></vrije-tekst></verdragtekst></verdrag>
</wetgeving>
  	