<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE wetgeving SYSTEM "http://wetten.overheid.nl/dtd/bwb-plus-meta-1_61w.dtd">
<wetgeving bwb-id="BWBV0005431" dtdversie="2.0" id="10000049059" verdragnummer="003738" soort="verdrag">
  
  
  
  <alias-titels><alias-titel>International Convention for the Suppression of the Traffic in Women and Children.</alias-titel></alias-titels><intitule>Internationaal Verdrag ter bestrijding van de handel in vrouwen en kinderen, zoals gewijzigd door het Protocol van 12 november 1947</intitule>
  
  <verdrag status="goed" tekst="authentiek" xml:lang="en"><verdragtekst><kop><titel status="officieel">International Convention for the Suppression of the Traffic in Women and Children.</titel></kop><aanhef><preambule><al>Albania, Germany, Austria, Belgium, Brazil, the British Empire (with Canada, the Commonwealth of Australia, the Union of South Africa, New Zealand and India), Chile, China, Colombia, Costa Rica, Cuba, Esthonia, Greece, Hungary, Italy, Japan, Latvia, Lithuania, Norway, the Netherlands, Persia, Poland (with Danzig), Portugal, Roumania, Siam, Sweden, Switzerland and Czechoslovakia.</al><al>Being anxious to secure more completely the suppression of the Traffic in Women and Children described in the preambles to the Agreement of May 18th, 1904, and to the Convention of May 4th, 1910, under the name of &#x201C;White Slave Traffic&#x201D;; </al><al>Having taken note of the Recommendations contained in the Final Act of the International Conference which was summoned by the Council of the League of Nations and met at Geneva from June 30th to July 5th, 1921; and</al><al>Having decided to conclude a Convention supplementary to the Arrangement and Convention mentioned above:</al><al>Have nominated for this purpose as their Plenipotentiaries:</al><al>The President of the Supreme Council of Albania: 
</al><al>Monsignor Fan S. Noli, Member of Parliament, Delegate to the Second Assembly of the Keague of Nations. 
</al><al>The President of the German Reich: 
</al><al>His Excellency Dr. Adolf M&#xFC;ller, Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary in Berne.</al><al> 

The President of the Austrian Republic:</al><al>His Excellency M. Albert Mensdorff&#x2014;Pouilly&#x2014;Dietrichstein, Former Ambassador, Delegate to the Second Assembly of the League of Nations. 

</al><al>His Majesty the King of the Belgians:</al><al>M. Michel Levie, Minister of State, President of the International Conference on Traffic in Women and Children. 

</al><al>The President of the Republic of Brazil: 
</al><al>His Excellency Dr. Cast&#xE3;o da Cunha, Ambassador in Paris, Delegate to the Second Assembly of the League of Nations. 

</al><al>His Majesty the King of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland and of the British Dominions Beyond the Seas, Emperor of India:</al><al>The Right Honourable Arthur James Balfour, O.M., M.P., Lord President of His Majesty's Most Honourable Privy Council, Delegate to the Second Assembly of the League of Nations; and 

</al><al>For the Dominion of Canada: 
</al><al>The Right Honourable Charles Joseph Doherty, Minister of Justice and Attorney-General, Delegate to the Second Assembly of the League of Nations.</al><al>For the Commonwealth of Australia:</al><al>Captain Stanly Melbourne Bruce, M.C., Member of the House of Representatives, Delegate to the Second Assembly of the League of Nations. 

</al><al>For the Union of South Africa: 
</al><al>The Honourable Sir Edgar Harris Walton, K.C.M.G., High Commissioner for the Union of South Africa in the United Kingdom, Delegate to the Second Assembly of the League of Nations. 

</al><al>For the Dominion of New Zealand: 
</al><al>The Honourable Sir James Allen, K.C.B., High Commissioner for New Zealand in the United Kingdom, Delegate to the Second Assembly of the League of Nations. 

</al><al>For India: 
</al><al>The Honourable Theo Russell, Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary of His Britannic Majesty in Berne. 

</al><al>The President of the Republic of Chile:</al><al>His Excellency M. Agustin Edwards, Envoy Extraordininary and Minister Plenipotentiary at London, Delegate to the Second Assembly of the League of Nations. 

</al><al>His Excellency M. Manuel Rivas Vicu&#xF1;a, Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary in Berne, Delegate to the International Conference on Traffic in Women and Children and 
to the Second Assembly of the League of Nations. 

</al><al>The President of the Republic of China:</al><al>His Excellency M. Ouang Yong-Pao, Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary in Berne.</al><al>The President of the Republic of Colombia: 
</al><al>His Excellence Dr. Francisco Jos&#xE9; Urrutia, Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary in Berne, Delegate to the Second Assembly of the League of Nations. 

</al><al>His Excellency Dr. A. J. Restrepo, Barrister for the Republic in the Colombo-Venezuelan arbitration. Delegate to the Second Assembly of the League of Nations. 

</al><al>The President of the Republic of Costa Rica:</al><al>His Excellency M. Manuel Maria de Peralta, Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary in Paris, Delegate to the Second Assembly of the League of Nations. 

</al><al>The President of the Republic of Cuba:</al><al>His Excellency M. Guillermo de Blanck, Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary in Berne and The Hague, Delegate to the Second Assembly of the League of Nations. 

</al><al>The President of the Republic of Esthonia:</al><al>His Excellency M. Antoine Piip, Minister for Foreign Affairs, Delegate to the Second Assembly of the League of Nations. 

</al><al>His Majesty the King of the Hellenes: 
</al><al>M. Vassili Dendramis, Director of the Permanent Greek Secretariat for the League of Nations, Delegate tho the International Conference on Traffic in Women and Children. 

</al><al>His Serene Highness the Governor of Hungary: 
</al><al>M. F&#xE9;lix Parcher de Terjekfalva, Charg&#xE9; d'Affaires in Berne. 

</al><al>His Majesty the King of Italy: 
</al><al>His Excellency the Marquis G. Imperiali dei Principi di Francavilla, Ambassador, Delegate to the Second Assembly of the League of Nations. 

</al><al>His Majesty the Emperor of Japan:</al><al>His Excellency M. le Baron G. Hayashi, Ambassador at London, Delegate to the Second Assembly of the League of Nations. 

</al><al>The President of the Republic of Latvia: 
</al><al>M. M. V. Salnais, Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affais, Delegate to the Second Assembly of the League of Nations. 

</al><al>The President of the Lithuanian Republic: 
</al><al>M. Ernest Galvanauskas, Minister for Finance, Commerce, Industry and Communications, Delegate to the Second Assembly of the League of Nations. 

</al><al>His Majesty the King of Norway: 
</al><al>Dr. Fridtjof Nansen, President of the Norwegian Delegation to the Second Assembly of the League of Nations. 

</al><al>Her Majesty the Queen of the Netherlands:</al><al>Jonkheer A. T. Baud, Attach&#xE9; at the Netherlands Legation in Berne. 

</al><al>His Imperial Majesty the Shah of Persia: 
</al><al>His Highness the Prince Arfa-ed-Dowleh, Delegate to the Second Assembly of the League of Nations. 

</al><al>The President of the Polish Republic: 
</al><al>M. Jean Perlowski<noot type="voet"><noot.nr>1)</noot.nr><noot.al>M. Perlowski is also authorized by the Polish Government to represent the Free city of Danzig.</noot.al></noot>, Counsellor of Legation, Secretary-General of the Polish Delegation accredited to the League of Nations, Delegate to the International Conference on Traffic in Women and Children. 
</al><al>The President of the Portuguese Republic:</al><al>His Excellency M. Alfredo Freire d&#x2019;Andrade, Former Minister for Foreign Affairs, Delegate to the Second Assembly of the League of Nations. 

</al><al>His Majesty the King of Roumania: 
</al><al>His Excellency M. E. Margaritesco Greciano, Minister Plenipotentiary and Roumanian Charg&#xE9; d'Affaires in Berne, Delegate to the International Conference on Traffic in Women and Children. 

</al><al>His Majesty the King of Siam:
</al><al>His Highness the Prince Charoon, Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary. Delegate to the Internationrl Conference on Traffic in Women and Children and to the Second Assembly of the League of Nations. 

</al><al>The Federal Council of the Swiss Confederation: 
</al><al>M. Giuseppe Motta, Federal Councillor, Head of the Political Federal Department, Delegate to the Second Assembly of the League of Nations. 

</al><al>The President of the Czecho-Slovak Republic:</al><al>His Excellency Dr. Robert Flieder, Envoy Extraordinary and and Minister Plenipotentiary in Berne. 

 
</al></preambule><afkondiging><al>Who, having communicated their full powers, found in good and due form, have agreed upon the following provisions:</al></afkondiging></aanhef><wettekst><artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Article</label><nr status="officieel">1</nr></kop><al>The High Contracting Parties agree that, in the event of their not being already Parties to the Agreement of May 18th, 1904, and the Convention of May 4th, 1910, mentioned above, they will transmit, with the least possible delay, their ratifications of, or adhesions to, those instruments in the manner laid down therein. </al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Article</label><nr status="officieel">2</nr></kop><al>The High Contracting Parties agree to take all measures to discover and prosecute persons who are engaged in the traffic in children of both sexes and who commit offences within the meaning of Article 1 of the Convention of May 4th, 1910.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Article</label><nr status="officieel">3</nr></kop><al>The High Contracting Parties agree to take the necessary steps to secure the punishment of attempts to commit, and, within legal limits, of acts preparatory to the commission of, the offences specified in Articles 1 and 2 of the Convention of May 4th, 1910. </al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Article</label><nr status="officieel">4</nr></kop><al>The High Contracting Parties agree that, in cases where there are no extradition Conventions in force between them, they will take all measures within their power to extradite or provide for the extradition of persons accused or convicted of the offences specified in Articles 1 and 2 of the Convention of May 4th, 1910. </al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Article</label><nr status="officieel">5</nr></kop><al>In paragraph B of the final Protocol of the Convention of 1910, the words &#x201C;twenty completed years of age&#x201D; shall be replaced by the words &#x201C;twenty-one completed years of age&#x201D;. </al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Article</label><nr status="officieel">6</nr></kop><al>The High Contracting Parties agree, in case they have not already taken legislative or administrative measures regarding licensing and supervision of employment agencies and offices, to prescribe such regulations as are required to ensure the protection of women and children seeking employment in another country. </al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Article</label><nr status="officieel">7</nr></kop><al> The High Contracting Parties undertake in connection with immigration and emigration to adopt such administrative and legislative measures as are required to check the traffic in women and children. In particular, they undertake to make such regulations as are required for the protection of women and children travelling on emigrant ships, not only at the points of departure and arrival, but also during the journey, and to arrange for the exhibition, in railway stations and in ports, of notices warning women and children of the danger of the traffic and indicating the places where they can obtain accommodation and assistance.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Article</label><nr status="officieel">8</nr></kop><al>The present Convention, of which the French and the English texts are both authentic, shall bear this day's date, and shall be open for signature until March 31st, 1922. </al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Article</label><nr status="officieel">9</nr></kop><al> The present Convention is subject to ratification. As from
1 January 1948 instruments of ratification shall be transmitted to the
Secretary-General of the United Nations, who will notify the receipt
of them to Members of the United Nations and to non-Member States
to which the Secretary-General has communicated a copy of the Convention.
The instruments of ratification shall be deposited in the
archives of the Secretariat of the United Nations.</al><al>In order to comply with the provisions of Article 18 of the Covenant of the League of Nations, the Secretary-General will register the present Convention upon the deposit of the first ratification. </al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Article</label><nr status="officieel">10</nr></kop><al>Members of the United Nations may accede to the present Convention.</al><al>The same applies to non-Member States to which the Economic and
Social Council of the United Nations may decide officially to communicate
the present Convention.</al><al>Accession will be notified to the Secretary-General of the United
Nations, who will notify all Members of the United Nations and the
non-Members States to which the Secretary-General has communicated
a copy of the Convention.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Article</label><nr status="officieel">11</nr></kop><al>The present Convention shall come into force in respect of each Party on the date of the deposit of its ratification or act of accession. </al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Article</label><nr status="officieel">12</nr></kop><al>The present Convention may be denounced by any State which is
a Party thereto, on giving twelve months' notice of its intention to
denounce.</al><al>Denunciation shall be effected by notification in writing addressed
to the Secretary-General of the United Nations. Copies of such notification
shall be transmitted forthwith by him to all Members of the
United Nations and to non-Member States to which the Secretary-General has communicated a copy of the Convention. The denunciation
shall take effect one year after the date on which it was
notified to the Secretary-General of the United Nations, and shall
operate only in respect of the notifying Power.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Article</label><nr status="officieel">13</nr></kop><al>A special record shall be kept by the Secretary-General of the
United Nations, showing which of the Parties have signed, ratified, acceded to or denounced the present Convention. This record shall be
open at all times to any Member of the United Nations or any non-Member State to which the Secretary-General has communicated
a copy of the Convention; it shall be published as often as possible,
in accordance with the directions of the Economic and Social Council
of the United Nations.</al></artikel></wettekst><wetsluiting status="goed"><slotformulering><al>Done at Geneva, the thirtieth day of September, nineteen hundred and twenty-one, in a single copy, which shall remain deposited in the archives of the League of Nations.</al></slotformulering></wetsluiting></verdragtekst></verdrag>
  
<verdrag status="goed" tekst="vertaling" xml:lang="nl"><verdragtekst><kop><titel status="officieel">Internationaal verdrag ter bestrijding van den handel in vrouwen en kinderen.</titel></kop><aanhef><preambule><al>Albani&#xEB;, Duitschland, Oostenrijk, Belgi&#xEB;, Brazili&#xEB;, het Britsche Rijk (met Canada, Australi&#xEB;, Zuid-Afrika, Nieuw-Zeeland en Indi&#xEB;), Chili, China, Columbia, Costa-Rica, Cuba, Estland, Griekenland, Hongarije, Itali&#xEB;, Japan, Letland, Lithauen, Noorwegen, Nederland, Perzi&#xEB;, Polen (met Dantzig), Portugal, Roemeni&#xEB;, Siam, Zweden, Zwitserland en Tsjecho-Slowakije, </al><al>Bezield met den wensch om op meer volledige wijze de bestrijding van den handel in vrouwen en kinderen te verzekeren, welke in de considerans van de regeling van 18 Mei 1904 en van het verdrag van 4 Mei 1910 wordt aangeduid onder den naam van &#x201E;den zoogenaamden handel in vrouwen en meisjes&#x201D;;</al><al>Kennis genomen hebbende van de aanbevelingen neergelegd in de slotakte van de Internationale Conferentie, die bijeengeroepen was door den Raad van den Volkenbond en te Gen&#xE8;ve is bijeengekomen van 30 Juni tot 5 Juli 1921; en </al><al>Besloten hebbende een verdrag te sluiten ter aanvulling van bovengenoemde regeling en verdrag;</al><al>Hebben te dien einde als haar gevolmachtigden benoemd: </al><al><redactie type="vervanging">Zie voor de namen van de gevolmachtigden de Engelse tekst.</redactie></al></preambule><afkondiging><al>die, na mededeeling van hunne volmachten welke in goede orde zijn bevonden, het volgende zijn overeengekomen:</al></afkondiging></aanhef><wettekst><artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Artikel</label><nr status="officieel">1</nr></kop><al>De Hooge Verdragsluitende Partijen komen overeen, voorzoover zij nog geen Partij zijn bij de bovenvermelde regeling van 18 Mei 1904 en het verdrag van 4 Mei 1910, zoo spoedig mogelijk en op de wijze voorzien in bovenbedoelde regeling en verdrag, haar bekrachtigingen van genoemde akten of haar toetredingen tot genoemde akten over te leggen.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Artikel</label><nr status="officieel">2</nr></kop><al>De Hooge Verdragsluitende Partijen komen overeen, alle maatregelen te nemen tot het opsporen en straffen van personen, die zich bezig houden met den handel in kinderen van beide seksen, welk misdrijf moet worden opgevat in den zin van artikel 1 van het verdrag van 4 Mei 1910. </al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Artikel</label><nr status="officieel">3</nr></kop><al>De Hooge Verdragsluitende Partijen komen overeen, de noodige maatregelen te nemen, teneinde strafbaar te stellen de pogingen en, binnen de perken der wet, de voorbereidende handelingen tot de misdrijven bedoeld in de artikelen 1 en 2 van het verdrag van 4 Mei 1910. </al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Artikel</label><nr status="officieel">4</nr></kop><al>De Hooge Verdragsluitende Partijen komen overeen, voorzoover er tusschen haar geen uitleveringsverdragen van kracht zijn, alle maatregelen te nemen, die in haar macht staan, teneinde te geraken tot de uitlevering van personen beschuldigd van of veroordeeld wegens de misdrijven bedoeld in de artikelen 1 en 2 van het verdrag van 4 Mei 1910. </al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Artikel</label><nr status="officieel">5</nr></kop><al>In Paragraaf B van het slotprotokol van het Verdrag van 1910 zullen de woorden &#x201E;twintig jaar&#x201D; vervangen worden door de woorden &#x201E;eenentwintig jaar&#x201D;. </al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Artikel</label><nr status="officieel">6</nr></kop><al>De Hooge Verdragsluitende Partijen komen overeen, ingeval zij nog geen wettelijke of administratieve maatregelen hebben genomen met betrekking tot het verleenen van vergunningen voor en het houden van toezicht op arbeidsbeurzen en plaatsingsbureau's, zoodanige regelingen uit te vaardigen als noodig zijn om de bescherming van vrouwen en kinderen, die werk zoeken in een ander land, te verzekeren. </al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Artikel</label><nr status="officieel">7</nr></kop><al>De Hooge Verdragsluitende Partijen komen overeen, met betrekking tot immigratie en emigratie, zoodanige wettelijke en administratieve maatregelen te nemen als noodig zijn om den handel in vrouwen en kinderen tegen te gaan. In het bijzonder verbinden zij zich om de maatregelen uit te vaardigen noodig voor de bescherming van vrouwen en kinderen, die op landverhuizersschepen reizen, niet alleen bij vertrek en aankomst, maar ook gedurende de reis, en tevens om te zorgen, dat in de spoorwegstations en bij de havens bekendmakingen worden aangeslagen, waarbij vrouwen en kinderen worden gewaarschuwd tegen de gevaren van den vrouwenhandel en waarbij wordt aangegeven, waar men onderkomen en bijstand kan verkrijgen. </al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Artikel</label><nr status="officieel">8</nr></kop><al>Dit verdrag, waarvan zoowel de Fransche als de Engelsche tekst authentiek is, zal den datum dragen van dezen dag en zal geteekend kunnen worden tot op 31 Maart 1922. </al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Artikel</label><nr status="officieel">9</nr></kop><al>Dit Verdrag is onderworpen aan bekrachtiging. Van 1 Januari
1948 af zullen de akten van bekrachtiging worden gezonden aan
de Secretaris-Generaal van de Verenigde Naties, die de ontvangst er
van ter kennis zal brengen van de Leden van de Verenigde Naties
en van de Staten, niet-Leden, aan welke de Secretaris-Generaal een
afschrift van het Verdrag heeft gezonden. De akten van bekrachtiging
zullen worden nedergelegd in het archief van het Secretariaat van
de Verenigde Naties.</al><al>Teneinde te voldoen aan de bepalingen van artikel 18 van het Volkenbondverdrag, zal de Secretaris-Generaal dit verdrag inschrijven, zoodra de nederlegging van de eerste bekrachtiging zal hebben plaats gehad. 
</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Artikel</label><nr status="officieel">10</nr></kop><al>Leden van de Verenigde Naties kunnen tot dit Verdrag toetreden.</al><al>Hetzelfde geldt voor Staten, niet-Leden, ten aanzien waarvan de
Economische en Sociale Raad van de Verenigde Naties zal besluiten
dit Verdrag officieel te hunner kennis te brengen.</al><al>De toetredingen zullen worden medegedeeld aan de Secretaris-Generaal van de Verenigde Naties, die daarvan alle Leden van de
Verenigde Naties en de niet-Leden, aan welke de Secretaris-Generaal
een afschrift van het Verdrag heeft gezonden, in kennis zal stellen.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Artikel</label><nr status="officieel">11</nr></kop><al>Dit verdrag zal voor iedere partij van kracht worden op den datum van de nederlegging van haar bekrachtiging of akte van toetreding. </al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Artikel</label><nr status="officieel">12</nr></kop><al>Dit Verdrag kan worden opgezegd door elke Staat, welke Partij
is, met inachtneming van een opzeggingstermijn van twaalf maanden.</al><al>Opzegging zal geschieden door schriftelijke kennisgeving aan de
Secretaris-Generaal van de Verenigde Naties. Afschriften van zodanige
kennisgeving zullen onmiddellijk door hem worden overgelegd
aan alle Leden van de Verenigde Naties en aan de Staten, niet-Leden,
aan welke de Secretaris-Generaal een afschrift van het Verdrag heeft
gezonden. De opzegging zal van kracht worden &#xE9;&#xE9;n jaar na de datum,
waarop deze aan de Secretaris-Generaal van de Verenigde Naties
werd bericht, en zal alleen gelden ten aanzien van de Mogendheid,
welke de opzegging heeft medegedeeld.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Artikel</label><nr status="officieel">13</nr></kop><al>De Secretaris-Generaal van de Verenigde Naties zal een afzonderlijk
register houden, waaruit zal blijken, wie van de Partijen dit Verdrag
hebben ondertekend, bekrachtigd, tot dit Verdrag zijn toegetreden
of het Verdrag hebben opgezegd. Dit register zal te allen tijde door
elk Lid van de Verenigde Naties, of elke Staat, niet-Lid, aan welke de Secretaris-Generaal een afschrift van het Verdrag heeft gezonden,
kunnen worden geraadpleegd; het zal, overeenkomstig door de Economische
en Sociale Raad van de Verenigde Naties te geven instructies,
zo dikwijls mogelijk worden openbaar gemaakt.</al></artikel></wettekst><wetsluiting status="goed"><slotformulering><al>Gedaan te Gen&#xE8;ve, op den dertigsten September, jaar negentienhonderd eenentwintig, in &#xE9;&#xE9;n exemplaar, dat bewaard zal blijven in de archieven van den Volkenbond. </al></slotformulering></wetsluiting></verdragtekst></verdrag></wetgeving>
  	