<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE wetgeving SYSTEM "http://wetten.overheid.nl/dtd/bwb-plus-meta-1_61w.dtd">
<wetgeving bwb-id="BWBV0004219" dtdversie="2.0" id="10000036939" sleutel="V3378" verdragnummer="004685" soort="verdrag"> 
  
  
  <intitule>Uitvoeringsovereenkomst tussen de Regering van het Koninkrijk der Nederlanden en de Regering van Canada bij de briefwisseling tussen de beide landen, ondertekend op 10 april 1952, houdende een overeenkomst ter bescherming van de rechten van bona fide houders van Canadese effecten</intitule> 
   
  <verdrag tekst="authentiek" xml:lang="en"><verdragtekst>
<kop>
<titel status="officieel">Executive Agreement between the Government of the Kingdom of the Netherlands and the Government of Canada supplementary to the Exchange of Letters between the two countries, signed on April 10, 1952, constituting an agreement to safeguard the rights of bona fide holders of bonds of Canada that have been reported by their Netherlands owners as lost or stolen during World War II</titel>
</kop><vrije-tekst><tekst status="goed"><al>The Government of the Kingdom of the Netherlands and the Government of Canada, desiring to conclude an agreement to further the implementation of the Agreement constituted by the Exchange of Letters between the two countries, signed on April 10, 1952, to safeguard the rights of bona fide holders of bonds of Canada that have been reported by their Netherlands owners as lost or stolen during World War II, agree as follows:</al><al>This Agreement which shall take effect from this date shall apply in the following terms to those bonds listed in the Schedule to the Letter of the Minister of Finance of Canada of April 10, 1952, that are set out in the Schedule to this Agreement (hereinafter referred to as the &#x201C;Schedule&#x201D;):</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>1.</li.nr><al>The duplicate bonds specified in Part III of the Schedule issued in respect of the bonds specified in Part I of the Schedule and the proceeds of redemption of bonds specified in Part II of the Schedule, which duplicate bonds and proceeds of redemption are held in the custody of the Bank of Canada for the Government of The Netherlands for the benefit of the true owners of the original bonds, shall be transferred by the Bank of Canada into the custody of the Government of The Netherlands for the benefit of the true owners of the original bonds.</al></li><li><li.nr>2.</li.nr><al>The duplicate bonds are issued without coupons and any interest payable on coupons maturing on or before September 15, 1966 shall be paid only upon presentation of coupons belonging to the original bonds.</al></li><li><li.nr>3.</li.nr><al>The Government of The Netherlands shall attempt to find the original bonds specified in Parts I and II of the Schedule and, except to the extent that the Bank of Canada otherwise specifies, the Government of The Netherlands shall give to the Bank of Canada any information it receives concerning the loss, theft or destruction of each bond, the whereabouts of each bond and the facts relied upon by all claimants to ownership of each bond.</al></li><li><li.nr>4.</li.nr><al>If any such original bond comes into the possession, ownership or control of the Government of The Netherlands, the Government of Canada, or the Bank of Canada, the Government of The Netherlands shall deliver or cause to be delivered to the Bank of Canada</al><al>the corresponding duplicate bond for cancellation by the Bank of Canada and, where applicable, the original bond, and the Bank of Canada shall cancel or otherwise deal with such duplicate bonds or original bonds as it sees fit.</al></li><li><li.nr>5.</li.nr><al>The Government of The Netherlands shall, upon the transfer of duplicate bonds and redemption proceeds described in Clause 1 hereof, give an undertaking to the Bank of Canada in the following terms:</al><lijst><li><al>The Government of The Netherlands shall indemnify and save harmless the Government of Canada and the Bank of Canada against and from all loss, costs, damages, expenses, legal fees and claims, whether litigated or not, that may result directly or indirectly from the issue or delivery of duplicate bonds or with respect to bonds exchanged therefor or with respect to delivery or payment of redemption proceeds, or any subsequent transactions or payments relating to or induced by the existence of the duplicate bonds or the delivery or payment of the redemption proceeds.</al></li></lijst></li></lijst></tekst></vrije-tekst><wetsluiting status="goed"><slotformulering><al>IN WITNESS WHEREOF the undersigned, duly authorized thereto, have signed this Agreement and have affixed thereto their seals.</al><al>DONE, in duplicate, this eighth day of February, nineteen hundred and sixty-three at Ottawa.</al><al><nadruk type="cur">For the Government of the Kingdom of The Netherlands:</nadruk></al><al>(sd.) A. H. J. LOVINK</al><al>L.S.</al><al><nadruk type="cur">For the Government of Canada:</nadruk></al><al>(sd.) GEORGE NOWLAN</al><al>L.S.</al></slotformulering></wetsluiting></verdragtekst><verdragtekst><kop><titel status="officieel">SCHEDULE</titel></kop><vrije-tekst><tekst status="goed"><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li>
<li.nr>I.</li.nr><al>Bonds of Canada for which duplicates have been issued.</al><al><nadruk type="cur">3% Canada Perpetual Loan 1936</nadruk></al><table><tgroup cols="3"><colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="*"/><colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="*"/><colspec colname="col3" colnum="3" colwidth="*"/><tbody><row><entry colname="col1"><al>Pl </al></entry><entry colname="col2"><al>E</al></entry><entry colname="col3"><al> 2583</al></entry></row><row><entry colname="col1"><al>Pl</al></entry><entry colname="col2"><al> E</al></entry><entry colname="col3"><al>6439</al></entry></row><row><entry colname="col1"><al>Pl</al></entry><entry colname="col2"><al> E</al></entry><entry colname="col3"><al>39767</al></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></li><li>
<li.nr>II.</li.nr><al>Bonds of Canada that have matured or been called for redemption and whose proceeds have been paid into a Special Account in the Bank of Canada.</al><al><nadruk type="cur">5% Canada External Loan 1922/52</nadruk></al><table><tgroup cols="2"><colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="*"/><colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="*"/><tbody><row><entry colname="col1"><al>17199</al></entry><entry colname="col2"><al>1 X $ 1000</al></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table><al><nadruk type="cur">3% Canada External Loan 1938/68</nadruk></al><table><tgroup cols="2"><colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="*"/><colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="*"/><tbody><row><entry colname="col1"><al>E 34446</al></entry><entry colname="col2"><al>1 X $ 1000</al></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></li><li><li.nr>III.</li.nr><al>Duplicate bonds of Canada issued in replacement of bonds listed in Part I of this Schedule.</al><table><tgroup cols="3"><colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="1.25*"/><colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="1.00*"/><colspec colname="col3" colnum="3" colwidth="1.50*"/><tbody><row><entry colname="col1"><al>PIE</al></entry><entry colname="col2"><al> 61564</al></entry><entry colname="col3"><al> (in replacement of Pl E 2583)</al></entry></row><row><entry colname="col1"><al>PIE</al></entry><entry colname="col2"><al> 61565</al></entry><entry colname="col3"><al> (in replacement of Pl E 6439)</al></entry></row><row><entry colname="col1"><al>PIE</al></entry><entry colname="col2"><al> 61566</al></entry><entry colname="col3"><al> (in replacement of Pl E 39767)</al></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></li></lijst></tekst></vrije-tekst></verdragtekst></verdrag> 
</wetgeving>
  	