<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE wetgeving SYSTEM "http://wetten.overheid.nl/dtd/bwb-plus-meta-1_61w.dtd">
<wetgeving bwb-id="BWBV0005357" dtdversie="2.0" id="10000048319" verdragnummer="007737" soort="verdrag"> 
  
  <alias-titels><alias-titel>European Convention on the Equivalence of Periods of University Study</alias-titel></alias-titels>
  <intitule>Europees Verdrag inzake de gelijkstelling van tijdvakken van universitaire studie</intitule>
  
  <verdrag status="goed" tekst="authentiek" xml:lang="en"><verdragtekst>
<kop>
<titel status="officieel">European Convention on the Equivalence of Periods of University Study</titel>
</kop><aanhef><preambule><al>The Governments signatory hereto, being Members of the Council of Europe,</al><al>Having regard to the European Convention on the equivalence of diplomas leading to admission to universities, signed in Paris on the 11th December, 1953;</al><al>Having regard to the European Cultural Convention, signed in Paris on the 19th December, 1954;</al><al>Considering that an important contribution would be made to European understanding if a larger number of students, among others students of modern languages, could spend a period of study abroad and if examinations passed and courses taken by such students during the period of study could be recognised by the home university;</al><al>Considering further that the recognition of periods of study spent abroad would contribute to the solution of the problem raised by the shortage of highly qualified scientists,</al></preambule><afkondiging><al>Have agreed als follows:</al></afkondiging></aanhef><wettekst><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">1</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>For the purposes of the present Convention, Contracting Parties shall be divided into categories according to whether the authority competent to deal with matters pertaining to equivalences in their territories is:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>the State;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>the university;</al></li><li><li.nr>(c)</li.nr><al>the State or university as the case may be.</al></li></lijst><al>Each Contracting Party shall inform the Secretary-General of the Council of Europe which is the competent authority in its territory to deal with matters pertaining to equivalences.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>The term &#x201C;universities&#x201D; shall denote:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>universities, and</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>institutions regarded as being similar in character to universities by the Contracting Party in whose territory they are situated.</al></li></lijst></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">2</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Contracting Parties falling within category <nadruk type="cur">(a)</nadruk> of Article 1, paragraph 1, shall recognise a period of study spent by a student of modern languages in a university of another member country of the Council of Europe as equivalent to a similar period spent in his home university provided that the authorities of the first-mentioned university have issued to such a student a certificate attesting that he has completed the said period of study to their satisfaction.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al> The length of the period of study referred to in the preceding paragraph shall be determined by the competent authorities of the Contracting Party concerned.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">3</nr>
</kop><al>Contracting Parties falling within category <nadruk type="cur">(a)</nadruk> of Article 1, paragraph 1, shall consider the means to be adopted in order to recognise a period of study spent in a university of another member country of the Council of Europe by students of disciplines other than modern languages and especially by students of pure and applied sciences.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">4</nr>
</kop><al>Contracting Parties falling within category <nadruk type="cur">(a)</nadruk> of Article 1, paragraph 1, shall endeavour to determine, by means of unilateral or bilateral arrangements, the conditions under which an examination passed or a course taken by a student during a period of study in a university of another member country of the Council of Europe may be considered as equivalent to a similar examination passed or a course taken by a student in his home university.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">5</nr>
</kop><al>Contracting Parties falling within category <nadruk type="cur">(b)</nadruk> of Article 1, paragraph 1, shall transmit the text of the present Convention to the authorities of the universities situated in their territories and shall encourage the favourable consideration and application by them of the principles mentioned in Articles 2, 3 and 4 above.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">6</nr>
</kop><al>Contracting Parties falling within category <nadruk type="cur">(c)</nadruk> of Article 1, paragraph 1, shall apply the provisions of Articles 2, 3 and 4 in respect of those universities for which the State is the competent authority in the matters dealt with in this Convention, and shall apply the provisions of Article 5 in respect of those universities which are themselves the competent authorities in these matters.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">7</nr>
</kop><al>Each Contracting Party shall, within a year of the coming into force of the present Convention, furnish the Secretary-General of the Council of Europe with a written statement on the measures taken to implement Articles 2, 3, 4, 5 and 6.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">8</nr>
</kop><al>The Secretary-General of the Council of Europe shall communicate to the other Contracting Parties the information received from each of them in accordance with Article 7 and shall keep the Committee of Ministers informed of the progress made in the implementation of this Convention.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">9</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>The present Convention shall be open to the signature of the Members of the Council of Europe. It shall be ratified. The instruments of ratification shall be deposited with the Secretary-General of the Council of Europe.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>The Convention shall come into force as soon as three instruments of ratification have been deposited.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>As regards any Signatory ratifying subsequently, the Convention shall come into force at the date of the deposit of its instrument of ratification.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr><al>The Secretary-General of the Council of Europe shall notify all the Members of the Council of Europe of the entry into force of the Convention, the names of the Contracting Parties which have ratified it and the deposit of all instruments of ratification which may be effected subsequently.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">5</lidnr><al>Any Contracting Party may specify the territories to which the provisions of the present Convention shall apply by addressing to the Secretary-General of the Council of Europe a declaration which shall be communicated by the latter to all the other Contracting Parties.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">10</nr>
</kop><al>The Committee of Ministers of the Council of Europe may invite any State which is not a Member of the Council to accede to the present Convention. Any State so invited may accede by depositing its instrument of accession with the Secretary-General of the Council, who shall notify all the Contracting Parties thereof. Any acceding State shall be considered a member country of the Council of Europe for the purposes of the present Convention. As regards any acceding State, the present Convention shall come into force on the date of the deposit of its instrument of accession.</al></artikel></wettekst><wetsluiting status="goed"><slotformulering><al>In witness whereof the undersigned, duly authorised thereto by their respective Governments, have signed the present Convention.</al><al>Done at Paris, this 15th day of December, 1956, in the English and French languages, both texts being equally authoritative, in a single copy which shall remain deposited in the archives of the Council of Europe. The Secretary-General shall transmit certified copies to each of the signatory and acceding Governments.</al></slotformulering></wetsluiting></verdragtekst>

</verdrag><verdrag status="goed" tekst="vertaling" xml:lang="nl"><verdragtekst>
<kop>
<titel status="officieel">Europees Verdrag inzake de gelijkstelling van tijdvakken van universitaire studie</titel>
</kop><aanhef><preambule><al>De Regeringen die dit Verdrag hebben ondertekend, Leden van de Raad van Europa,</al><al>Gelet op het Europees Verdrag betreffende de gelijkstelling van diploma's voor toelating tot universiteiten, ondertekend te Parijs op 11 december 1953,</al><al>Gelet op het Europees Cultureel Verdrag, ondertekend te Parijs op 19 december 1954,</al><al>Overwegende, dat een belangrijke bijdrage zou worden geleverd tot een goede verstandhouding tussen de volkeren van Europa, indien een groter aantal studenten, onder andere studenten in de moderne talen, een zekere studietijd in het buitenland zou kunnen doorbrengen en indien de door die studenten tijdens die studietijd afgelegde examens en gevolgde cursussen door hun eigen universiteit zouden kunnen worden erkend,</al><al>Voorts overwegende, dat de erkenning van in het buitenland doorgebrachte studietijden zou bijdragen tot de oplossing van het probleem dat is ontstaan door het tekort aan exact-wetenschappelijk geschoolden van hoog niveau,</al></preambule><afkondiging><al>Zijn het volgende overeengekomen:</al></afkondiging></aanhef><wettekst><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">1</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>In dit Verdrag worden de Verdragsluitende Partijen in groepen verdeeld, al naar de autoriteit die op haar gebied bevoegd is ten aanzien van aangelegenheden welke betrekking hebben op gelijkstelling is:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>de Staat;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>de universiteit;</al></li><li><li.nr>(c)</li.nr><al>de Staat of de universiteit, al naar het geval zich voordoet.</al></li></lijst><al>Iedere Verdragsluitende Partij deelt de Secretaris-Generaal van de Raad van Europa mede, welke autoriteit op haar grondgebied bevoegd is ten aanzien van aangelegenheden welke betrekking hebben op gelijkstelling.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Onder &#x201E;universiteiten&#x201D; worden verstaan:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>universiteiten, en</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>instellingen welke door de Verdragsluitende Partij binnen welker grondgebied zij zijn gelegen worden geacht van dezelfde aard te zijn als een universiteit.</al></li></lijst></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">2</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>De Verdragsluitende Partijen welke behoren tot groep <nadruk type="cur">(a)</nadruk> van artikel 1, lid 1, stellen een studietijd die een student in de moderne talen heeft doorgebracht aan een universiteit van een ander land, lid van de Raad van Europa, gelijk met eenzelfde studietijd aan zijn eigen universiteit, mits de autoriteiten van eerstgenoemde universiteit aan die student een verklaring hebben uitgereikt waaruit blijkt dat hij die studietijd tot hun tevredenheid heeft voltooid.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>De duur van de in het voorgaande lid bedoelde studietijd wordt bepaald door de bevoegde autoriteiten van de betrokken Verdragsluitende Partij.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">3</nr>
</kop><al>De Verdragsluitende Partijen welke behoren tot groep <nadruk type="cur">(a)</nadruk> van artikel 1, lid 1, zullen de mogelijkheden onderzoeken om te geraken tot erkenning van een studietijd welke is doorgebracht aan een universiteit van een ander land, lid van de Raad van Europa, door studenten van andere studierichtingen dan die der moderne talen en in het bijzonder door studenten in de zuivere en toegepaste exacte wetenschappen.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">4</nr>
</kop><al>De Verdragsluitende Partijen welke behoren tot groep <nadruk type="cur">(a)</nadruk> van artikel 1, lid 1, zullen trachten door middel van unilaterale of bilaterale regelingen de voorwaarden te bepalen waarop een door een student tijdens een studietijd, doorgebracht aan een universiteit van een ander land, lid van de Raad van Europa, afgelegd examen of gevolgde cursus kan worden geacht gelijk te staan met een dergelijk examen of een dergelijke cursus, afgelegd of gevolgd aan zijn eigen universiteit.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">5</nr>
</kop><al>De Verdragsluitende Partijen welke behoren tot groep <nadruk type="cur">(b)</nadruk> van artikel 1, lid 1, zullen de tekst van dit Verdrag doen toekomen aan de autoriteiten van de op hun grondgebied gelegen universiteiten en zoveel mogelijk bevorderen, dat die autoriteiten de in de artikelen 2, 3 en 4 neergelegde beginselen in welwillende overweging nemen en in toepassing brengen.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">6</nr>
</kop><al>De Verdragsluitende Partijen welke behoren tot groep <nadruk type="cur">(c)</nadruk> van artikel 1, lid 1, passen de bepalingen van de artikelen 2, 3 en 4 toe op die universiteiten voor wie de Staat de bevoegde autoriteit is ten aanzien van de aangelegenheden welke het onderwerp vormen van dit Verdrag, en passen de bepalingen van artikel 5 toe ten aanzien van die universiteiten die zelf de bevoegde autoriteit in dit opzicht vormen.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">7</nr>
</kop><al>Iedere Verdragsluitende Partij zal binnen een jaar na de inwerkingtreding van dit Verdrag aan de Secretaris-Generaal van de Raad van Europa een overzicht doen toekomen van de maatregelen welke zij heeft genomen ter uitvoering van de artikelen 2, 3, 4, 5 en 6.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">8</nr>
</kop><al>De Secretaris-Generaal van de Raad van Europa deelt aan de andere Verdragsluitende Partijen de inlichtingen mede, welke hij van elk van hen heeft ontvangen overeenkomstig het bepaalde in artikel 7, en houdt het Comit&#xE9; van Ministers op de hoogte van de voortgang welke is gemaakt bij de tenuitvoerlegging van dit Verdrag.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">9</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Dit Verdrag staat ter ondertekening open voor de Leden van de Raad van Europa. Het dient te worden bekrachtigd. De akten van bekrachtiging worden nedergelegd bij de Secretaris-Generaal van de Raad van Europa.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Het Verdrag treedt in werking zodra drie akten van bekrachtiging zijn nedergelegd.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>Ten aanzien van een ondertekenende Staat die het Verdrag op een later tijdstip bekrachtigt treedt het Verdrag in werking op het ogenblik waarop die Staat zijn akte van bekrachtiging nederlegt.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr><al>De Secretaris-Generaal van de Raad van Europa stelt alle Leden van de Raad van Europa in kennis van de inwerkingtreding van het Verdrag, van de namen van de Verdragsluitende Partijen die het hebben bekrachtigd en van elke op een later tijdstip plaatsvindende nederlegging van een akte van bekrachtiging.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">5</lidnr><al> Iedere Verdragsluitende Partij kan door middel van een verklaring tegenover de Secretaris-Generaal van de Raad van Europa de gebieden aangeven waarop de bepalingen van dit Verdrag van toepassing zullen zijn. De Secretaris-Generaal doet van deze verklaring mededeling aan alle andere Verdragsluitende Partijen.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">10</nr>
</kop><al>Het Comit&#xE9; van Ministers van de Raad van Europa kan iedere Staat welke geen lid is van de Raad uitnodigen tot dit Verdrag toe te treden. ledere aldus uitgenodigde Staat kan toetreden door nederlegging van zijn akte van toetreding bij de Secretaris-Generaal, die daarvan mededeling doet aan alle Verdragsluitende Partijen. Voor de toepassing van dit Verdrag zal iedere toetredende Staat worden gelijkgesteld met een lid van de Raad van Europa. Ten aanzien van iedere toetredende Staat treedt dit Verdrag in werking op het ogenblik waarop die Staat zijn akte van toetreding nederlegt.</al></artikel></wettekst><wetsluiting status="goed"><slotformulering><al>Ten blijke waarvan de ondergetekenden, daartoe behoorlijk gemachtigd door hun onderscheidene Regeringen, dit Verdrag hebben ondertekend.</al><al>Gedaan te Parijs, de 15de december 1956, in de Engelse en de Franse taal, zijnde beide teksten gelijkelijk gezaghebbend, in een enkel exemplaar dat zal worden bewaard in het archief van de Raad van Europa. De Secretaris-Generaal zal gewaarmerkte afschriften hiervan doen toekomen aan iedere ondertekenende en toetredende Regering.</al></slotformulering></wetsluiting></verdragtekst></verdrag></wetgeving>
  	