<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE wetgeving SYSTEM "http://wetten.overheid.nl/dtd/bwb-plus-meta-1_61w.dtd">
<wetgeving bwb-id="BWBV0001128" dtdversie="2.0" id="10000010379" verdragnummer="005250" soort="verdrag">
  <intitule>Verdrag tot oprichting van het Europees Bureau voor Communicatie (EBC)</intitule>
  
  
  <verdrag tekst="authentiek" xml:lang="en">
				
				
				
				
				
				
				
				
				
			<verdragtekst>
					<kop>
						<titel status="officieel">Convention for the Establishment of the European Radiocommunications Office (ERO)</titel>
					</kop>
					<aanhef>
						<preambule>
							<al>The States Parties to this Convention, hereinafter referred to as the &#x201C;Contracting Parties&#x201D;;</al>
							<al>Acknowledging the growing demand on the radio frequency spectrum and the need to make the most efficient use of this scarce natural resource;</al>
							<al>Underlining therefore that the current mechanisms set up by the European Conference of Postal and Telecommunications Administrations, hereinafter referred to as the &#x201C;CEPT&#x201D;, should be strengthened and equipped with the necessary permanent resources to undertake long-term analyses of frequency requirements aiming at promoting the most efficient use of the frequency spectrum, taking timely account of service and user requirements against the background of industrial development and the development of standards;</al>
							<al>Determined to establish a permanant non-profit-making institution, to assist the European Radiocommunications Committee of CEPT, hereinafter referred to as the &#x201C;ERC&#x201D;, with its tasks relating to the development of radiocommunications policies and the coordination of frequency regulatory and technical matters concerning radiocommunications, including space communications;</al>
							
						</preambule>
					<afkondiging><al>Have agreed as follows:</al></afkondiging></aanhef>
					<wettekst>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Article</label>
								<nr status="officieel">1</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">Establishment of ERO</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
								<al>A European Radiocommunications Office, hereinafter referred to as the "ERO", is hereby established.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
								<al>The Headquarters of the ERO shall be in Copenhagen, Denmark.</al>
							</lid>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Article</label>
								<nr status="officieel">2</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">Purpose of the ERO</titel>
							</kop>
							<al>The ERO shall be a centre of expertise in radiocommunications to assist and advise the ERC.</al>
							
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Article</label>
								<nr status="officieel">3</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">Functions of the ERO</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
								<al>The functions of the ERO shall be:</al>
							<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>1.</li.nr><al>to provide a centre of expertise which shall act as a focal point, identifying problem areas and new possibilities in the radiocommunications field and to advise the ERC accordingly;</al></li><li><li.nr>2.</li.nr><al>to draft long-term plans for future use of the radio frequency spectrum on a European level;</al></li><li><li.nr>3.</li.nr><al>to liaise with the national frequency management authorities;</al></li><li><li.nr>4.</li.nr><al>to coordinate actions and provide guidance for research studies;</al></li><li><li.nr>5.</li.nr><al>to conduct consultations on specific topics or parts of the frequency spectrum;</al></li><li><li.nr>6.</li.nr><al>to assist the ERC or its Working Groups in the arrangement of specific consultation meetings;</al></li><li><li.nr>7.</li.nr><al>to apply criteria for attendance at consultation meetings;</al></li><li><li.nr>8.</li.nr><al>to maintain a record of important ERC actions and of the implementation of relevant CEPT Recommendations and Decisions;</al></li><li><li.nr>9.</li.nr><al>to provide the ERC with status reports at regular intervals; and</al></li><li><li.nr>10.</li.nr><al>to liaise with the European Communities and with the European Free Trade Association.</al></li></lijst></lid>
							
							
							
							
							
							
							
							
							
							
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
								<al>In carrying out the above functions related to consultation meetings, the ERO shall develop, and maintain up-to-date procedures designed to enable organizations in Europe with a relevant interest in the use of radiocommunications - including government departments, public radiocommunications operators, manufacturers, users and private network operators, service providers, research establishments and standards-making bodies or organizations representing groups of such parties - to subscribe to relevant information on a regular basis and to participate in these consultation meetings in an equitable manner having regard to their particular interests.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
								<al>In addition to the functions mentioned in paragraph 1 the ERO shall organize, normally on an annual basis, a meeting open to organizations mentioned in paragraph 2 to provide an opportunity to discuss the activities and the future work programmes of the ERC and the ERO.</al>
							</lid>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Article</label>
								<nr status="officieel">4</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">Legal Status and Privileges</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
								<al>The ERO shall have legal personality. The ERO shall enjoy full capacity necessary for the exercise of its functions and the achievement of its purposes, and may in particular:</al>
							<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>1.</li.nr><al>enter into contracts;</al></li><li><li.nr>2.</li.nr><al>acquire, lease, hold and dispose of movable and immovable property;</al></li><li><li.nr>3.</li.nr><al>be a party to legal proceedings; and</al></li><li><li.nr>4.</li.nr><al>conclude agreements with States or international organizations.</al></li></lijst></lid>
							
							
							
							
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
								<al>The Head of Office and the Staff of the ERO shall have privileges and immunities in Denmark as defined in an Agreement concerning the Headquarters of the ERO between the ERO and the Government of Denmark.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
								<al>Other countries may grant similar privileges and immunities in support of the ERO's activities in such countries, in particular with regard to immunity from legal process in respect of words spoken and written and all acts performed by the Head of Office and the Staff of the ERO in their official capacity.</al>
							</lid>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Article</label>
								<nr status="officieel">5</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">Organs of the ERO</titel>
							</kop>
							<al>The ERO shall consist of a Council and a Head of Office, assisted by a Staff.</al>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Article</label>
								<nr status="officieel">6</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">The Council</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
								<al>The Council shall consist of representatives of the respective Radiocommunications Regulatory Administrations of all the Contracting Parties.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
								<al>The Chairman of the ERC shall be the Chairman of the Council. If the Chairman of the ERC is from a country that is not Party to this Convention the Council shall elect a Chairman from its members. The Chairman shall have authority to act on behalf of the Council.</al>
								
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
								<al>Representatives of the Commission of the European Communities and of the Secretariat of the European Free Trade Association may participate in the Council with the status of Observer.</al>
							</lid>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Article</label>
								<nr status="officieel">7</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">Functions of the Council</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
								<al>The Council shall be the supreme decision-making body of the ERO and shall in particular:</al>
							<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>1.</li.nr><al>determine ERO's policy in technical and administrative matters;</al></li><li><li.nr>2.</li.nr><al>approve the work programme, the budget and the accounts;</al></li><li><li.nr>3.</li.nr><al>determine the number of staff;</al></li><li><li.nr>4.</li.nr><al>appoint the Head of Office and the Staff;</al></li><li><li.nr>5.</li.nr><al>enter into contracts and agreements on behalf of the ERO;</al></li><li><li.nr>6.</li.nr><al>adopt amendments to the Convention in accordance with Articles 15 and 20; and</al></li><li><li.nr>7.</li.nr><al>take all measures necessary for the fulfilment of the purposes of the ERO within the framework of the Convention.</al></li></lijst></lid>
							
							
							
							
							
							
							
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
								<al>The Council shall establish all necessary rules for the proper functioning of the ERO and its organs.</al>
							</lid>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Article</label>
								<nr status="officieel">8</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">Voting Rules</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
								<al>Decisions of the Council shall be reached by consensus as far as possible. If consensus cannot be reached a decision shall be taken by a two-thirds majority of the weighted votes cast.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
								<al>The weighting of the individual votes of the Council shall be in accordance with Annex A.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
								<al>Proposals to amend this Convention, including the Annexes, shall be considered only if they are supported by at least 25% of the total weighted votes of all Contracting Parties.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr>
								<al>For all decisions of the Council, a quorum must exist at the time when the decision is made which:</al>
							<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>1.</li.nr><al>for decisions relating to amendments to the Convention and its Annexes, is equivalent to at least two thirds of the total weighted votes of all Contracting Parties;</al></li><li><li.nr>2.</li.nr><al>for all other decisions, is equivalent to at least one half of the total weighted votes of all Contracting Parties.</al></li></lijst></lid>
							
							
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">5</lidnr>
								<al>Observers to the Council may participate in the discussions but shall not have the right to vote.</al>
							</lid>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Article</label>
								<nr status="officieel">9</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">Head of Office and Staff</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
								<al>The Head of Office shall act as the legal representative of the ERO and shall have the authority, within limits agreed by the Council, to enter into contracts on behalf of the ERO. The Head of Office may delegate this authority, in whole or in part, to the Deputy Head of Office.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
								<al>The Head of Office shall be responsible for the proper execution of all internal and external activities of the ERO in accordance with this Convention, the Headquarters Agreement, the work programme, the budget, and directives and guidelines given by the Council.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
								<al>A set of Staff Rules shall be established by the Council.</al>
							</lid>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Article</label>
								<nr status="officieel">10</nr>
							</kop>
							<al>A work programme for the ERO covering a three year period shall each year be established by the Council on the basis of a proposal from the ERC. The first year of this programme shall contain sufficient detail to enable the annual budget of the ERO to be established.</al>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Article</label>
								<nr status="officieel">11</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">Budgeting and Accounting</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid><lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>The financial year of the ERO shall run from the 1st of January to
the 31st of December following.</al></lid><lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
								<al>The Head of Office shall be responsible for preparing the annual budget and annual accounts for the ERO and submitting them for consideration and approval as appropriate by the Council.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
								<al>The budget shall be prepared taking into account the requirements of the work programme established in accordance with Article 10. The timetable for submitting and approving the budget, in advance of the year to which it applies, shall be determined by the Council.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr>
								<al>A set of detailed financial regulations shall be established by the Council. They shall, inter alia, contain provisions about the timetable for the submission and approval of the annual accounts of the ERO and provisions concerning the audit of the accounts.</al>
							</lid>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Article</label>
								<nr status="officieel">12</nr>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
								<al>The capital expenditure and the current operating expenses of the ERO, excluding costs related to Council meetings, shall be borne by the Contracting Parties, who shall share the costs on the basis of the contributory units in accordance with the table at Annex A, which is an integral part of this Convention.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
								<al>This shall not preclude the ERO, after decision by the Council, from carrying out work for third parties on a cost-recovery basis.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
								<al>Costs related to Council meetings shall be borne by the Radiocommunications Regulatory Administration of the country in which the meeting takes place. Travel and subsistence expenses shall be borne by the authorities represented.</al>
							</lid>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Article</label>
								<nr status="officieel">13</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">Contracting Parties</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
								<al>A State becomes a Contracting Party to this Convention either by the procedure of Article 14 or by the procedure of Article 15.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
								<al>On a State becoming a Contracting Party to this Convention, the contributory unit referred to in Annex A, as amended in accordance with article 15, shall apply.</al>
							</lid>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Article</label>
								<nr status="officieel">14</nr>
							<titel status="officieel">Signature</titel></kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
								<al>Any State whose Telecommunications Administration is a Member of CEPT may become a Contracting Party by:</al>
							<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>1.</li.nr><al>signature without reservation as to ratification, acceptance or approval, or</al></li><li><li.nr>2.</li.nr><al>signature subject to ratification, acceptance or approval, followed by ratification, acceptance or approval.</al></li></lijst></lid>
							
							
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
								<al>This Convention shall be open for signature as of the 23rd of June 1993 until it enters into force, and shall thereafter remain open for accession.</al>
							</lid>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Article</label>
								<nr status="officieel">15</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">Accession</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
								<al>This Convention shall be open for accession by any State whose Telecommunications Administration is a Member of CEPT.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
								<al>After consultation with the acceding State, the Council shall adopt the necessary amendments to Annex A. Notwithstanding paragraph 2 of Article 20, such amendment shall enter into force on the first day of the second month following the date on which the Government of Denmark has received the instrument of accession of that State.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
								<al>The instrument of accession shall express the consent of the acceding State with the adopted amendments of Annex A.</al>
							</lid>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Article</label>
								<nr status="officieel">16</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">Entry into Force</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
								<al>This Convention shall enter into force on the first day of the second month following the date on which the Government of Denmark has received sufficient signatures and, if required, instruments of ratification, acceptance or approval from Contracting Parties, so as to ensure that at least 80% of the maximum possible number of contributory units referred to in Annex A have been committed.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
								<al>After entry into force of this Convention each subsequent Contracting Party shall be bound by its provisions including amendments in force as from the first day of the second month following the date on which the Government of Denmark has received that party's instrument of ratification, acceptance, approval or accession.</al>
							</lid>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Article</label>
								<nr status="officieel">17</nr>
							<titel status="officieel">Denunciation</titel></kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
								<al>After this Convention has been in force for two years, any Contracting Party may denounce it by giving notice in writing to the Government of Denmark, who shall notify this denunciation to the Council, the Contracting Parties and the Head of Office.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
								<al>The denunciation shall take effect at the expiry of the next full financial year as specified in Article 11, paragraph 1, following the date of receipt of the notice of denunciation by the Government of Denmark.</al>
							</lid>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Article</label>
								<nr status="officieel">18</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">Rights and Obligations of the Contracting Parties</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
								<al>Nothing in this Convention shall interfere with the sovereign right of each Contracting Party to regulate its own telecommunications.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
								<al>Each Contracting Party which is a Member State of the European Economic Community will apply this Convention in accordance with its obligations under the Treaty establishing the European Economic Community.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
								<al>No reservation may be made to this Convention.</al>
							</lid>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Article</label>
								<nr status="officieel">19</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">Settlement of Disputes</titel>
							</kop>
							<al>Any dispute concerning the interpretation or application of this Convention and its Annexes which is not settled by the good offices of the Council, shall be submitted by the parties concerned to arbitration in accordance with Annex B, which is an integral part of this Convention.</al>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Article</label>
								<nr status="officieel">20</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">Amendments</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
								<al>The Council may adopt amendments to the Convention subject to confirmation in writing by all Contracting Parties.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
								<al>The amendments shall enter into force for all Contracting Parties on the first day of the third month after the Government of Denmark has notified the Contracting Parties of the receipt of notifications of ratification, acceptance or approval from all Contracting Parties.</al>
							</lid>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Article</label>
								<nr status="officieel">21</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">Depositary</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
								<al>The original of this Convention, with subsequent amendments, and instruments of ratification, acceptance or approval or accession shall be deposited in the archives of the Government of Denmark.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
								<al>The Government of Denmark shall provide a certified copy of the Convention and the text of any amendment as adopted by the Council, to all States that have signed or acceded the Convention and to the President in Office of CEPT. Copies shall further be sent for information to the Secretary-General of the International Telecommunication Union, to the Liaison Office of CEPT, to the President of the Commission of the European Communities and to the Secretary-General of the European Free Trade Association.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
								<al>The Government of Denmark shall notify all States that have signed or acceded the Convention and the President in Office of CEPT, of all signatures, ratifications, acceptances, approvals and denunciations, as well as of the entry into force of the Convention and of each amendment. The Government of Denmark shall further notify all States that have signed or acceded to the Convention and the President in Office of CEPT of the entry into force of each accession.</al>
							</lid>
						</artikel>
					</wettekst>
					<wetsluiting status="goed">
						<slotformulering>
							<al>IN WITNESS WHEREOF the undersigned representatives, having been duly authorised thereto, have signed this Convention.</al>
							<al>DONE at The Hague this 23rd day of June 1993 in a single copy in the English, French and German languages, each text being equally authentic.</al>
							
						</slotformulering>
					</wetsluiting>
				</verdragtekst><verdragtekst>
					<kop>
						<label>Annex</label>
						<nr status="officieel">A</nr>
						<titel status="officieel">Contributory Units to be Used as a Basis for Financial Contribution and in Weighted Voting</titel>
					</kop>
					
					<vrije-tekst>
						<tekst status="goed">
							
						<table frame="all">
								<tgroup align="left" char="" charoff="50" cols="3" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
									<tbody valign="top">
										<row rowsep="1">
											<entry colsep="1" morerows="0" rotate="0" rowsep="1">
												<al>25 Units:</al>
											</entry>
											<entry colsep="1" morerows="0" rotate="0" rowsep="1">
												<al>France</al>
												<al>Germany </al><al>Italy</al>
											</entry>
											<entry colsep="1" morerows="0" rotate="0" rowsep="1">
												<al>Spain </al><al>United Kingdom</al>
											</entry>
										</row>
										<row rowsep="1">
											<entry colsep="1" morerows="0" rotate="0" rowsep="1">
												<al>15 Units:</al>
											</entry>
											<entry colsep="1" morerows="0" rotate="0" rowsep="1">
												<al>Switzerland</al>
											</entry>
											<entry colsep="1" morerows="0" rotate="0" rowsep="1"/>
										</row>
										<row rowsep="1">
											<entry colsep="1" morerows="0" rotate="0" rowsep="1">
												<al>10 Units:</al>
											</entry>
											<entry colsep="1" morerows="0" rotate="0" rowsep="1">
												<al>Austria</al>
												<al>Belgium</al>
												<al>Denmark</al>
												<al>Finland</al>
												<al>Greece </al><al>Luxembourg</al>
											</entry>
											<entry colsep="1" morerows="0" rotate="0" rowsep="1">
												<al>Netherlands</al>
												<al>Norway</al>
												<al>Portugal</al>
												<al>Sweden </al><al>Turkey</al>
											</entry>
										</row>
										<row rowsep="1">
											<entry colsep="1" morerows="0" rotate="0" rowsep="1">
												<al>5 Units:</al>
											</entry>
											<entry colsep="1" morerows="0" rotate="0" rowsep="1">
												<al>Ireland</al>
											</entry>
											<entry colsep="1" morerows="0" rotate="0" rowsep="1"/>
										</row>
										<row rowsep="1">
											<entry colsep="1" morerows="0" rotate="0" rowsep="1">
												<al>1 Unit:</al>
											</entry>
											<entry colsep="1" morerows="0" rotate="0" rowsep="1">
												<al>Albania</al>
												<al>Bulgaria</al>
												<al>Czechia</al>
												<al>Croatia</al>
												<al>Cyprus</al>
												<al>Hungary</al>
												<al>Iceland</al>
												<al>Latvia</al><al>Liechtenstein </al><al>Lithuania</al>
											</entry>
											<entry colsep="1" morerows="0" rotate="0" rowsep="1">
												<al>Malta</al>
												<al>Moldova</al>
												<al>Monaco</al>
												<al>Poland</al>
												<al>Romania</al>
												<al>San Marino</al>
												<al>Slovenia </al><al>Vatican City</al>
											</entry>
										</row>
									</tbody>
								</tgroup>
							</table></tekst>
					</vrije-tekst>
				</verdragtekst><verdragtekst>
					<kop>
						<label>Annex</label>
						<nr status="officieel">B</nr>
						<titel status="officieel">Arbitration Procedure</titel>
					</kop>
					<wettekst>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<nr status="officieel">1</nr>
							</kop>
							
							<al>For the purposes of adjudicating upon any dispute referred to in Article 19 of the Convention, an Arbitral Tribunal shall be established in accordance with the following paragraphs.</al>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<nr status="officieel">2</nr>
							</kop>
							
							<al>Any Party to the Convention may join either party to the dispute in the arbitration.</al>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<nr status="officieel">3</nr>
							</kop>
							
							<al>The Tribunal shall consist of three members. Each party to the dispute shall nominate one arbitrator within a period of two months from the date of receipt of the request by one party to refer the dispute to arbitration. The first two arbitrators shall, within a period of six months from the nomination of the second arbitrator, nominate the third arbitrator, who shall be the Chairman of the Tribunal. If one of the two arbitrators has not been nominated within the required period he shall, at the request of either party, be nominated by the Secretary General of the Permanent Court of Arbitration. The same procedure shall apply if the Chairman of the Tribunal has not been nominated within the required period.</al>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<nr status="officieel">4</nr>
							</kop>
							
							<al>The Tribunal shall determine its seat and establish its own rules of procedure.</al>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<nr status="officieel">5</nr>
							</kop>
							
							<al>The decision of the Tribunal shall be in accordance with international law and shall be based on the Convention and general principles of law.</al>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<nr status="officieel">6</nr>
							</kop>
							
							<al>Each party shall bear the costs relating to the arbitrator for whose nomination it is responsible, as well as the costs of being represented before the Tribunal. The expenditure relating to the Chairman of the Tribunal shall be shared equally by the parties to the dispute.</al>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<nr status="officieel">7</nr>
							</kop>
							
							<al>The award of the Tribunal shall be made by a majority of its members, who may not abstain from voting. This award shall be final and binding on all parties to the dispute and no appeal shall lie against it. The parties shall comply with the award without delay. In the event of a dispute as to its meaning or scope, the Tribunal shall interpret it at the request of any party to the dispute.</al>
						</artikel>
					</wettekst>
				</verdragtekst></verdrag>
  
  
  
<verdrag tekst="vertaling" xml:lang="nl">
				
				
				
				
				
				
				
				
				
			<verdragtekst>
					<kop>
						<titel status="officieel">Verdrag tot oprichting van het Europees Bureau voor Radiocommunicatie (EBR)</titel>
					</kop>
					<aanhef>
						<preambule>
							<al>De Staten die Partij zijn bij dit Verdrag, hierna te noemen de &#x201E;Verdragsluitende Partijen";</al>
							<al>De groeiende vraag erkennend wat het radiofrequentiespectrum betreft en de noodzaak optimaal gebruik te maken van deze schaarse natuurlijke hulpbron;</al>
							<al>Derhalve onderstrepend dat de huidige mechanismen, ingesteld door de Europese Conferentie van PTT-administraties, hierna te noemen de &#x201E;CEPT", moeten worden versterkt en toegerust met de noodzakelijke permanente middelen om lange-termijnanalyses te kunnen maken van de behoeften aan frequenties, gericht op een optimaal gebruik van het frequentiespectrum, daarbij rekening houdend met de actuele behoeften van diensten en gebruikers in het licht van de ontwikkelingen in de industrie en het vastleggen van normen;</al>
							<al>Vastbesloten een permanente instelling zonder winstoogmerk op te richten, die het Europees Comit&#xE9; voor Radiocommunicatie van de CEPT, hierna te noemen de &#x201E;ECR", moet bijstaan in de verrichting van haar taken met betrekking tot het te voeren beleid inzake radiocommunicatie en de co&#xF6;rdinatie van de regelgeving betreffende frequenties en technische aangelegenheden van het radioverkeer, met inbegrip van ruimtecommunicatie;</al>
							
							
						</preambule>
					<afkondiging><al>Zijn het volgende overeengekomen:</al></afkondiging></aanhef>
					<wettekst>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Artikel</label>
								<nr status="officieel">1</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">Oprichting van het EBR</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
								<al>Hierbij wordt een Europees Bureau voor Radiocommunicatie op gericht, hierna te noemen het &#x201E;EBR". </al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
								<al>De zetel van het EBR wordt gevestigd te Kopenhagen, Denemarken. </al>
							</lid>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Artikel</label>
								<nr status="officieel">2</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">Doel van het EBR</titel>
							</kop>
							<al>Het EBR is een vaktechnisch centrum op het gebied van de radiocommunicatie, dat het ECR bijstaat en adviseert.</al>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Artikel</label>
								<nr status="officieel">3</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">Taken van het EBR</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
								<al>Het EBR heeft tot taak: </al>
							<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>1.</li.nr><al>op te treden als co&#xF6;rdinerend vaktechnisch centrum, dat probleemgebieden opspoort en zoekt naar nieuwe mogelijkheden op het gebied van de radiocommunicatie en hierover advies uitbrengt aan het ECR; </al></li><li><li.nr>2.</li.nr><al>lange-termijnplannen op te stellen voor het toekomstig gebruik van het radiofrequentiespectrum op Europese schaal; </al></li><li><li.nr>3.</li.nr><al>contacten te onderhouden met de nationale autoriteiten die zijn belast met het frequentiebeheer; </al></li><li><li.nr>4.</li.nr><al>het werk te co&#xF6;rdineren en richtsnoeren te geven voor onderzoek; </al></li><li><li.nr>5.</li.nr><al>overleg te voeren over specifieke onderwerpen of delen van het frequentiespectrum; </al></li><li><li.nr>6.</li.nr><al>het ECR of zijn werkgroepen bij te staan bij het organiseren van speciale overlegbijeenkomsten;</al></li><li><li.nr>7.</li.nr><al>criteria toe te passen voor het bijwonen van overlegbijeenkomsten; </al></li><li><li.nr>8.</li.nr><al>een register bij te houden van belangrijke activiteiten van het ECR en van de uitvoering van de desbetreffende aanbevelingen en besluiten van de CEPT; </al>
							</li><li><li.nr>9.</li.nr><al>het ECR regelmatig voortgangsrapporten te verstrekken; en </al></li><li><li.nr>10.</li.nr><al>contacten te onderhouden met de Europese Gemeenschappen en de Europese Vrijhandelsassociatie.</al></li></lijst></lid>
							
							
							
							
							
							
							
							
							
							
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
								<al>In de uitvoering van de bovengenoemde taken met betrekking tot overlegbijeenkomsten ontwikkelt en actualiseert het EBR procedures om Europese organisaties die zijn betrokken bij het gebruik van radiocommunicatie -  waaronder ministeries, exploitanten van openbare radionetwerken, producenten, gebruikers, exploitanten van particuliere netten, dienstverleners, onderzoeksinstellingen, normalisatie-instituten of organisaties die groepen van deze partijen vertegenwoordigen - in staat te stellen regelmatig relevante informatie te ontvangen en billijkerwijs aan deze overlegbijeenkomsten deel te nemen, gelet op hun specifieke belangen. </al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
								<al>Naast de in het eerste lid genoemde taken belegt het EBR, gewoonlijk eenmaal per jaar, een vergadering die openstaat voor de in het tweede lid genoemde organisaties, ten einde hun de gelegenheid te bieden de activiteiten en de toekomstige werkprogramma's van het ECR en het EBR te bespreken. </al>
							</lid>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Artikel</label>
								<nr status="officieel">4</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">Rechtspositie en voorrechten</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
								<al>Het EBR bezit rechtspersoonlijkheid. Het EBR bezit volledige handelingsbekwaamheid, noodzakelijk om zijn taken te verrichten en zijn doelstellingen te verwezenlijken, en kan in het bijzonder: </al>
							<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>1.</li.nr><al>overeenkomsten aangaan; </al></li><li><li.nr>2.</li.nr><al>roerende en onroerende zaken aanschaffen, (ver)huren, houden en vervreemden; </al></li><li><li.nr>3.</li.nr><al>in rechte optreden; en </al></li><li><li.nr>4.</li.nr><al>verdragen sluiten met staten of internationale organisaties. </al></li></lijst></lid>
							
							
							
							
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
								<al>De Directeur en het personeel van het EBR genieten in Denemarken voorrechten en immuniteiten als omschreven in een Verdrag tussen het EBR en de Deense regering inzake de zetel van het EBR. </al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
								<al>Andere landen kunnen soortgelijke voorrechten en immuniteiten verlenen ten behoeve van activiteiten van het EBR in die landen, in het bijzonder immuniteit van rechtsvervolging met betrekking tot het gesproken en geschreven woord en alle handelingen verricht door de Directeur of het personeel van het EBR in de uitoefening van hun offici&#xEB;le functies. </al>
							</lid>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Artikel</label>
								<nr status="officieel">5</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">Organen van het EBR</titel>
							</kop>
							<al>Het EBR bestaat uit een Raad en een Directeur, bijgestaan door personeel.</al>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Artikel</label>
								<nr status="officieel">6</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">De Raad</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
								<al>De Raad bestaat uit vertegenwoordigers van de onderscheiden instanties belast met de regelgeving inzake het radioverkeer van alle Verdragsluitende Partijen. </al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
								<al>De Voorzitter van het ECR is Voorzitter van de Raad. Indien de Voorzitter van het ECR afkomstig is uit een land dat geen Partij bij dit Verdrag is, kiest de Raad een Voorzitter uit zijn leden. De Voorzitter is bevoegd namens de Raad te handelen. </al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
								<al>Vertegenwoordigers van de Commissie van de Europese Gemeenschappen en van het Secretariaat van de Europese Vrijhandelsassociatie kunnen in de Raad zitting nemen als waarnemer. </al>
							</lid>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Artikel</label>
								<nr status="officieel">7</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">Taken van de Raad</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
								<al>De Raad is het hoogste bestuursorgaan van het EBR en heeft in het bijzonder tot taak: </al>
							<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>1.</li.nr><al>het beleid van het EBR te bepalen inzake technische en administratieve aangelegenheden; </al></li><li><li.nr>2.</li.nr><al>het werkprogramma, de begroting en de boeken goed te keuren; </al></li><li><li.nr>3.</li.nr><al>het aantal personeelsleden vast te stellen; </al></li><li><li.nr>4.</li.nr><al>de Directeur en het personeel te benoemen; </al></li><li><li.nr>5.</li.nr><al>overeenkomsten en verdragen te sluiten namens het EBR; </al></li><li><li.nr>6.</li.nr><al>wijzigingen op het Verdrag aan te nemen overeenkomstig de artikelen 15 en 20; en </al></li><li><li.nr>7.</li.nr><al>alle maatregelen te nemen die noodzakelijk zijn voor de verwezenlijking van de doelstellingen van het EBR in het kader van het Verdrag. </al></li></lijst></lid>
							
							
							
							
							
							
							
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
								<al>De Raad stelt de nodige reglementen op om het EBR en zijn organen goed te doen functioneren. </al>
							</lid>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Artikel</label>
								<nr status="officieel">8</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">Stemregels</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
								<al>Besluiten van de Raad worden voor zover mogelijk bij consensus genomen. Indien geen consensus kan worden bereikt, wordt een besluit genomen met een meerderheid van tweederde van de uitgebrachte gewogen stemmen. </al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
								<al>Het wegen van de afzonderlijke stemmen in de Raad geschiedt overeenkomstig Bijlage A. </al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
								<al>Voorstellen tot wijziging van dit Verdrag, met inbegrip van de Bijlagen, worden slechts in overweging genomen indien zij worden gesteund door ten minste 25% van de totale gewogen stemmen van alle Verdragsluitende Partijen. </al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr>
								<al>Voor elk besluit van de Raad moet op het tijdstip waarop het wordt genomen een quorum aanwezig zijn, dat: </al>
							<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>1.</li.nr><al>bij besluiten betreffende wijzigingen op het Verdrag en de Bijlagen daarbij, gelijk is aan ten minste tweederde van de totale gewogen stemmen van alle Verdragsluitende Partijen; </al></li><li><li.nr>2.</li.nr><al>bij alle andere besluiten, gelijk is aan ten minste de helft van de totale gewogen stemmen van alle Verdragsluitende Partijen. </al></li></lijst></lid>
							
							
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">5</lidnr>
								<al>Waarnemers kunnen aan de besprekingen van de Raad deelnemen, maar zij hebben geen stemrecht. </al>
							</lid>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Artikel</label>
								<nr status="officieel">9</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">Directeur en personeel</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
								<al>De Directeur treedt op als wettelijk vertegenwoordiger van het EBR en is, binnen de door de Raad overeengekomen grenzen, bevoegd namens het EBR overeenkomsten te sluiten. De Directeur kan deze bevoegdheid geheel of gedeeltelijk delegeren aan de Adjunct-Directeur. </al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
								<al>De Directeur is verantwoordelijk voor de goede uitvoering van alle interne en externe activiteiten van het EBR in overeenstemming met dit Verdrag, het zetelverdrag, het werkprogramma, de begroting en de door de Raad gegeven richtlijnen en aanwijzingen. </al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
								<al>De Raad stelt een personeelsreglement op. </al>
							</lid>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Artikel</label>
								<nr status="officieel">10</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">Werkprogramma</titel>
							</kop>
							<al>Jaarlijks wordt door de Raad, op basis van een voorstel van het ECR, een werkprogramma voor het EBR vastgesteld voor een periode van drie jaar. Het eerste jaar van dit programma moet voldoende gegevens bevatten om de jaarbegroting van het EBR te kunnen vaststellen.</al>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Artikel</label>
								<nr status="officieel">11</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">Vaststelling van de begroting en boekhouding</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
								<al>Het boekjaar van het EBR loopt van 1 januari tot en met 31 december. </al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
								<al>De Directeur is belast met het opstellen van de jaarbegroting en de jaarrekeningen van het EBR en dient deze ter bestudering en/of goedkeuring voor te leggen aan de Raad. </al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
								<al>Bij het opstellen van begroting wordt rekening gehouden met de vereisten van het overeenkomstig artikel 10 vastgestelde werkprogramma. De termijnen voor indiening en goedkeuring van de begroting, voorafgaande aan het boekjaar waarop zij betrekking heeft, worden bepaald door de Raad. </al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr>
								<al>De Raad stelt een gedetailleerd financieel reglement vast. Dit dient onder andere bepalingen te bevatten betreffende de termijnen voor indiening en goedkeuring van de jaarrekeningen van het EBR alsmede bepalingen betreffende de accountantscontrole daarvan. </al>
							</lid>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Artikel</label>
								<nr status="officieel">12</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">Financi&#xEB;le bijdragen</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
								<al>De kapitaaluitgaven en de lopende bedrijfsuitgaven van het EBR, met uitzondering van de kosten verbonden aan de vergaderingen van de Raad, worden over de Verdragsluitende Partijen omgeslagen overeenkomstig de bijdragen-eenheden genoemd in de tabel in Bijlage A, die een integrerend deel van dit Verdrag uitmaakt. </al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
								<al>Dit belet het EBR niet, na een besluit van de Raad, werk voor derden te verrichten tegen vergoeding van de kosten. </al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
								<al>Kosten verbonden aan de vergaderingen van de Raad worden gedragen door de instantie belast met de regelgeving inzake het radioverkeer van het land waarin de vergadering plaatsvindt. Reis- en verblijfkosten worden gedragen door de vertegenwoordigde instanties. </al>
							</lid>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Artikel</label>
								<nr status="officieel">13</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">Verdragsluitende Partijen</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
								<al>Een Staat wordt Partij bij dit Verdrag via de procedure van artikel 14, dan wel via de procedure van artikel 15. </al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
								<al>Zodra een Staat Partij bij dit Verdrag wordt, is de bijdrage-eenheid genoemd in Bijlage A, zoals gewijzigd overeenkomstig artikel 15, van toepassing. </al>
							</lid>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Artikel</label>
								<nr status="officieel">14</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">Ondertekening</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
								<al>Een Staat waarvan de telecommunicatie-administratie lid is van de CEPT kan Verdragsluitende Partij worden door middel van: </al>
							<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>1.</li.nr><al>ondertekening zonder voorbehoud van bekrachtiging, aanvaarding of goedkeuring, of </al></li><li><li.nr>2.</li.nr><al>ondertekening onder voorbehoud van bekrachtiging, aanvaarding of goedkeuring, gevolgd door bekrachtiging, aanvaarding of goedkeuring.</al></li></lijst></lid>
							
							
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
								<al>Dit Verdrag staat open voor ondertekening vanaf 23 juni 1993 tot de datum van inwerkingtreding en blijft daarna openstaan voor toetreding. </al>
							</lid>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Artikel</label>
								<nr status="officieel">15</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">Toetreding</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
								<al>Dit Verdrag staat open voor toetreding door een Staat waarvan de telecommunicatie-administratie lid is van de CEPT. </al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
								<al>Na overleg met de toetredende Staat neemt de Raad de noodzakelijke wijzigingen op Bijlage A aan. In afwijking van artikel 20, tweede lid, wordt een dergelijke wijziging van kracht op de eerste dag van de tweede maand volgend op de datum waarop de Deense regering de akte van toetreding van die Staat heeft ontvangen. </al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
								<al>Uit de akte van toetreding dient te blijken dat de toetredende Staat instemt met de aangenomen wijzigingen op Bijlage A. </al>
							</lid>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Artikel</label>
								<nr status="officieel">16</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">Inwerkingtreding</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
								<al>Dit Verdrag treedt in werking op de eerste dag van de tweede maand volgend op de datum waarop de Deense regering voldoende ondertekeningen en, indien vereist, akten van bekrachtiging, aanvaarding of goedkeuring van Verdragsluitende Partijen heeft ontvangen, zodat is verzekerd dat tenminste 80% van het maximumaantal bijdrage-eenheden genoemd in Bijlage A is bereikt. </al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
								<al>Na de inwerkingtreding van dit Verdrag is iedere nieuwe Verdragsluitende Partij gebonden door de bepalingen ervan, met inbegrip van de van kracht zijnde wijzigingen, vanaf de eerste dag van de tweede maand volgend op de datum waarop de Deense regering de akte van bekrachtiging, aanvaarding, goedkeuring of toetreding van die Partij heeft ontvangen. </al>
							</lid>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Artikel</label>
								<nr status="officieel">17</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">Opzegging</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
								<al>Na het verstrijken van twee jaar na de inwerkingtreding van dit Verdrag kan elke Verdragsluitende Partij dit opzeggen door middel van een schriftelijke kennisgeving aan de Deense regering, die kennisgeving van deze opzegging doet aan de Raad, de Verdragsluitende Partijen en de Directeur. </al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
								<al>De opzegging wordt van kracht na het verstrijken van het volgende volledige boekjaar, zoals omschreven in artikel 11, eerste lid, na de datum van ontvangst van de kennisgeving van opzegging door de Deense regering. </al>
							</lid>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Artikel</label>
								<nr status="officieel">18</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">Rechten en verplichtingen van de Verdragsluitende Partijen</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
								<al>Dit Verdrag laat het soevereine recht van elke Verdragsluitende Partij om haar eigen telecommunicatie te regelen onverlet. </al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
								<al>Elke Verdragsluitende Partij die Lidstaat is van de Europese Economische Gemeenschap past dit Verdrag toe overeenkomstig haar verplichtingen ingevolge het Verdrag tot oprichting van de Europese Economische Gemeenschap. </al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
								<al>Ten aanzien van dit Verdrag kan geen enkel voorbehoud worden gemaakt. </al>
							</lid>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Artikel</label>
								<nr status="officieel">19</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">Geschillenregeling</titel>
							</kop>
							<al>Geschillen betreffende de uitlegging of toepassing van dit Verdrag en de Bijlagen daarbij die niet kunnen worden geregeld via bemiddeling door de Raad, worden door de betrokken partijen onderworpen aan arbitrage overeenkomstig Bijlage B, die een integrerend deel van dit Verdrag vormt.</al>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Artikel</label>
								<nr status="officieel">20</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">Wijzigingen</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
								<al>De Raad kan wijzigingen op dit Verdrag aannemen, onder voorbehoud van schriftelijke bevestiging door alle Verdragsluitende Partijen. </al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
								<al>De wijzigingen treden voor alle Verdragsluitende Partijen in werking op de eerste dag van de derde maand nadat de Deense regering de Verdragsluitende Partijen in kennis heeft gesteld van de ontvangst van kennisgevingen van bekrachtiging, aanvaarding of goedkeuring van alle Verdragsluitende Partijen. </al>
							</lid>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Artikel</label>
								<nr status="officieel">21</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">Depositaris</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
								<al>Het origineel van dit Verdrag, alsmede latere wijzigingen daarop, en de akten van bekrachtiging, aanvaarding, goedkeuring of toetreding worden nedergelegd in het archief van de Deense regering. </al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
								<al>De Deense regering doet een voor eensluidend gewaarmerkt afschrift van het Verdrag en van de tekst van eventuele door de Raad aangenomen wijzigingen toekomen aan alle Staten die het Verdrag hebben ondertekend of hiertoe zijn toegetreden en aan de fungerend voorzitter van de CEPT. Voorts worden ter kennisgeving afschriften toegezonden aan de Secretaris-Generaal van de Internationale Telecommunicatie-Unie, het contactbureau van de CEPT, de voorzitter van de Commissie van de Europese Gemeenschappen en de Secretaris-Generaal van de Europese Vrijhandelsassociatie. </al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
								<al>De Deense regering stelt alle Staten die het Verdrag hebben ondertekend of hiertoe zijn toegetreden en de fungerend voorzitter van de CEPT in kennis van alle ondertekeningen, bekrachtigingen, aanvaardingen, goedkeuringen en opzeggingen, alsmede van de inwerkingtreding van het Verdrag en van elke wijziging. De Deense regering stelt alle Staten die het Verdrag hebben ondertekend of hiertoe zijn toegetreden en de fungerend voorzitter van de CEPT voorts in kennis van de inwerkingtreding van elke toetreding. </al>
							</lid>
						</artikel>
					</wettekst>
					<wetsluiting status="goed">
						<slotformulering>
							<al>TEN BLIJKE WAARVAN de ondertekenende vertegenwoordigers, daartoe naar behoren gemachtigd, dit Verdrag hebben ondertekend.</al>
							<al>GEDAAN te 's-Gravenhage op 23 juni 1993 in &#xE9;&#xE9;n exemplaar in de Duitse, de Engelse en de Franse taal, zijnde alle teksten gelijkelijk authentiek.</al>
							
						</slotformulering>
					</wetsluiting>
				</verdragtekst><verdragtekst>
					<kop>
						<label>BIJLAGE</label>
						<nr status="officieel">A</nr>
						<titel status="officieel">Bijdragen-eenheden die als uitgangspunt dienen voor de financi&#xEB;le bijdragen en de gewogen stemming</titel>
					</kop>
					<vrije-tekst>
						<tekst status="goed">
							<table frame="all">
								<tgroup align="left" char="" charoff="50" cols="3" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
									<tbody valign="top">
										<row>
											<entry colsep="1" morerows="0" rotate="0" rowsep="1">
												<al>25 eenheden:</al>
												
												
											</entry>
											<entry colsep="1" morerows="0" rotate="0" rowsep="1">
												<al>Duitsland </al><al>Frankrijk </al><al>Itali&#xEB;</al>
												
												
											</entry>
											<entry colsep="1" morerows="0" rotate="0" rowsep="1">
												<al>Spanje </al><al>Verenigd Koninkrijk</al>
												
											</entry>
										</row><row><entry colsep="1" morerows="0" rotate="0" rowsep="1"><al>15 eenheden:</al></entry><entry colsep="1" morerows="0" rotate="0" rowsep="1"><al>Zwitserland</al></entry><entry colsep="1" morerows="0" rotate="0" rowsep="1"/></row><row><entry colsep="1" morerows="0" rotate="0" rowsep="1"><al>10 eenheden:</al></entry><entry colsep="1" morerows="0" rotate="0" rowsep="1"><al>Belgi&#xEB;</al><al> Denemarken</al><al>Finland</al><al> Griekenland </al><al>Luxemburg</al><al> Nederland</al></entry><entry colsep="1" morerows="0" rotate="0" rowsep="1"><al>Noorwegen </al><al>Oostenrijk </al><al>Portugal </al><al>Turkije</al><al> Zweden</al></entry></row><row><entry colsep="1" morerows="0" rotate="0" rowsep="1"><al>5 eenheden:</al></entry><entry colsep="1" morerows="0" rotate="0" rowsep="1"><al>Ierland</al></entry><entry colsep="1" morerows="0" rotate="0" rowsep="1"/></row><row><entry colsep="1" morerows="0" rotate="0" rowsep="1"><al>1 eenheid:</al></entry><entry colsep="1" morerows="0" rotate="0" rowsep="1"><al>Albani&#xEB; </al><al>Bulgarije</al><al> Cyprus</al><al> Hongarije</al><al> IJsland</al><al> Kroati&#xEB;</al><al>Letland</al><al>Liechtenstein</al><al> Litouwen </al><al>Malta</al>
											</entry><entry colsep="1" morerows="0" rotate="0" rowsep="1"><al>Moldavi&#xEB;</al><al> Monaco </al><al>Polen</al><al> Roemeni&#xEB; </al><al>San Marino </al><al>Sloveni&#xEB;</al><al> Tsjechi&#xEB; </al><al>Vaticaanstad</al>
											</entry></row>
									</tbody>
								</tgroup>
							</table>
							
						</tekst>
					</vrije-tekst>
				</verdragtekst><verdragtekst>
					<kop>
						<label>BIJLAGE</label>
						<nr status="officieel">B</nr>
						<titel status="officieel">Arbitrageprocedure</titel>
					</kop>
					<wettekst><artikel status="goed"><kop><nr status="officieel">1</nr></kop><al>Ter verkrijging van een scheidsrechterlijke uitspraak in elk geding als bedoeld in artikel 19 van het Verdrag wordt een scheidsgerecht ingesteld overeenkomstig de onderstaande paragrafen.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><nr status="officieel">2</nr></kop><al>Elke Partij bij het Verdrag kan zich in de arbitrageprocedure voegen bij een partij bij het geschil. </al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><nr status="officieel">3</nr></kop><al>Het scheidsgerecht bestaat uit drie leden. Elke partij bij het geschil benoemt een scheidsman binnen een termijn van twee maanden te rekenen vanaf de datum van ontvangst van het verzoek van &#xE9;&#xE9;n van de partijen om het geschil aan arbitrage te onderwerpen. De eerste twee scheidsmannen benoemen binnen een termijn van zes maanden na de benoeming van de tweede scheidsman een derde scheidsman, die voorzitter van het scheidsgerecht is. Indien &#xE9;&#xE9;n van de twee scheidsmannen niet binnen de voorgeschreven termijn is benoemd, wordt deze op verzoek van &#xE9;&#xE9;n van de partijen benoemd door de Secretaris-Generaal van het Permanente Hof van Arbitrage. Deze procedure is ook van toepassing indien de voorzitter van het scheidsgerecht niet binnen de voorgeschreven termijn is benoemd. </al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><nr status="officieel">4</nr></kop><al>Het scheidsgerecht bepaalt waar zijn zetel is en stelt zijn eigen reglement van orde vast. </al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><nr status="officieel">5</nr></kop><al>De beslissing van het scheidsgerecht dient in overeenstemming te zijn met het internationale recht en dient gebaseerd te zijn op dit Verdrag en de algemene rechtsbeginselen. </al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><nr status="officieel">6</nr></kop><al>Elke partij draagt de kosten van de scheidsman die zij benoemt, alsmede de kosten van haar vertegenwoordiging voor het scheidsgerecht. De kosten van de voorzitter worden in gelijke delen gedragen door de partijen bij het geschil. </al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><nr status="officieel">7</nr></kop><al>De beslissing van het scheidsgerecht wordt genomen bij een meerderheid van stemmen van zijn leden, die zich niet van stemming mogen onthouden. De uitspraak is onherroepelijk en bindend voor alle partijen bij het geschil en hiertegen staat geen enkel rechtsmiddel open. De partijen gaan onverwijld over tot tenuitvoerlegging van de uitspraak. In geval van verschil van mening aangaande de betekenis of strekking van de uitspraak, legt het scheidsgerecht deze uit op verzoek van &#xE9;&#xE9;n van de partijen bij het geschil.</al></artikel></wettekst>
				</verdragtekst></verdrag></wetgeving>
  	