<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE wetgeving SYSTEM "http://wetten.overheid.nl/dtd/bwb-plus-meta-1_61w.dtd">
<wetgeving bwb-id="BWBV0003393" dtdversie="2.0" id="10000028679" verdragnummer="002637" soort="verdrag"><alias-titels><alias-titel>Agreement on economic cooperation between the Government of the Kingdom of the Netherlands and the Government of the Republic of Singapore</alias-titel></alias-titels><intitule>Overeenkomst inzake economische samenwerking tussen de Regering van het Koninkrijk der Nederlanden en de Regering van de Republiek Singapore</intitule><verdrag tekst="authentiek" xml:lang="en"><verdragtekst>
<kop>
<titel status="officieel">Agreement on economic cooperation between the Government of the Kingdom of the Netherlands and the Government of the Republic of Singapore</titel>
</kop><aanhef><preambule><al>The Government of the Kingdom of the Netherlands and the Government of the Republic of Singapore,</al><al>Desiring to strengthen their traditional ties of friendship, to extend and intensify their economic relations and to encourage investments on the basis of equality in order to develop the industrial and commercial activities of their countries,</al></preambule><afkondiging><al>Have agreed as follows:</al></afkondiging></aanhef><wettekst><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">I</nr>
</kop><al>In this Agreement &#x2013;</al><al>&#x201C;investments&#x201D; includes every kind of asset, in particular &#x2013;</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>movable and immovable property as well as any other rights <nadruk type="cur">in rem;</nadruk></al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>shares or other kinds of interests in companies;</al></li><li><li.nr>(c)</li.nr><al>title to money or to any performance, such as goodwill, having an economic value;</al></li><li><li.nr>(d)</li.nr><al>rights in the fields of intellectual property, technical processes and know how; and</al></li><li><li.nr>(e)</li.nr><al>such business concessions under public law, including concessions regarding the prospecting for, or the extraction or the winning of natural resources, which give to their holders a legal position of some duration.</al></li></lijst><al>&#x201C;nationals&#x201D; in respect of either Contracting Party means &#x2013;</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>natural persons having the nationality of that Contracting Party;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>legal persons constituted in accordance with the laws of that Contracting Party; or</al></li><li><li.nr>(c)</li.nr><al>legal persons controlled directly or indirectly by nationals of that Contracting Party and constituted in accordance with the laws of the other Contracting Party.</al></li></lijst><al>&#x201C;intellectual property&#x201D; means the rights relating to &#x2013;</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>literary and scientific works;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>phonograms;</al></li><li><li.nr>(c)</li.nr><al>inventions in all fields of human endeavour;</al></li><li><li.nr>(d)</li.nr><al>scientific discoveries;</al></li><li><li.nr>(e)</li.nr><al>industrial designs;</al></li><li><li.nr>(f)</li.nr><al>trademarks, service marks, and commercial names and designations;</al></li><li><li.nr>(g)</li.nr><al>protection against unfair competition; and</al></li><li><li.nr>(h)</li.nr><al>all other rights resulting from intellectual activity in the industrial, scientific or literary fields.</al></li></lijst></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">II</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">(1)</lidnr><al>The Contracting Parties shall promote and develop economic cooperation between their respective countries.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">(2)</lidnr><al>In particular they undertake to promote cooperation between their nationals and to facilitate, within the framework of their respective legislation, the participation of their nationals in the establishment of industrial and commercial activities and the provision of services in their respective countries which would contribute towards the improvement of the standard of living in and the prosperity of their countries.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">III</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">(1)</lidnr><al>To further the achievement of the aims of the present Agreement, each Contracting Party is prepared, within the limits of its legislation, to authorize their nationals to deliver capital goods to and carry out public works for governmental and private enterprises, in the territory of the other Contracting Party, against payment by instalments.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">(2)</lidnr><al>Either Contracting Party shall authorize, subject to its legislation, the transfer, when due, of the sums owing to creditors who are nationals of the other Contracting Party.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">IV</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">(1)</lidnr><al>The Contracting Parties undertake to promote the development of international merchant shipping services. In doing so they shall maintain free and normal competitive conditions. Either Contracting Party shall refrain from taking any discriminatory measures against, and from restricting the free participation in international traffic of merchant vessels flying the flag of the other Contracting Party and operated by nationals of that Contracting Party or merchant vessels chartered by nationals of the latter Contracting Party.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">(2)</lidnr><al>Either Contracting Party shall accord in its ports to the merchant vessels flying the flag of the other Contracting Party and operated by nationals of that Contracting Party or merchant vessels chartered by nationals of the latter Contracting Party the same treatment as it accords to its own vessels. This provision applies, without prejudice to the provisions of international conventions binding on the Contracting Parties, to custom formalities, port fees and port charges, the free entry into ports, the assignment of berths, facilities for loading and unloading, and to all other facilities accorded to shipping and to economic activities in connection with merchant vessels, their crews, their passengers and the cargoes they carry.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">(3)</lidnr><al>From the provisions of the foregoing paragraphs of this Article shall be excepted &#x2013;</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>fisheries;</al><al>and</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>coastal shipping in the non-European parts of the Kingdom of the Netherlands, to which only the internal regulations of these parts of the Kingdom shall apply.</al></li></lijst></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">V</nr>
</kop><al>Nationals of either Contracting Party shall, in the field of the protection of intellectual property, enjoy in the territory of the other Contracting Party protection not less favourable than that enjoyed by the nationals of the latter Contracting Party, without prejudice to the provisions of international conventions in this field binding on the Contracting Parties.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">VI</nr>
</kop><al>Each Contracting Party undertakes to facilitate with regard to the other Contracting Party, to the extent permitted by the former Contracting Party's legislation and without prejudice to the provisions of international conventions binding on the Contracting Parties &#x2013;</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>the holding in its territory by the other Contracting Party or by its nationals of economic and commercial exhibitions and displays;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>the importation, duty-free, of goods, materials and equipment to be used for economic and commercial exhibitions and displays, on condition that they are re-exported within a limited period;</al></li><li><li.nr>(c)</li.nr><al>the importation, duty-free, of professional equipment, and of goods, materials and equipments to be used for technical work on behalf of governmental bodies or private enterprises, on condition that they are re-exported within a limited period;</al></li><li><li.nr>(d)</li.nr><al>the re-exportation, duty-free, of goods, materials and equipment referred to in (b) and (c); and</al></li><li><li.nr>(e)</li.nr><al>the disposal of goods, materials and equipment referred to in (b) and (c) in the territory where they have been used, subject to the payment of duty.</al></li></lijst></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">VII</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">(1)</lidnr><al>Each Contracting Party shall ensure fair and equitable treatment to the investments of nationals of the other Contracting Party and shall not impair, by unjustified or discriminatory measures, the management, maintenance, use, enjoyment or disposal thereof by those nationals.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">(2)</lidnr><al>More particularly, each Contracting Party shall accord to such investments the same security and protection as it accords to those of its own nationals or to those of nationals of third countries, whichever is more favourable to the investor.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">VIII</nr>
</kop><al>Recognizing the principle of the freedom of transfer, each Contracting Party shall authorize, subject to its relevant most favourable laws and regulations, the transfer, without undue restriction and delay, to the country of the other Contracting Party and in the currency of that country of payments resulting from investment activities, and in particular &#x2013;</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>nett profits, interest, dividends and other current income;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>funds necessary</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(i)</li.nr><al>for the acquisition of raw or auxiliary materials, semi-fabricated or fineshed products, or</al></li><li><li.nr>(ii)</li.nr><al>for the replacement of capital assets, in order to safeguard the continuity of an investment;</al></li></lijst></li><li><li.nr>(e)</li.nr><al>additional funds necessary for the development of an investment;</al></li><li><li.nr>(d)</li.nr><al>earnings of natural persons;</al></li><li><li.nr>(e)</li.nr><al>the proceeds of liquidation of capital;</al></li><li><li.nr>(f)</li.nr><al>funds in repayment of loans;</al></li><li><li.nr>(g)</li.nr><al>management fees; and</al></li><li><li.nr>(h)</li.nr><al>royalties.</al></li></lijst></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">IX</nr>
</kop><al>Neither Contracting Party shall take any measures depriving, directly or indirectly, nationals of the other Contracting Party of their investments unless the following conditions are complied with:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>the measures are taken in the public interest and under due process of law;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>the measures are not discriminatory or contrary to any undertaking which the former Contracting Party may have given to the particular nationals concerned; and</al></li><li><li.nr>(c)</li.nr><al>the measures are accompanied by provisions for the payment of just compensation. Such compensation shall be paid and made transferable, without undue delay, to the country of the nationals affected and in the currency of that country.</al></li></lijst></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">X</nr>
</kop><al>The Contracting Party in the territory of which an investment has been made, in respect of which investment the other Contracting Party or a national thereof has granted any financial security against non-commercial risks, shall recognize the subrogation of the grantor of that security into the rights of the investor as to damages if payment has been made under that security.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">XI</nr>
</kop><al>The Contracting Party in the territory of which nationals of the other Contracting Party make or intend to make investments, shall after the exhaustion of all local administrative and judicial remedies, agree to any demand on the part of such nationals to submit, for arbitration or conciliation, to the Centre established by the Convention of Washington of 18 March 1965 on the settlement of investment disputes between States and nationals of other States, any disputes that may arise in connection with the investments.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">XII</nr>
<titel status="officieel"/>
</kop><lid><lidnr status="officieel">(1)</lidnr><al>The present Agreement shall apply &#x2013;</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>in respect of investments in the Republic of Singapore, to all investments made by nationals of the Kingdom of the Netherlands whose applications for the investments concerned have been approved in writing by the Government of the Republic of Singapore;</al><al>and</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>in respect of investments in the Kingdom of the Netherlands, to all investments made by nationals of the Republic of Singapore.</al></li></lijst></lid><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">(2)</lidnr><al>The provisions of the foregoing paragraph of this Article shall apply to all investments referred to therein irrespective of whether those investments were made before or after the coming into force of the present Agreement.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">XIII</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">(1)</lidnr><al>The Contracting Parties agree to establish a Joint Committee which will meet at the request of either Contracting Party for the purpose of &#x2013;</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>discussing any matter pertaining to the implementation of the present Agreement;</al><al>and</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>considering means of promoting economic cooperation between their countries.</al></li></lijst></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">(2)</lidnr><al>The composition and procedure of the Joint Committee shall be mutually agreed upon by the Contracting Parties.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">XIV</nr>
</kop><al>In respect of any matter governed by the present Agreement nothing in this Agreement shall prevent nationals of one Contracting Party from benefiting from any right more favourable to them and accorded by the other Contracting Party.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">XV</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">(1)</lidnr><al>Any dispute between the Contracting Parties concerning the interpretation or application of the present Agreement which cannot be settled within a reasonable lapse of time by means of diplomatic negotiations, shall be submitted, at the request of either Contracting Party, to an arbitral tribunal composed of three members. Each Contracting Party shall appoint one arbitrator and the two arbitrators thus appointed shall together appoint a third arbitrator as their chairman who is not a national of either Contracting Party.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">(2)</lidnr><al>If one of the Contracting Parties fails to appoint its arbitrator within two months after an invitation from the other Contracting Party to make such appointment, the latter Contracting Party may invite the President of the International Court of Justice to make the necessary appointment.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">(3)</lidnr><al>If the two arbitrators are unable to reach agreement, in the two months following their appointments, on the choice of the third arbitrator, either Contracting Party may invite the President of the International Court of Justice to make the necessary appointment.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">(4)</lidnr><al>If, in the cases provided for in the paragraphs (2) and (3) of this Article, the President of the International Court of Justice is prevented from discharging the said functions or is a national of either Contracting Party, the Vice-President shall make the necessary appointments. If the Vice-President is prevented from discharging the said functions or is a national of either Contracting Party, the most senior member of the said Court who is not a national of either Contracting Party shall make the necessary appointments.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">(5)</lidnr><al>The tribunal shall decide on the basis of respect for the law. Before the tribunal makes a decision, it may at any stage of the proceedings propose to the Contracting Parties that the dispute be settled amicably. The foregoing provisions shall not prejudice the power of the tribunal to decide the dispute <nadruk type="cur">ex aequo et bono</nadruk>    if the Contracting Parties so agree.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">(6)</lidnr><al>Unless the Contracting Parties decide otherwise, the tribunal shall determine its own procedure.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">(7)</lidnr><al>The tribunal shall reach its decision by a majority of votes. Such decision shall be final and binding on the Contracting Parties.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">(8)</lidnr><al>Each Contracting Party shall bear the cost of its own arbitrator and of its representatives in the arbitral proceedings. The cost of the chairman and the remaining costs shall be borne in equal parts by the Contracting Parties.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">XVI</nr>
</kop><al>As regards the Kingdom of the Netherlands, the present Agreement shall apply to the territory of the Kingdom in Europe, to Surinam and to the Netherlands Antilles, unless the Diplomatic Note of the Government of the Kingdom of the Netherlands, provided for in paragraph (1) of Article XVII of the present Agreement, stipulates otherwise.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">XVII</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">(1)</lidnr><al>The present Agreement shall come into force on the thirtieth (30th) day after the date of the exchange of Diplomatic Notes by the Contracting Parties confirming that all formalities for the coming into force of the present Agreement have been fulfilled in the respective countries, and shall remain in force for a period of five (5) years. Unless written notice of termination has been given by either Contracting Party at least six months before the date of the expiry of its validity, the present Agreement shall be extended tacitly for another period of five (5) years, and so on, each Contracting Party reserving the right to terminate the present Agreement upon written notice of at least six months before the date of expiry of the current period of validity.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">(2)</lidnr><al>Subject to the periods mentioned in paragraph (1) of this Article, the Government of the Kingdom of the Netherlands shall be entitled to terminate the application of the present Agreemen separately in respect of Surinam or the Netherlands Antilles.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">(3)</lidnr><al>Notwithstanding anything in paragraphs (1) and (2) of this Article, the provisions of the present Agreement shall continue to apply to investments made before the date of its termination for a period of fifteen (15) years from that date.</al></lid></artikel></wettekst><wetsluiting status="goed">
  <slotformulering>
	 <al>IN WITNESS WHEREOF, the undersigned representatives, duly authorized
		thereto, have signed the present Agreement.</al>
	 <al>DONE at Singapore this sixteenth day of May 1972, in duplicate, in the
		English language.</al>
  <al>For the Government of the Kingdom of the Netherlands:</al><al>(sd.) PEKELHARING</al><al>(R. C. Pekelharing)</al><al>For the Government of the Republic of Singapore:</al><al>(sd.) G. E. BOGAARS</al><al>(G. E. Bogaars)</al></slotformulering>
</wetsluiting></verdragtekst><verdragtekst><kop><label>Protocol</label></kop><vrije-tekst><tekst status="goed"><al>At the time of signing the Agreement on economic cooperation between the Government of the Kingdom of the Netherlands and the Government of the Republic of Singapore, the undersigned representatives confirm that their respective Governments have reached the understanding that &#x2013;</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>In respect of Article XIV of the said Agreement, any right accorded by the Government of the Republic of Singapore shall mean any right accorded by the said Government after the coming into force of the Constitution (Amendment) Act, 1965, (Act No. 8 of 1965) on the 9th day of August, 1965.</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>This Protocol shall form an integral part of the said Agreement.</al></li></lijst><al>IN WITNESS WHEREOF, the undersigned representatives, duly authorized thereto, have signed the Protocol.</al><al>DONE at Singapore this sixteenth day of May 1972, in duplicate, in the English language.</al><al>For the Government of the Kingdom of the Netherlands:</al><al>(sd.) PEKELHARING</al><al>(R. C. Pekelharing)</al><al>For the Government of the Republic of Singapore:</al><al>(sd.) G. E. BOGAARS</al><al>(G. E. Bogaars)</al></tekst></vrije-tekst></verdragtekst></verdrag><verdrag tekst="vertaling" xml:lang="nl"><verdragtekst>
<kop>
<titel status="officieel">Overeenkomst inzake economische samenwerking tussen de Regering van het Koninkrijk der Nederlanden en de Regering van de Republiek Singapore</titel>
</kop><aanhef><preambule><al>De Regering van het Koninkrijk der Nederlanden en de Regering van de Republiek Singapore,</al><al>Verlangende hun traditionele vriendschapsbanden nauwer aan te halen, hun economische betrekkingen uit te breiden en te intensiveren en investeringen op basis van gelijkheid te bevorderen ten einde de industri&#xEB;le en commerci&#xEB;le activiteiten van hun landen te ontwikkelen;</al></preambule><afkondiging><al>Zijn als volgt overeengekomen:</al></afkondiging></aanhef><wettekst><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">I</nr>
</kop><al>In deze Overeenkomst</al><al> omvat &#x201E;investering&#x201D; alle vermogensbestanddelen, in het bijzonder:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>roerende en onroerende goederen, alsmede alle andere zakelijke rechten;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>aandelen of andere belangen in vennootschappen;</al></li><li><li.nr>(c)</li.nr><al>recht op geld of op iedere verrichting, zoals goodwill, die economische waarde heeft;</al></li><li><li.nr>(d)</li.nr><al>rechten op het gebied van de intellectuele eigendom, technische werkwijzen en technische vaardigheid; en</al></li><li><li.nr>(e)</li.nr><al>zodanige publiekrechtelijke commerci&#xEB;le concessies, waaronder concessies betreffende het zoeken naar, of het delven of winnen van natuurlijke rijkdommen, die de houder daarvan gedurende enige tijd een rechtspositie verlenen;</al></li></lijst><al>betekent &#x201E;onderdanen&#x201D; wat betreft elk der Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>natuurlijke personen die de nationaliteit van die Overeenkomstsluitende Partij bezitten;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>rechtspersonen opgericht overeenkomstig de wetten van die Overeenkomstsluitende Partij; of</al></li><li><li.nr>(c)</li.nr><al>rechtspersonen waarin onderdanen van die Overeenkomstsluitende Partij direct of indirect een overwegend belang hebben en die zijn opgericht overeenkomstig de wetten van de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij;</al></li></lijst><al>betekent &#x201E;intellectuele eigendom&#x201D; de rechten betreffende:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>werken van letterkunde en wetenschap;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>fonogrammen;</al></li><li><li.nr>(c)</li.nr><al>uitvindingen op alle gebieden van de menselijke werkzaamheid;</al></li><li><li.nr>(d)</li.nr><al>wetenschappelijke ontdekkingen;</al></li><li><li.nr>(e)</li.nr><al>tekeningen en modellen van nijverheid;</al></li><li><li.nr>(f)</li.nr><al>fabrieks-, handels- en dienstmerken alsmede handelsnamen en commerci&#xEB;le aanduidingen;</al></li><li><li.nr>(g)</li.nr><al>bescherming tegen oneerlijke mededinging; en</al></li><li><li.nr>(h)</li.nr><al>alle andere rechten verband houdende met de intellectuele werkzaamheid op het gebied van de nijverheid, de wetenschap of de letterkunde.</al></li></lijst></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">II</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">(1)</lidnr><al>De Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen bevorderen en ontwikkelen de economische samenwerking tussen hun onderscheiden landen.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">(2)</lidnr><al>In het bijzonder verbinden zij zich de samenwerking tussen hun onderdanen te bevorderen en, in het kader van hun onderscheiden wetgeving, de deelneming van hun onderdanen bij het verrichten van industri&#xEB;le en commerci&#xEB;le activiteiten en bij de verlening van diensten binnen hun onderscheiden landen die zouden kunnen bijdragen tot de verbetering van de levensstandaard in en tot de voorspoed van hun landen, te vergemakkelijken.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">III</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">(1)</lidnr><al>Ten einde te bevorderen dat de doeleinden van deze Overeenkomst worden bereikt is elke Overeenkomstsluitende Partij bereid, binnen de grenzen van haar wetgeving, haar onderdanen vergunning te verlenen tot het leveren van kapitaalgoederen aan en het uitvoeren van openbare werken ten behoeve van de Overheids- en particuliere ondernemingen op het grondgebied van de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij, een en ander tegen betalingen in termijnen.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">(2)</lidnr><al>Elke Overeenkomstsluitende Partij verleent overeenkomstig haar wetgeving vergunning tot de overmaking van opeisbare bedragen die verschuldigd zijn aan de crediteuren die onderdaan van de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij zijn.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">IV</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">(1)</lidnr><al>De Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen verbinden zich de ontwikkeling van de internationale koopvaardij te bevorderen. Daarbij handhaven zij de normale, vrije mededinging. Elk der Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen onthoudt zich van het nemen van enige discriminatoire maatregel gericht tegen, en van elke beperking in de vrije deelneming aan het internationale verkeer van, koopvaardijschepen die de vlag voeren van de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij en die ge&#xEB;xploiteerd worden door onderdanen van die Overeenkomstsluitende Partij of koopvaardijschepen die in charter verhuurd zijn aan onderdanen van laatstgenoemde Overeenkomstsluitende Partij.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">(2)</lidnr><al>Elk der Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen verleent in haar havens aan koopvaardijschepen die de vlag voeren van de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij en die ge&#xEB;xploiteerd worden door onderdanen van die Overeenkomstsluitende Partij of aan koopvaardijschepen die in charter verhuurd zijn aan onderdanen van laatstgenoemde Overeenkomstsluitende Partij, dezelfde behandeling als zij aan haar eigen schepen verleent. Deze bepaling is, onverminderd de bepalingen van internationale verdragen, die beide Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen verbinden, van toepassing op douaneformaliteiten, havenrechten en havengelden, de vrije toegang tot de havens, de toewijzing van ligplaatsen, laad- en losfaciliteiten en alle andere faciliteiten die worden verleend aan de scheepvaart en ten behoeve van economische activiteiten in verband met koopvaardijschepen, hun bemanningen, hun passagiers en de door hen vervoerde lading.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">(3)</lidnr><al>Van het bepaalde in de voorgaande leden van dit artikel zijn uitgezonderd:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>de visserij, en</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>de kustvaart in de buiten Europa gelegen delen van het Koninkrijk der Nederlanden waarop slechts de interne regelingen van deze delen van het Koninkrijk van toepassing zijn.</al></li></lijst></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">V</nr>
</kop><al>Onverminderd de bepalingen van internationale verdragen, die ter zake de Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen verbinden, genieten onderdanen van elk der Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen, wat de bescherming van de intellectuele eigendom betreft, op het grondgebied van de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij een bescherming die niet minder gunstig is dan die welke onderdanen van laatstgenoemde Overeenkomstsluitende Partij genieten.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">VI</nr>
</kop><al>Elke Overeenkomstsluitende Partij verbindt zich, in de mate waarin zulks ingevolge haar wetgeving is toegestaan en onverminderd de bepalingen van de internationale verdragen welke voor de Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen verbindend zijn, ten opzichte van de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij te vergemakkelijken:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>het organiseren op haar grondgebied door de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij of haar onderdanen van economische en commerci&#xEB;le tentoonstellingen en soortgelijke manifestaties;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>de invoer, vrij van rechten, van goederen, materialen en uitrusting bestemd voor economische en commerci&#xEB;le tentoonstellingen en soortgelijke manifestaties, mits zij binnen een bepaald tijdvak weer worden uitgevoerd;</al></li><li><li.nr>(c)</li.nr><al>de invoer, vrij van rechten, van beroepsuitrusting en van goederen, materialen en uitrusting bestemd voor technische werken ten behoeve van Overheidsinstellingen of particuliere ondernemingen, mits zij binnen een bepaald tijdvak weer worden uitgevoerd;</al></li><li><li.nr>(d)</li.nr><al>de wederuitvoer, vrij van rechten, van de goederen, materialen en uitrusting bedoeld onder (b) en (c); en van</al></li><li><li.nr>(e)</li.nr><al>de vervreemding, tegen betaling van rechten, van de goederen, materialen en uitrusting bedoeld onder (b) en (c) in het grondgebied waar zij zijn gebruikt.</al></li></lijst></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">VII</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">(1)</lidnr><al>Elke Overeenkomstsluitende Partij waarborgt de eerlijke en billijke behandeling van de investeringen van onderdanen van de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij en belemmert niet door ongerechtvaardigde of discriminatoire maatregelen het beheer, de instandhouding, het gebruik en het genot daarvan, of de beschikking daarover door die onderdanen.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">(2)</lidnr><al>Met name kent elke Overeenkomstsluitende Partij aan zodanige investeringen dezelfde zekerheid en bescherming toe als zij toekent aan die van haar eigen onderdanen of aan die van onderdanen van derde landen, indien deze laatste behandeling voor die investeerder gunstiger is.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">VIII</nr>
</kop><al>Het beginsel van de vrije overmaking erkennend, staat elke Overeenkomstsluitende Partij met inachtneming van haar gunstigste wetten en voorschriften ter zake de overmaking toe, zonder onnodige beperking of vertraging, naar het land van de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij en in de valuta van dat land, van betalingen die voortvloeien uit investeringsactiviteiten, en in het bijzonder van:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>netto-winsten, interesten, dividenden en andere lopende inkomsten;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>gelden nodig voor</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(i)</li.nr><al>het verwerven van grondstoffen of hulpmaterialen, halffabrikaten of eindprodukten, of</al></li><li><li.nr>(ii)</li.nr><al>de vervanging van kapitaalgoederen, ten einde de continu&#xEF;teit van een investering te waarborgen;</al></li></lijst></li><li><li.nr>(c)</li.nr><al>bijkomende gelden noodzakelijk voor de ontwikkeling van een investering;</al></li><li><li.nr>(d)</li.nr><al>inkomsten uit arbeid van natuurlijke personen;</al></li><li><li.nr>(e)</li.nr><al>de opbrengst van de liquidatie van kapitaal;</al></li><li><li.nr>(f)</li.nr><al>gelden voor de terugbetaling van leningen;</al></li><li><li.nr>(g)</li.nr><al>honoraria voor verleende beheersdiensten; en</al></li><li><li.nr>(h)</li.nr><al>royalties.</al></li></lijst></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">IX</nr>
</kop><al>Geen der Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen neemt maatregelen waardoor aan onderdanen van de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij direct of indirect hun investeringen worden ontnomen, tenzij aan de volgende voorwaarden is voldaan:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>de maatregelen zijn genomen in het openbaar belang en met inachtneming van een behoorlijke rechtsgang;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>de maatregelen zijn niet discriminatoir of in strijd met enige toezegging van de eerstgenoemde Overeenkomstsluitende Partij aan de bijzondere betrokken onderdanen; en</al></li><li><li.nr>(c)</li.nr><al>de maatregelen gaan vergezeld van regelingen voor de betaling van een rechtvaardige schadeloosstelling. Deze schadeloosstelling wordt uitgekeerd, en machtiging tot overmaking wordt verleend zonder onnodige vertraging naar het land waarvan de gerechtigden onderdaan zijn en in de valuta van dat land.</al></li></lijst></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">X</nr>
</kop><al>De Overeenkomstsluitende Partij op wier grondgebied een investering is gedaan, ten aanzien van welke investering de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij of een onderdaan daarvan enige financi&#xEB;le zekerheid tegen niet-commerci&#xEB;le risico's heeft gesteld, erkent de subrogatie van degene die deze zekerheid heeft gesteld in de rechten van de investeerder met betrekking tot schadevergoeding indien op grond van deze zekerheid betalingen zijn gedaan.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">XI</nr>
</kop><al>De Overeenkomstsluitende Partij op wier grondgebied onderdanen van de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij investeringen doen of voornemens zijn zulks te doen, stemt, na de uitputting van alle nationale administratieve en gerechtelijke middelen, in met elk verzoek van de zijde van zodanige onderdanen om geschillen die zouden kunnen rijzen in verband met investeringen ter bemiddeling of arbitrage voor te leggen aan het Centrum, opgericht bij het Verdrag van Washington van 18 maart 1965 inzake de beslechting van geschillen met betrekking tot investeringen tussen Staten en onderdanen van andere Staten.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">XII</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">(1)</lidnr><al>Deze Overeenkomst is van toepassing:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>wat investeringen in de Republiek Singapore betreft, op alle investeringen gedaan door onderdanen van het Koninkrijk der Nederlanden wier aanvragen voor het doen van deze investeringen schriftelijk door de Regering van de Republiek Singapore zijn goedgekeurd; en</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>wat investeringen in het Koninkrijk der Nederlanden betreft, op alle investeringen gedaan door onderdanen van de Republiek Singapore.</al></li></lijst></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">(2)</lidnr><al>Het in het voorgaande lid van dit artikel bepaalde is van toepassing op alle daarin bedoelde investeringen, ongeacht of deze investeringen gedaan zijn voor of na de inwerkingtreding van deze Overeenkomst.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">XIII</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">(1)</lidnr><al>De Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen komen overeen een Gemeenschappelijke Commissie in te stellen, welke, ten verzoeke van een der Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen, bijeenkomt ten einde:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>aangelegenheden met betrekking tot de tenuitvoerlegging van de onderhavige Overeenkomst te bespreken; en</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>middelen ter bevordering van de economische samenwerking tussen hun landen in overweging te nemen.</al></li></lijst></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">(2)</lidnr><al>De samenstelling en de procedure van de Gemeenschappelijke Commissie worden wederzijds door de Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen overeengekomen.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">XIV</nr>
</kop><al>Ten aanzien van door deze Overeenkomst beheerste aangelegenheden belet niets in deze Overeenkomst dat onderdanen van een Overeenkomstsluitende Partij enig voor hen gunstiger recht genieten dat is toegekend door de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">XV</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">(1)</lidnr><al>Enig geschil tussen de Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen betreffende de uitlegging of de toepassing van deze Overeenkomst dat niet binnen een redelijke termijn door middel van diplomatieke onderhandelingen kan worden beslecht, wordt, op verzoek van een van beide Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen, voorgelegd aan een scheidsgerecht bestaande uit drie leden. Elke Overeenkomstsluitende Partij benoemt een lid en de beide aldus benoemde scheidsmannen benoemen te zamen een derde scheidsman die geen onderdaan is van een der Partijen tot hun voorzitter.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">(2)</lidnr><al>Indien een der Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen nalaat haar scheidsman te benoemen binnen twee maanden nadat de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij haar heeft uitgenodigd een zodanige benoeming te verrichten, kan de laatstgenoemde Overeenkomstsluitende Partij de President van het Internationaal Gerechtshof verzoeken de noodzakelijke benoeming te verrichten.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">(3)</lidnr><al>Indien de beide scheidsmannen niet binnen twee maanden na hun benoeming tot overeenstemming komen inzake de keuze van de derde scheidsman, kan elk der Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen de President van het Internationaal Gerechtshof verzoeken de noodzakelijke benoeming te verrichten.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">(4)</lidnr><al>Indien in de gevallen voorzien in het tweede en het derde lid van dit artikel de President van het Internationaal Gerechtshof verhinderd is deze functie uit te oefenen of indien hij onderdaan is van een der Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen, doet de Vice-President de noodzakelijke benoeming. Indien de Vice-President verhinderd is deze functie uit te oefenen of onderdaan is van een der Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen, doet het lid van het Hof dat het hoogst in anci&#xEB;nniteit is en dat geen onderdaan is van een der Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen de noodzakelijke benoemingen.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">(5)</lidnr><al>Het scheidsgerecht doet een uitspraak op grondslag van de eerbiediging van het recht. Alvorens uitspraak te doen kan het scheidsgerecht in elke stand van het geding de Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen een minnelijke schikking voorstellen. De voorgaande bepalingen doen geen afbreuk aan de bevoegdheid van het scheidsgerecht in het geschil een uitspraak <nadruk type="cur">ex aequo et bono</nadruk>    te doen indien de Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen daarmede instemmen.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">(6)</lidnr><al>Tenzij de Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen anders beslissen, stelt het scheidsgerecht zijn eigen procedure vast.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">(7)</lidnr><al>Het scheidsgerecht doet zijn uitspraak bij meerderheid van stemmen. Deze uitspraak is onherroepelijk en bindend voor de Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">(8)</lidnr><al>Elke Overeenkomstsluitende Partij draagt de kosten van haar eigen scheidsman en van haar vertegenwoordigers bij de scheidsrechterlijke procedure. De kosten van de voorzitter en de andere kosten worden gelijkelijk door de Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen gedragen.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">XVI</nr>
</kop><al>Wat het Koninkrijk der Nederlanden betreft, is de onderhavige Overeenkomst van toepassing op het in Europa gelegen grondgebied van het Koninkrijk, op Suriname en op de Nederlandse Antillen, tenzij de diplomatieke nota van de Regering van het Koninkrijk der Nederlanden voorzien in het eerste lid van artikel XVII van de onderhavige Overeenkomst, anders bepaalt.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">XVII</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">(1)</lidnr><al>Deze Overeenkomst treedt in werking op de dertigste (30ste) dag na de datum van de wisseling door de Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen van diplomatieke nota's waarin wordt bevestigd dat aan alle formaliteiten voor de inwerkingtreding van deze Overeenkomst in de onderscheiden landen is voldaan, en blijft van kracht gedurende een tijdvak van vijf (5) jaren. Tenzij de Overeenkomst door een de Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen ten minste zes maanden voor de datum van be&#xEB;indiging van haar geldigheid schriftelijk is opgezegd wordt deze Overeenkomst stilzwijgend verlengd voor een volgend tijdvak van vijf (5) jaren, en zo vervolgens, waarbij elk der Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen zich het recht voorbehoudt deze Overeenkomst te be&#xEB;indigen door middel van een schriftelijke mededeling daartoe ten minste zes maanden voor de datum van be&#xEB;indiging van het dan lopende tijdvak van geldigheid.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">(2)</lidnr><al>Met inachtneming van de tijdvakken genoemd in het eerste lid van dit artikel is de Regering van Koninkrijk der Nederlanden gerechtigd de toepassing van de onderhavige Overeenkomst afzonderlijk te be&#xEB;indigen voor Suriname of de Nederlandse Antillen.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">(3)</lidnr><al>Ongeacht het bepaalde in het eerste en het tweede lid van dit artikel blijven de bepalingen van de onderhavige Overeenkomst van toepassing op investeringen die zijn gedaan voor de datum van haar be&#xEB;indiging en wel gedurende een tijdvak van vijftien (15) jaren vanaf die datum.</al></lid></artikel></wettekst><wetsluiting status="goed">
  <slotformulering>
	 <al>TEN BLIJKE WAARVAN de ondertekenende vertegenwoordigers daartoe
		behoorlijk gemachtigd, deze Overeenkomst hebben ondertekend.</al>
	 <al>GEDAAN te Singapore, de zestiende mei 1972, in tweevoud, in de Engelse
		taal.</al>
  <al>Voor de Regering van het Koninkrijk der Nederlanden:</al><al>(w.g.) PEKELHARING</al><al>(R. C. Pekelharing)</al><al>Voor de Regering van de Republiek Singapore:</al><al>(w.g.) G. E. BOGAARS</al></slotformulering>
</wetsluiting></verdragtekst>
<verdragtekst>
<kop>
<label>Protocol</label>
</kop><vrije-tekst><tekst status="goed"><al>Op het tijdstip van ondertekening van de Overeenkomst inzake economische samenwerking tussen de Regering van het Koninkrijk der Nederlanden en de Regering van de Republiek Singapore bevestigen de ondertekenende vertegenwoordigers dat hun onderscheiden Regeringen overeenstemming hebben bereikt dat</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>wat artikel XIV van genoemde Overeenkomst betreft, onder enig recht toegekend door de Regering van de Republiek Singapore wordt verstaan enig recht door deze Regering toegekend na de inwerkingtreding van de Wet van 1965 tot wijziging van de Grondwet (Wet no. 8 van 1965) op 9 augustus 1965.</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>dit Protocol een integrerend deel uitmaakt van genoemde Overeenkomst.</al></li></lijst><al>TEN BLIJKE WAARVAN de ondertekenende vertegenwoordigers, daartoe behoorlijk gemachtigd, dit Protocol hebben ondertekend.</al><al>GEDAAN te Singapore, de zestiende mei 1972, in tweevoud, in de Engelse taal.</al><al>Voor de Regering van het Koninkrijk der Nederlanden:</al><al>(w.g.) PEKELHARING</al><al>(R. C. Pekelharing)</al><al>Voor de Regering van de Republiek Singapore:</al><al>(w.g.) G. E. BOGAARS</al></tekst></vrije-tekst></verdragtekst></verdrag></wetgeving>
  	