<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE wetgeving SYSTEM "http://wetten.overheid.nl/dtd/bwb-plus-meta-1_61w.dtd">
<wetgeving bwb-id="BWBV0005368" dtdversie="2.0" id="10000048429" sleutel="V4734" verdragnummer="007315" soort="verdrag">
  
  
  
  <alias-titels><alias-titel>CUSTOMS CONVENTION ON THE TEMPORARY IMPORTATION OF PRIVATE ROAD VEHICLES</alias-titel></alias-titels>
  
  <intitule>Douaneverdrag inzake de tijdelijke invoer van particuliere wegvoertuigen</intitule>
  
  <verdrag status="nogniet" tekst="authentiek" xml:lang="en">
    <verdragtekst>
      <kop>
        <titel status="officieel">CUSTOMS CONVENTION ON THE TEMPORARY IMPORTATION OF PRIVATE ROAD VEHICLES</titel>
      </kop>
      <aanhef>
        <preambule>
          <al>The Contracting Parties,</al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">Desiring</nadruk> to facilitate the development of international touring,</al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">Having regard</nadruk> to the aims of the Convention on Road Traffic, adopted by the United Nations Conference on Road and Motor Transport held at Geneva from 23 August to 19 September 1949 and opened for signature at Geneva on 19 September 1949,</al>
          
        </preambule>
      <afkondiging><al>
            <nadruk type="cur">Have decided</nadruk> to conclude a Convention and have agreed upon the following provisions:</al></afkondiging></aanhef>
      <wettekst>
        <hoofdstuk>
          <kop>
            <label>CHAPTER</label>
            <nr status="officieel">I</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Definitions</titel>
          </kop>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">1</nr>
            </kop>
            <al>For the purpose of this Convention:</al>
            <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
              <li>
                <li.nr>(a)</li.nr>
                <al>The term &#x2018;import duties and import taxes&#x2019; shall mean customs duties and all other duties, taxes, fees and other charges which are collected on, or in connection with, the import of goods mentioned in this Convention, but not including fees and charges limited in amount to the approximate costs of services rendered;</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>(b)</li.nr>
                <al>The term &#x201C;vehicles&#x201D; shall, unless the context otherwise requires, mean all road motor vehicles (including cycles with engines) and trailers (whether imported with the vehicle or separately), together with their component parts, and normal accessories and equipment, when imported with the vehicle;</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>(c)</li.nr>
                <al>The term &#x201C;private use&#x201D; shall exclude the transport of persons for remuneration, reward or other consideration and the industrial or commercial transport of goods with or without remuneration;</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>(d)</li.nr>
                <al>The term &#x201C;temporary importation papers&#x201D; shall include the Customs document showing the guarantee or deposit of import duties and import taxes;</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>(e)</li.nr>
                <al>The term &#x2018;persons&#x2019; shall mean both natural and legal persons;</al>
              </li>
            <li>
									<li.nr>(f)</li.nr>
									<al>The term &#x2018;issuing association&#x2019; shall mean an association authorized to issue temporary importation papers;</al>
									
								</li>
							<li>
											<li.nr>(g)</li.nr>
											<al>The term &#x2018;guaranteeing association&#x2019; shall mean an association approved by the Customs authorities of a Contracting Party to act as surety for persons using temporary importation papers;</al>
										</li>
										<li>
											<li.nr>(h)</li.nr>
											<al>The term &#x2018;international organization&#x2019; shall mean an organization to which national associations are affiliated which are entitled to issue and to guarantee temporary importation papers;</al>
										</li>
										<li>
											<li.nr>(i)</li.nr>
											<al>The term &#x2018;Contracting Party&#x2019; shall mean a State or regional economic integration organization, Party to this Convention;</al>
										</li>
										<li>
											<li.nr>(j)</li.nr>
											<al>The term &#x2018;regional economic integration organization&#x2019; shall mean an organization constituted by and composed of States as referred to in article 33, paragraph 1 of this Convention, which has competence to adopt its own legislation that is binding on its Member States, in respect of matters governed by this Convention, and has competence to decide, in accordance with its internal procedures, to accede to this Convention.</al>
										</li></lijst>
          </artikel>
        </hoofdstuk>
        <hoofdstuk>
          <kop>
            <label>CHAPTER</label>
            <nr status="officieel">II</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Importation without payment of import duties and import taxes
and free of import prohibitions and restrictions</titel>
          </kop>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">2</nr>
            </kop>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
              <al>Each of the Contracting Parties shall grant temporary admission without payment of import duties and import taxes and free of import prohibitions and restrictions, subject to re-exportation and to the other conditions laid down in this Convention, to vehicles owned by persons normally resident outside its territory which are imported and utilized, for their private use on the occasion of a temporary visit, either by the owners of the vehicles or by other persons normally resident outside its territory.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
              <al>The Contracting Parties may under the conditions set out in this Convention prescribe that such vehicles shall be covered by temporary importation papers guaranteeing payment of import duties and import taxes or an equivalent sum subject to the special provisions of article 27, paragraph 4, should the vehicles covered by temporary importation papers not be re-exported within the prescribed time limit.</al>
            </lid>
          </artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">3</nr>
            </kop>
            <al>The fuel contained in the ordinary supply tanks of vehicles temporarily imported shall be admitted without payment of import duties and import taxes and free of import prohibitions and restrictions, it being understood that the ordinary tank is that designed by the maker for the type of vehicle concerned.</al>
          </artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">4</nr>
            </kop>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
              <al>Component parts imported for the repair of a particular vehicle already temporarily imported shall be admitted temporarily without payment of import duties and import taxes and free of import prohibitions and restrictions. Contracting Parties may require these parts to be covered by temporary importation papers.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
              <al>Replaced parts which are not re-exported shall be liable to import duties and import taxes except where, in conformity with regulations of the country concerned, they may be abandoned free of all expense to the Exchequer or destroyed, under official supervision, at the expense of the parties concerned.</al>
            </lid>
          </artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">5</nr>
            </kop>
            <al>Temporary importation papers and international circulation papers intended to be issued to persons residing in the country into which the papers are imported who wish to enter other countries and which are sent to the authorized touring associations by the corresponding foreign associations, by international organizations or by the Customs authorities of the Contracting Parties shall be admitted without payment of import duties and import taxes and free of import prohibitions and restrictions.</al>
          </artikel>
        </hoofdstuk>
        <hoofdstuk>
          <kop>
            <label>CHAPTER</label>
            <nr status="officieel">III</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Issue of temporary importation papers</titel>
          </kop>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">6</nr>
            </kop>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
              <al>Subject to such guarantees and under such conditions as it may determine, each Contracting Party may authorize associations, such as those affiliated to an international organization, to issue either directly or through corresponding associations the temporary importation papers covered by this Convention.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
              <al>Temporary importation papers may be valid for a single country or Customs territory, or for several countries or Customs territories.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
              <al>The period of validity of these papers shall not exceed a year from the date of issue.</al>
            </lid>
          </artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">7</nr>
            </kop>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>

              <al>Temporary importation papers valid for the territories of all or several of the Contracting Parties shall be known as <nadruk type="cur">carnets de passages en douane</nadruk> and shall conform to the standard form contained in Annex 1 of this Convention.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
              <al>If a <nadruk type="cur">carnet de passages en douane</nadruk> is not valid for one or several territories, the issuing association shall indicate the fact on the cover and on the importation vouchers of the <nadruk type="cur">carnet.</nadruk>
              </al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
              <al>Temporary importation papers valid only for the territory of a single Contracting Party may conform to the standard form contained in Annex 2 of this Convention. Contracting Parties may also use other documents, in accordance with their legislation or regulations.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr>
              <al>The period of validity of temporary importation papers, other than those issued by authorized associations as provided for in article 6, shall be laid down by each Contracting Party in accordance with its legislation or regulations.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">5</lidnr>
              <al>Each Contracting Party shall, upon request, supply the other Contracting Parties with models of temporary importation papers valid for its territory, other than those appearing in the annexes to this Convention.</al>
            </lid>
          </artikel>
        </hoofdstuk>
        <hoofdstuk>
          <kop>
            <label>CHAPTER</label>
            <nr status="officieel">IV</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Particulars on temporary importation papers</titel>
          </kop>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">8</nr>
            </kop>
            <al>Temporary importation papers issued by authorized associations shall be made out in the name of the persons who own the vehicles temporarily imported or who have the possession or control of them provided that, if the vehicle has been hired, the papers shall be made out in the name of the hirer.</al>
          </artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">9</nr>
            </kop>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
              <al>The weight to be declared on temporary importation papers is the net weight of the vehicles. It shall be expressed in the metric system. In the case of papers valid for one country only, the Customs authorities of that country may prescribe the use of another system.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>

              <al>The value to be declared on temporary importation papers valid for one country only shall be expressed in the currency of that country. The value to be declared on a <nadruk type="cur">cornet de passages en douane</nadruk> shall be expressed in the currency of the country where the <nadruk type="cur">carnet</nadruk> is issued.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
              <al>The articles and tool-kit which form the normal equipment of vehicles need not be specially declared on the temporary importation papers.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr>
              <al>When the Customs authorities so require, parts (such as wheels, tyres, and inner tubes) and accessories not considered as constituting the normal equipment of the vehicle (such as radio sets, trailers not declared on a separate document, or luggage carriers) shall be declared on the temporary importation papers with the necessary particulars (such as weight and value) and shall be produced on exit from the country visited.</al>
            </lid>
          </artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">10</nr>
            </kop>
            <al>Any particulars inserted on temporary importation papers by the issuing association may be altered only with the approval of the issuing or guaranteeing association. No alteration to the papers may be made after they have been passed by the Customs authorities of the country of importation except with the consent of those authorities.</al>
          </artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">11</nr>
            </kop>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
              <al>Vehicles admitted under the cover of temporary importation papers may be used, for their private use, by third persons duly authorized by the holders of the papers, provided that those third persons normally reside outside the country of importation and also fulfil the other conditions laid down in this Convention. The Customs authorities of the Contracting Parties have the right to require evidence that such persons have been duly authorized by the holders of the papers and fulfil the aforesaid conditions. If this evidence does not appear sufficient, the Customs authorities may refuse use of the vehicle in their country under cover of the papers. In the case of vehicles which have been hired, each Contracting Party may, in the case of fear of abuse, require that the holder of the temporary importation paper be present at the time of importation of the vehicle.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
              <al>Notwithstanding the provisions of the preceding paragraph, the Customs authorities of the Contracting Parties may permit, in special circumstances and under conditions of which they shall be sole judges, a vehicle circulating under cover of temporary importation papers to be driven by a person who is normally resident in the country of importation, in particular when the driver drives the vehicle on behalf of or under instructions from the holder of the temporary importation papers.</al>
            </lid>
          </artikel>
        </hoofdstuk>
        <hoofdstuk>
          <kop>
            <label>CHAPTER</label>
            <nr status="officieel">V</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Conditions of temporary importation</titel>
          </kop>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">12</nr>
            </kop>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
              <al>The vehicles mentioned in the temporary importation papers shall be re-exported in the same general state, except for wear and tear, within the period of validity of such papers. In the case of vehicles which have been hired, the Customs authorities of the Contracting Parties shall have the right to require the re-exportation of the vehicle as soon as the hirer has left the country of temporary importation.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
              <al>Evidence of re-exportation shall be provided by the exit visa properly appended to the temporary importation papers by the Customs authorities of the country into which the vehicles were temporarily imported.</al>
            </lid>
          </artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">13</nr>
            </kop>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
              <al>Notwithstanding the requirement of re-exportation laid down in article 12, the re-exportation of badly damaged vehicles shall not be required, in the case of duly authenticated accidents, provided that the vehicles:</al>
              <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
                <li>
                  <li.nr>(a)</li.nr>
                  <al>are subjected to the import duties and import taxes to which they are liable; or</al>
                </li>
                <li>
                  <li.nr>(b)</li.nr>
                  <al>are abandoned free of all expenses to the Exchequer of the country into which they were imported temporarily, in which case the holder of the temporary importation papers shall be exempt from import duties and import taxes; or</al>
                </li>
                <li>
                  <li.nr>(c)</li.nr>
                  <al>are destroyed, under official supervision, at the expense of the parties concerned, any salvaged parts and materials being subjected to the import duties and import taxes to which they are liable</al>
                </li>
              </lijst>
              <al>as the Customs authorities may require.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
              <al>When a vehicle temporarily admitted cannot be re-exported as a result of a seizure, other than a seizure made at the suit of private persons, the requirement of re-exportation within the period of validity of the temporary importation papers shall be suspended for the duration of the seizure.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
              <al>The Customs authorities shall notify, so far as possible, to the guaranteeing association, seizures made by or on behalf of these Customs authorities of vehicles admitted under cover of temporary importation papers guaranteed by that association and shall advise it of the measures they intend to take.</al>
            </lid>
          <lid><lidnr>4</lidnr><al>When the vehicle or the object listed in the papers are either lost
or stolen during the course of seizure only during the period when the public
authority possesses the vehicle or the object other than a seizure made at
the suit of private persons, no import duties or import taxes can be levied
against the holder of the temporary importation papers, who should submit
evidence of seizure to the Customs Authorities. </al></lid></artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">14</nr>
            </kop>
            <al>Vehicles imported into the territory of one of the Contracting Parties under cover of temporary importation papers may not be used even incidentally for transport against payment, reward or other consideration between points within the frontiers of that territory.</al>
          </artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">15</nr>
            </kop>
            <al>Persons entitled to temporary importation facilities may, during the period of validity of temporary importation papers, import the vehicles covered by those papers as often as necessary, on condition that they have each passage (entry and exit) established by a visa of the Customs officers concerned if the Customs authorities so require. Temporary importation papers may be made valid for a single journey only.</al>
          </artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">16</nr>
            </kop>
            <al>When temporary importation papers without detachable vouchers for each passage are used, the visas given by the Customs officers between the first entry and the final exit are provisional. Nevertheless, when the last visa is a provisional exit visa, it will be admitted as proof of the re-exportation of the vehicle or component parts temporarily imported.</al>
          </artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">17</nr>
            </kop>
            <al>When temporary importation papers with a detachable voucher for each passage are used, each entry implies the passing of the document by the Customs, and each subsequent exit constitutes its final discharge, except as provided in article 18.</al>
          </artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">18</nr>
            </kop>
            <al>When the Customs authorities of a country have finally and unconditionally discharged temporary importation papers they can no longer claim from the guaranteeing association payment of import duties and import taxes, unless the certificate of discharge was obtained improperly or fraudulently.</al>
          </artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">19</nr>
            </kop>
            <al>Visas on temporary importation papers used under the conditions laid down in this Convention shall not be subject to the payment of charges for Customs attendance during the authorized hours for Customs offices and posts.</al>
          </artikel>
        </hoofdstuk>
        <hoofdstuk>
          <kop>
            <label>CHAPTER</label>
            <nr status="officieel">VI</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Extension of validity and renewal of temporary importation papers</titel>
          </kop>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">20</nr>
            </kop>
            <al>The lack of proof of re-exportation within the time allowed of vehicles temporarily imported shall be disregarded when the vehicles are presented to the Customs authorities for re-exportation within fourteen days from the expiry of the temporary entry deadline for the vehicles and satisfactory explanations of the delay are given.</al>
          </artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">21</nr>
            </kop>

            <al>Each of the Contracting Parties shall recognize as valid extensions of validity of <nadruk type="cur">carnets de passages en douane</nadruk> granted by another Contracting Party in accordance with the procedure laid down in Annex 3 of this Convention.</al>
          </artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">22</nr>
            </kop>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>

              <al>Requests for extension of validity of temporary importation papers shall be presented to the competent Customs authorities before the expiry of the period of validity of these papers, unless this is rendered impossible by <nadruk type="cur">force majeure.</nadruk> If the temporary importation paper has been issued by an authorized association, the request for extension shall be made by the association which guarantees the papers.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>

              <al>Extensions of time necessary for the re-exportation of vehicles or component parts imported temporarily shall be granted when the persons concerned can establish to the satisfaction of the Customs authorities that they are prevented by <nadruk type="cur">force majeure</nadruk> from re-exporting the said vehicles or component parts within the time allowed.</al>
            </lid>
          <lid><lidnr>3</lidnr><al>The validity of temporary importation papers can only be extended once for not more than one year. After this period, a new carnet must be issued and delivered in replacement of the former carnet.</al></lid></artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">23</nr>
            </kop>
            <al>Each of the Contracting Parties shall, unless the conditions of temporary admission are no longer satisfied, authorize, subject to whatever measures of control they may consider necessary, the renewal of temporary importation papers issued by the authorized associations and relating to vehicles or component parts temporarily imported into its territory. Requests for renewal shall be presented by the guaranteeing association.</al>
          </artikel>
        </hoofdstuk>
        <hoofdstuk>
          <kop>
            <label>CHAPTER</label>
            <nr status="officieel">VII</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Regularization of temporary importation papers</titel>
          </kop>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">24</nr>
            </kop>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>

              <al>If temporary importation papers have not been regularly discharged, the Customs authorities of the country of importation shall (whether the papers have expired or not) accept as evidence of re-exportation of the vehicle or component parts the presentation of a certificate based on the standard form shown in Annex 4 of this Convention issued by an official authority (consul, Customs, police, mayor, judicial officer, etc.), attesting the facts that the vehicle or component parts in question have been presented to it and are outside the country of importation. As an alternative they shall accept any other valid documentary evidence that the vehicle or component parts are outside the country of temporary importation. In the case of papers, other than the <nadruk type="cur">carnets de passages en douane, </nadruk>which have not expired, the papers shall be produced at the same time as the &#xE9;vidence referred to above. In the case of carnets the Customs authorities shall accept, as evidence of re-exportation of the vehicles or component parts, the visas entered thereon by the Customs authorities of countries subsequently visited.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>

              <al>In the case of the destruction, loss or theft of a temporary importation paper not regularly discharged but relating to a vehicle or component parts which have been re-exported, the Customs authorities of the country of importation shall accept as proof of re-exportation the presentation of a certificate based on the standard form shown in Annex 4 of this Convention issued by an official authority (consul, Customs, police, mayor, judicial official<noot><noot.nr>1)</noot.nr><noot.al>[Red: Lees &#x201E;officer&#x201D;.]</noot.al></noot>, etc.), attesting the facts that the vehicle or component parts in question have been presented to it and are outside the country of importation after the date of expiry of the paper. As an alternative they shall accept any other valid documentary evidence that the vehicle or component parts are outside the country of temporary importation.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
              <al>In the case of the destruction, loss or theft of a <nadruk type="cur">carnet de passages en douane</nadruk> while the vehicle or component parts to which it refers are in the territory of one of the Contracting Parties, the Customs authorities of that Party shall, at the request of the association concerned, accept a replacement document, the validity of which expires on the date of expiration of validity of the <nadruk type="cur">carnet</nadruk> which it replaces. This acceptance will annul the previous acceptance of the <nadruk type="cur">carnet</nadruk> destroyed, lost or stolen. In case of the misuse of a carnet after cancellation by the Customs authorities and the issuing association, the latter cannot be held responsible for import duties and import taxes payable. If, instead of a replacement document, an export licence or similar document is issued for the re-exportation of the vehicle or component parts, the exit visa on this licence or document shall be considered as sufficient proof of reexportation.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr>
              <al>If the vehicle is stolen after having been re-exported from the country of temporary importation, without the exit having been regularly endorsed on the temporary importation papers and in the absence of entry visas on the papers entered thereon by the Customs authorities of countries subsequently visited, the papers may nevertheless be regularized provided that the guaranteeing association furnishes the papers together with such evidence of theft as may be considered sufficient. If the temporary importation papers have not expired, the Customs authorities may require their surrender.</al>
            </lid>
          </artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">25</nr>
            </kop>
            <al>In the cases referred to in article 24, the Customs authorities shall have the right to charge a regularization fee.</al>
          </artikel>
          <artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Article</label><nr> 25 bis</nr></kop><al>The competent customs authorities shall not require payment of import duties and taxes where it is proved to their satisfaction that a vehicle imported under cover of temporary importation papers can no longer be re-exported because it has been destroyed or irrecoverably lost for reasons of force majeure.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">26</nr>
            </kop>
            <al>Customs authorities shall not have the right to require from the guaranteeing association payment of import duties and import taxes on vehicles or component parts temporarily imported when the nondischarge of the temporary importation papers has not been notified to the guaranteeing association within a year of the date of expiry of the validity of those papers. The Customs authorities shall provide the guaranteeing associations with details of the amount of import duties and import taxes within one year from the notification of the non-discharge. The guaranteeing associations' liability for these sums shall cease if such information is not furnished within this one year period.</al>
          </artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">27</nr>
            </kop>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
              <al>The guaranteeing associations shall have a period of one year from the date of notification of the non-discharge of temporary importation papers in which to furnish proof of the re-exportation of the vehicles or component parts in question under the conditions laid down in this Convention. Nevertheless, this period can come into force only as of the date of expiry of the temporary importation papers. If the Customs authorities contest the validity of the proof provided they must so inform the guarantor within a period not exceeding one year.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
              <al>If such proof is not furnished within the time limit allowed, the guaranteeing association shall deposit or pay provisionally within a maximum period of three months the import duties and import taxes payable. This deposit or payment shall become final after a period of one year from the date of the deposit or provisional payment. During the latter period, the guaranteeing association may still avail itself of the facilities provided by the preceding paragraph with a view to repayment of the sums deposited or paid.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
              <al>For countries whose regulations do not provide for the deposit or provisional payment of import duties, payments made in conformity with the provisions of the preceding paragraph will be regarded as final, it being understood that the sums paid may be refunded when the conditions laid down in this article are fulfilled.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr>
              <al>In the case of the non-discharge of temporary importation papers, the guaranteeing association shall not be required to pay a sum greater than the total of the import duties and import taxes applicable to the vehicles or component parts not re-exported, together with interest if applicable.</al>
            </lid>
          </artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">28</nr>
            </kop>
            <al>In the event of fraud, contravention or abuse the Contracting Parties shall, notwithstanding the provisions of this Convention, be free to take proceedings, against persons using temporary importation papers, for the recovery of the import duties and import taxes and also for the imposition of any penalties to which such persons have rendered themselves liable. In such cases, the guaranteeing associations shall lend their assistance to the Customs authorities.</al>
          </artikel>
        </hoofdstuk>
        <hoofdstuk>
          <kop>
            <label>CHAPTER</label>
            <nr status="officieel">VIII</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Miscellaneous Provisions</titel>
          </kop>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">29</nr>
            </kop>
            <al>The Contracting Parties shall endeavour not to introduce Customs procedures which might have the effect of impeding the development of international touring.</al>
          </artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">30</nr>
            </kop>
            <al>In order to expedite Customs procedures contiguous Contracting Parties shall endeavour to place their respective Customs posts close together and to keep them open during the same hours.</al>
          </artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">31</nr>
            </kop>
            <al>Any breach of the provisions of this Convention, any substitution, false declaration or act having the effect of causing a person or an article improperly to benefit from the system of importation laid down in this Convention, may render the offender liable in the country where the offence was committed to the penalties prescribed by the laws of that country.</al>
          </artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">32</nr>
            </kop>
            <al>Nothing in this Convention shall prevent Contracting Parties which form a customs or economic union from enacting special provisions applicable to residents of the States forming that union.</al>
          </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Article</label><nr>32 bis</nr></kop><al>This Convention shall not prevent the application of greater facilities which Contracting Parties grant or may wish to grant, either by unilateral provisions or in virtue of bilateral or multilateral agreements, provided that such facilities do not impede the application of the provisions of this Convention. The Contracting Parties are recommended to waive the request for temporary importation papers and guarantees.</al></artikel></hoofdstuk>
        <hoofdstuk>
          <kop>
            <label>CHAPTER</label>
            <nr status="officieel">IX</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Final Provisions</titel>
          </kop>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">33</nr>
            </kop>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
              <al>This Convention shall be open for signature until 31 December 1954 on behalf of any State Member of the United Nations and any other State invited to attend the United Nations Conference on Customs Formalities for the Temporary Importation of Private Road Motor Vehicles and for Tourism held in New York in May and June 1954, hereinafter referred to as the Conference.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
              <al>This Convention shall be subject to ratification and the instruments of ratification shall be deposited with the Secretary-General of the United Nations.</al>
            </lid>
          </artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">34</nr>
            </kop>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
              <al>From 1 January 1955 this Convention shall be open for accession by any State referred to in paragraph 1 of article 33 and any other State so invited by the Economic and Social Council of the United Nations. It shall also be open for accession on behalf of any Trust Territory of which the United Nations is the Administering Authority.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid><lidnr>1bis</lidnr><al>Any regional economic integration organization may become, in accordance with paragraph 1 of this article, a Contracting Party to this Convention. Such organization which has acceded to this Convention shall inform the Secretary-General of the United Nations of its competence and any subsequent changes thereto, with respect to the matters governed by this Convention. The organization and its Member States may, without however any derogation from the obligations under this Convention, decide on their respective responsibilities for the performance on their obligations under this Convention.</al></lid><lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
              <al>Accession shall be effected by the deposit of an instrument of accession with the Secretary-General of the United Nations.</al>
            </lid>
          </artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">35</nr>
            </kop>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
              <al>This Convention shall enter into force on the ninetieth day following the date of the deposit of the fifteenth instrument of ratification or accession either without reservation or with reservations accepted in accordance with article 39.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
              <al>For each State or regional economic integration organization ratifying or acceding to the Convention after the date of the deposit of the fifteenth instrument of ratification or accession in accordance with the preceding paragraph, the Convention shall enter into force on the ninetieth day following the date of the deposit by such State or regional economic integration organization of its instrument of ratification or accession either without reservation or with reservations accepted in accordance with article 39.</al>
            </lid>
          </artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">36</nr>
            </kop>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
              <al>After this Convention has been in force for three years, any Contracting Party may denounce it by so notifying the Secretary-General of the United Nations.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
              <al>Denunciation shall take effect fifteen months after the date of receipt by the Secretary-General of the United Nations of the notification of denunciation.</al>
            </lid>
          </artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">37</nr>
            </kop>
            <al>This Convention shall cease to have effect if, for any period of twelve consecutive months after its entry into force, the number of Contracting Parties is less than eight.</al>
          </artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">38</nr>
            </kop>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
              <al>Any State may, at the time of the deposit of its instrument of ratification or accession or at any time thereafter, declare by notification addressed to the Secretary-General of the United Nations that this Convention shall extend to all or any of the territories for the international relations of which it is responsible. The Convention shall extend to the territories named in the notification as from the ninetieth day after its receipt by the Secretary-General if the notification is not accompanied by a reservation, or from the ninetieth day after the notification has taken effect in accordance with article 39, or on the date on which the Convention enters into force for the State concerned, whichever is the later.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
              <al>Any State which has made a declaration under the preceding paragraph extending this Convention to any territory for whose international relations it is responsible may denounce the Convention separately in respect of that territory in accordance with the provisions of article 36.</al>
            </lid>
          </artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">39</nr>
            </kop>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
              <al>Reservations to this Convention made before the signing of the Final Act shall be admissible if they have been accepted by a majority of the members of the Conference and recorded in the Final Act.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
              <al>Reservations made after the signing of the Final Act shall not be admitted if objection is expressed by one-third of the Signatory States or of the Contracting Parties as hereinafter provided.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
              <al>The text of any reservation submitted to the Secretary-General of the United Nations by a State or a regional economic integration organization at the time of the signature, the deposit of an instrument of ratification or accession or of any notification under article 38 shall be circulated by the Secretary-General to all Contracting Parties which have at that time signed, ratified or acceded to the Convention. If one-third of these Contracting Parties expresses an objection within ninety days from the date of circulation, the reservation shall not be accepted. The Secretary-General shall notify all Contracting Parties referred to in this paragraph of any objection received by him as well as of the acceptance or rejection of the reservation.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr>
              <al>An objection by a State which has signed but not ratified the Convention shall cease to have effect if, within a period of nine months from the date of making its objection, the objecting State has not ratified the Convention. If, as the result of an objection ceasing to have effect, a reservation is accepted by application of the preceding paragraph, the Secretary-General shall so inform the Contracting Parties referred to in that paragraph. The text of any reservation shall not be circulated to any signatory State under the preceding paragraph if that State has not ratified the Convention within three years following the date of signature on its behalf.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">5</lidnr>
              <al>The Contracting Party submitting the reservation may, within a period of twelve months from the date of the notification by the Secretary-General referred to in paragraph 3 that a reservation has been rejected in accordance with the procedure provided for in that paragraph, withdraw the reservation, in which case the instrument of ratification or accession or the notification under article 38 as the case may be shall take effect with respect to such Contracting Party as from the date of the withdrawal. Pending such withdrawal, the instrument or the notification as the case may be, shall not have effect, unless, by application of the provisions of paragraph 4, the reservation is subsequently accepted.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">6</lidnr>
              <al>Reservations accepted in accordance with this article may be withdrawn at any time by notification to the Secretary-General.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">7</lidnr>
              <al>No Contracting Party shall be required to extend to a Contracting Party making a reservation the benefit of the provisions to which such reservation applies. Any Contracting Party availing itself of this right shall notify the Secretary-General accordingly and the latter shall communicate this decision to all signatory States and Contracting Parties.</al>
            </lid>
          </artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">40</nr>
            </kop>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
              <al>Any dispute between two or more Contracting Parties concerning the interpretation or application of this Convention shall so far as possible be settled by negotiation between them.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
              <al>Any dispute which is not settled by negotiation shall be submitted to arbitration if any one of the Contracting Parties in dispute so requests and shall be referred accordingly to one or more arbitrators selected by agreement between the Contracting Parties in dispute. If within three months from the date of the request for arbitration the Contracting Parties in dispute are unable to agree on the selection of an arbitrator or arbitrators, any of those Contracting Parties may request the President of the International Court of Justice to nominate a single arbitrator to whom the dispute shall be referred for decision.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
              <al>The decision of the arbitrator or arbitrators appointed under the preceding paragraph shall be binding on the Contracting Parties concerned.</al>
            </lid>
          </artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">41</nr>
            </kop>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
              <al>After this Convention has been in force for three years, any Contracting Party may, by notification to the Secretary-General of the United Nations, request that a conference be convened for the purpose of reviewing the Convention. The Secretary-General shall notify all Contracting Parties of the request and a review conference shall be convened by the Secretary-General if, within a period of four months following the date of notification by the Secretary-General, not less than one-half of the Contracting Parties notify him of their concurrence with the request.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
              <al>If a conference is convened in accordance with the preceding paragraph, the Secretary-General shall notify all Contracting Parties and invite them to submit within a period of three months such proposals as they may wish the conference to consider. The Secretary-General shall circulate to all Contracting Parties the provisional agenda for the conference together with the texts of such proposals at least three months before the date on which the conference is to meet.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
              <al>The Secretary-General shall invite to any conference convened in accordance with this article all Contracting Parties and all other States Members of the United Nations or of any of the specialized agencies.</al>
            </lid>
          </artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">42</nr>
            </kop>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
              <al>Any Contracting Party may propose one or more amendments to this Convention. The text of any proposed amendment shall be transmitted to the Secretary-General of the United Nations who shall circulate it to all Contracting Parties.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
              <al>Any proposed amendment circulated in accordance with the preceding paragraph shall be deemed to be accepted if no Contracting Party expresses an objection within a period of six months following the date of circulation of the proposed amendment by the Secretary-General. Regional economic integration oganizations which are Contracting Parties to this Convention, for the matters within their competence, shall exercise their right to express an objection. In such case the Member States of said organizations, which are Contracting Parties to this Convention, shall not be entitled to exercise individually such right.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
              <al>The Secretary-General shall notify as soon as possible all Contracting Parties whether an objection to the proposed amendment has been expressed, and if no such objection has been expressed, the amendment shall enter into force for all Contracting Parties three months after the expiration of the period of six months referred to in the preceding paragraph.</al>
            </lid>
          </artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">43</nr>
            </kop>
            <al>The Secretary-General of the United Nations shall notify all Contracting Parties and all Member States of the United Nations of the following:</al>
            <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
              <li>
                <li.nr>(a)</li.nr>
                <al>Signatures, ratifications and accessions, received in accordance with articles 33 and 34;</al>
              </li>
              <li><li.nr>(a) bis</li.nr><al>Information on the competence of regional economic integration organizations and any subsequent changes thereto in accordance with article 34, paragraph 1 bis;</al></li><li>
                <li.nr>(b)</li.nr>
                <al>The date upon which this Convention shall enter into force in accordance with article 35;</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>(c)</li.nr>
                <al>Denunciations received in accordance with article 36;</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>(d)</li.nr>
                <al>The abrogation of this Convention in accordance with article 37;</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>(e)</li.nr>
                <al>Notifications received under article 38;</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>(f)</li.nr>
                <al>Entry into force of any amendment in accordance with article 42.</al>
              </li>
            </lijst>
          </artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">44</nr>
            </kop>
            <al>The original of this Convention shall be deposited with the Secretary-General of the United Nations who shall transmit certified copies thereof to all Contracting Parties and all Member States of the United Nations.</al>
          </artikel>
        </hoofdstuk>
      </wettekst>
      <wetsluiting status="goed">
        <slotformulering>
          <al>IN WITNESS WHEREOF the undersigned, being duly authorized thereto, have signed this Convention.</al>
          <al>DONE at New York this fourth day of June, one thousand nine hundred and fifty-four, in a single copy in the English, French and Spanish languages, each text being equally authentic.</al>
          <al>The Secretary-General is requested to prepare an authoritative translation of this Convention in the Chinese and Russian languages and to add the Chinese and Russian texts to the English, French and Spanish texts when transmitting certified copies thereof to the States in accordance with article 44 of this Convention.</al>
        </slotformulering>
      </wetsluiting>
    </verdragtekst>
    <verdragtekst>
      <kop>
        <label>Annex</label>
        <nr status="officieel">1</nr>
        <titel status="officieel">&#x201C;GARNET DE PASSAGES EN DOUANE&#x201D;</titel>
      </kop>
      <vrije-tekst>
        <tekst status="goed">
          <al>The &#x201C;Carnet&#x201D; is issued in English and French</al><al> The dimensions are 21 x 29.7 cm.</al>
							<al>The issuing association shall insert its name on each voucher and shall include the initials of the international organization to which it belongs.</al>
							<plaatje>
								<illustratie bin-id="10000055036" formaat="gif" kleur="nee" naam="TRB-1993-003_01.gif" url="http://wetten.overheid.nl/Illustration/10000055036"/>
							</plaatje>
							
							<plaatje>
								<illustratie bin-id="10000055037" formaat="gif" kleur="nee" naam="TRB-1993-003_02.gif" url="http://wetten.overheid.nl/Illustration/10000055037"/>
							</plaatje>
							
							<plaatje>
								<illustratie bin-id="10000055038" formaat="gif" kleur="nee" naam="TRB-1993-003_03.gif" url="http://wetten.overheid.nl/Illustration/10000055038"/>
							</plaatje>
							<tussenkop>&#x2039;&#x399;nside back cover / Int&#xE9;rieur du dos de la couverture&#x203A;</tussenkop>
							<al>The following information is provided by the issuing association to motorists.</al>
							<al>L'association qui a d&#xE9;livr&#xE9; le pr&#xE9;sent carnet fournit les renseignements suivants aux usagers.</al>
							<tussenkop>&#x2039;Back cover / Ext&#xE9;rieur du dos de la couverture&#x203A;</tussenkop>
							
							<al>This carnet, which has been drawn up in accordance with the provisions of the Customs Conventions on the Temporary importation of Private Road Vehicles (1954) and Commercial Road Vehicles (1956), may be used in the following countries under the guarantee of the authorized associations indicated:/</al>
							<al>Ce carnet, qui a &#xE9;t&#xE9; &#xE9;labor&#xE9; selon les dispositions des Conventions douani&#xE8;res relatives &#xE0; l'importation temporaire des v&#xE9;hicules routiers priv&#xE9;s (1954) et des v&#xE9;hicules routiers commerciaux (1956), peut &#xEA;tre utilise dans les pays suivants, sous la garantie des associations autoris&#xE9;es ci-apr&#xE8;s:</al>
							<al>(LIST OF COUNTRIES AND AUTHORIZED ASSOCIATIONS)</al>
							<al>(LISTE DES PAYS ET ASSOCIATIONS AUTORISEES)</al>
							<plaatje>
								<illustratie bin-id="10000055041" formaat="gif" kleur="nee" naam="TRB-1993-003_04.gif" url="http://wetten.overheid.nl/Illustration/10000055041"/>
							</plaatje>
        </tekst>
      </vrije-tekst>
    </verdragtekst>
    <verdragtekst>
      <kop>
        <label>Annex</label>
        <nr status="officieel">2</nr>
        <titel status="officieel">TRIPTYCH</titel>
      </kop>
      <vrije-tekst>
        <tekst status="goed">
          <al>The triptych should be printed in the national language of the country of importation and, if desired, also in one other language.</al>
          <al>The dimensions are 13 x 29.5 cm.</al>
          <plaatje>
            <illustratie bin-id="10000055070" display="block" formaat="gif" kleur="nee" naam="TRB-1955-123_06.gif" type="tekst" uitlijning="start" url="http://wetten.overheid.nl/Illustration/10000055070"/>
          </plaatje>
          <plaatje>
            <illustratie bin-id="10000055071" display="block" formaat="gif" kleur="nee" naam="TRB-1955-123_07.gif" type="tekst" uitlijning="start" url="http://wetten.overheid.nl/Illustration/10000055071"/>
          </plaatje>
        </tekst>
      </vrije-tekst>
    </verdragtekst>
    
    <verdragtekst>
      <kop>
        <label>Annex</label>
        <nr status="officieel">3</nr>
        <titel status="officieel">EXTENSION OF VALIDITY OF THE &#x201C;CARNET DE PASSAGES EN DOUANE&#x201D;</titel>
      </kop>
      <wettekst>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <nr status="officieel">1</nr>
          </kop>
          <al>The stamp for extension of validity shall conform to the model contained in this annex.</al>
											<al>The stamp shall be drawn up in English or French. The inscribed wording may be repeated in another language.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <nr status="officieel">2</nr>
          </kop>
          <al>The following procedure shall be observed by the person requesting the extension and by the guaranteeing association dealing with the request:</al>
          <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
            <li>
              <li.nr>(a)</li.nr>
              <al> As soon as the holder of a <nadruk type="cur">carnet de passages en douane</nadruk> realizes that he is obliged to request an extension of the period of validity of the document, he sends to the guaranteeing association the <nadruk type="cur">carnet</nadruk> and a request for extension, indicating the circumstances which oblige him to make the request. He will submit with his request, as supporting evidence, such papers as a medical certificate, a statement from the garage repairing his vehicle, or any other authentic document showing that the delay in question is caused by <nadruk type="cur">force majeure</nadruk>.</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr> (b)</li.nr>

              <al>If the guaranteeing association considers that the request for extension might be passed on to the Customs authorities, it stamps the cover of the <nadruk type="cur">carnet de passages en douane</nadruk> in the space specially reserved for this purpose.</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>(c)</li.nr>
              <al>In the left-hand side of the stamp the guaranteeing association fills in the date, in figures and words, until which the extension is requested. The President or representative of the association signs and the stamp of the association is affixed.</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>(d)</li.nr>

              <al>The length of the extension must not exceed a reasonable period necessary to complete the journey, and should not normally exceed three months from the previous date of expiry of the <nadruk type="cur">carnet</nadruk>.</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>(e)</li.nr>
              <al>The guraranteeing association then sends the <nadruk type="cur">carnet</nadruk> to the competent Customs authority of its country. The request made by the holder of the <nadruk type="cur">carnet</nadruk> and the supporting evidence are attached to the <nadruk type="cur">carnet.</nadruk>
              </al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>(f)</li.nr>

              <al>The Customs authority decides whether the extension shall be granted. It may reduce the period of extension requested, or refuse to grant any extension. If it is granted, the competent Customs officer completes the stamp placed on the cover of the <nadruk type="cur">carnet</nadruk> by the guaranteeing association, by adding a serial or registry number, the place and date and his own official position. He then signs and adds the Customs stamp.</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>(g)</li.nr>
              <al>The <nadruk type="cur">carnet</nadruk> is then returned to the guaranteeing association, which in turn returns it to the person concerned.</al>
            </li>
          </lijst>
          <plaatje>
            <illustratie bin-id="10000055072" display="block" formaat="gif" kleur="nee" naam="TRB-1955-123_10.gif" type="tekst" uitlijning="start" url="http://wetten.overheid.nl/Illustration/10000055072"/>
          </plaatje>
        </artikel>
      </wettekst>
    </verdragtekst>
    <verdragtekst>
      <kop>
        <label>Annex</label>
        <nr status="officieel">4</nr>
        <titel status="officieel">MODEL CERTIFICATE FOR THE ADJUSTMENT OF UNDISCHARGED, DESTROYED, LOST OR STOLEN TEMPORARY IMPORTATION PAPERS</titel>
      </kop>
      <vrije-tekst>
        <tekst status="goed">
          <plaatje>
            <illustratie bin-id="10000055040" display="block" formaat="gif" kleur="nee" naam="TRB-1955-123_11.gif" type="tekst" uitlijning="start" url="http://wetten.overheid.nl/Illustration/10000055040"/>
          </plaatje>
        </tekst>
      </vrije-tekst>
    </verdragtekst>
  </verdrag>
<verdrag tekst="vertaling" xml:lang="nl">
				<verdragtekst>
					<kop>
						<titel>DOUANEVERDRAG INZAKE DE TIJDELIJKE INVOER VAN PARTICULIERE WEGVOERTUIGEN</titel>
						</kop>
					<aanhef>
						<preambule><al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al></preambule></aanhef>
					<wettekst>
						<hoofdstuk>
							<kop>
								<label>HOOFDSTUK</label>
								<nr>I</nr>
								<titel>Begripsomschrijvingen</titel>
							</kop>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>1</nr>
								</kop>
								<al>Voor de toepassing van dit Verdrag wordt verstaan:</al>
								<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." type="expliciet">
									<li>
										<li.nr>a)</li.nr>
										<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
									</li>
									<li>
										<li.nr>b)</li.nr>
										<al>onder &#x201E;voertuigen&#x201D;, tenzij het zinsverband het tegendeel vereist, alle motorvoertuigen welke voor het vervoer langs de weg worden gebezigd (daaronder begrepen rijwielen met hulpmotor) en aanhangwagens (met het voertuig zelf dan wel afzonderlijk ingevoerd), alsmede de bijbehorende reservedelen, de normale toebehoren en uitrusting, welke te zamen met het voertuig zijn ingevoerd;</al>
									</li>
									<li>
										<li.nr>c)</li.nr>
										<al>onder &#x201E;persoonlijk gebruik&#x201D; het gebruik voor andere doeleinden dan: 1&#xB0;. het vervoer van personen tegen betaling, beloning of ander materieel voordeel; 2&#xB0;. het bedrijfsmatige vervoer van goederen, al dan niet tegen betaling;</al>
									</li>
									<li>
										<li.nr>d)</li.nr>
										<al>onder &#x201E;Bewijs van tijdelijke invoer&#x201D; het douanedocument blijkens hetwelk voor de rechten en heffingen ter zake van de invoer zekerheid is gesteld dan wel consignatie heeft plaatsgevonden;</al>
									</li>
									<li>
										<li.nr>e)</li.nr>
										<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
									</li>
								<li>
										<li.nr>f)</li.nr>
										<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
									</li>
								<li>
										<li.nr>g)</li.nr>
										<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
									</li>
								<li>
										<li.nr>h)</li.nr>
										<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
									</li>
								<li>
										<li.nr>h)</li.nr>
										<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
									</li>
								<li>
										<li.nr>i)</li.nr>
										<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
									</li><li>
										<li.nr>j)</li.nr>
										<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
									</li>
								</lijst>
							</artikel>
						</hoofdstuk>
						<hoofdstuk>
							<kop>
								<label>HOOFDSTUK</label>
								<nr>II</nr>
								<titel>Invoer met vrijstelling van rechten en heffingen ter zake van de invoer en zonder toepassing van invoerverboden en invoerbeperkingen</titel>
							</kop>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>2</nr>
								</kop>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>1</lidnr>
									<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>2</lidnr>
									<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
								</lid>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>3</nr>
								</kop>
								<al>Met vrijstelling van rechten en heffingen ter zake van de invoer en zonder toepassing van invoerverboden en invoerbeperkingen wordt toegelaten de motorbrandstof welke zich bevindt in de normale tanks van de tijdelijk ingevoerde voertuigen, met dien verstande dat als de normale tank wordt beschouwd de tank welke door de fabrikant is ontworpen voor het desbetreffende type van het voertuig.</al>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>4</nr>
								</kop>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>1</lidnr>
									<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>2</lidnr>
									<al>De vervangen onderdelen welke niet weder worden uitgevoerd, zijn onderworpen aan rechten en heffingen ter zake van de invoer, tenzij zij overeenkomstig de bepalingen van het betrokken land vrij van alle kosten ten gunste van de Schatkist worden afgestaan of wel onder ambtelijk toezicht op kosten van belanghebbenden worden vernietigd.</al>
								</lid>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>5</nr>
								</kop>
								<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
							</artikel>
						</hoofdstuk>
						<hoofdstuk>
							<kop>
								<label>HOOFDSTUK</label>
								<nr>III</nr>
								<titel>Afgifte van Bewijzen van tijdelijke invoer</titel>
							</kop>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>6</nr>
								</kop>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>1</lidnr>
									<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>2</lidnr>
									<al>De Bewijzen van tijdelijke invoer kunnen geldig zijn voor &#xE9;&#xE9;n land of douanegebied dan wel voor verschillende landen of douanegebieden.</al>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>3</lidnr>
									<al>De geldigheidsduur van deze Bewijzen mag niet langer zijn dan &#xE9;&#xE9;n jaar, te rekenen van de dag van afgifte.</al>
								</lid>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>7</nr>
								</kop>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>1</lidnr>
									<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>2</lidnr>
									<al>Indien het &#x201E;carnet de passages en douane&#x201D; voor een of meer gebieden niet geldig is, moet dit door de organisatie die het Bewijs afgeeft, worden vermeld op de omslag en op de invoerstroken van het &#x201E;carnet&#x201D;.</al>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>3</lidnr>
									<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>4</lidnr>
									<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>5</lidnr>
									<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
								</lid>
							</artikel>
						</hoofdstuk>
						<hoofdstuk>
							<kop>
								<label>HOOFDSTUK</label>
								<nr>IV</nr>
								<titel>Bijzonderheden welke op de Bewijzen van tijdelijke invoer moeten worden vermeld</titel>
							</kop>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>8</nr>
								</kop>
								<al>De Bewijzen van tijdelijke invoer, afgegeven door gemachtigde organisaties, worden gesteld op naam van de eigenaars of op naam van de houders van de tijdelijk ingevoerde voertuigen. In de gevallen dat het gehuurde voertuigen betreft, moeten de Bewijzen worden gesteld op naam van de huurder<noot><noot.nr>1)</noot.nr><noot.al>[Red: Voor de vertaling is op deze plaats, waar de Engelse tekst (&#x201C;hirer&#x201D;) en de Franse tekst (&#x201E;loueur&#x201D;) niet met elkaar overeenstemmen, de Engelse tekst gevolgd.]</noot.al></noot>.</al>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>9</nr>
								</kop>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>1</lidnr>
									<al>Het gewicht dat op de Bewijzen van tijdelijke invoer moet worden vermeld, is het eigen gewicht van het voertuig. Het moet worden uitgedrukt volgens het metrieke stelsel. Indien de Bewijzen slechts geldig zijn voor &#xE9;&#xE9;n enkel land, kunnen de douane-autoriteiten van dat land het gebruik van een ander stelsel voorschrijven.</al>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>2</lidnr>
									<al>De op de Bewijzen van tijdelijke invoer te vermelden waarde moet, indien bedoelde Bewijzen slechts voor &#xE9;&#xE9;n enkel land geldig zijn, worden uitgedrukt in de geldsoort van dat land. De waarde welke op een &#x201E;carnet de passages en douane&#x201D; moet worden vermeld, dient te zijn uitgedrukt in de geldsoort van het land waar het &#x201E;carnet&#x201D; is afgegeven.</al>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>3</lidnr>
									<al>Voorwerpen en gereedschappen welke tot de normale uitrusting van voertuigen behoren, behoeven niet afzonderlijk op de Bewijzen van tijdelijke invoer te worden vermeld.</al>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>4</lidnr>
									<al>Indien de douane-autoriteiten zulks vorderen, moeten reservedelen (zoals wielen, binnen- en buitenbanden), alsmede toebehoren welke niet geacht worden tot de normale uitrusting van het voertuig te behoren (zoals radio-ontvangtoestellen, aanhangwagens waarvoor geen afzonderlijk Bewijs is afgegeven, en bagagedragers) op de Bewijzen van tijdelijke invoer worden vermeld met aanduiding van de nodige bijzonderheden (zoals gewicht en waarde). Bij het verlaten van het land dat is bezocht, moeten genoemde delen en toebehoren worden getoond.</al>
								</lid>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>10</nr>
								</kop>
								<al>Elke wijziging die wordt aangebracht in hetgeen op de Bewijzen van tijdelijke invoer is vermeld door de organisatie die de Bewijzen heeft afgegeven, dient door deze organisatie of door de aansprakelijke organisatie behoorlijk te zijn goedgekeurd. Zonder toestemming van de douane-autoriteiten van het land van invoer is geen enkele wijziging toegestaan, nadat de Bewijzen door die autoriteiten voor invoer zijn afgetekend.</al>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>11</nr>
								</kop>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>1</lidnr>
									<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>2</lidnr>
									<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
								</lid>
							</artikel>
						</hoofdstuk>
						<hoofdstuk>
							<kop>
								<label>HOOFDSTUK</label>
								<nr>V</nr>
								<titel>Voorwaarden voor de tijdelijke invoer</titel>
							</kop>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>12</nr>
								</kop>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>1</lidnr>
									<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>2</lidnr>
									<al>Dat de wederuitvoer heeft plaatsgehad, blijkt uit de omstandigheid dat het Bewijs van tijdelijke invoer op regelmatige wijze voor uitvoer is afgetekend door de douane-autoriteiten van het land waar de voertuigen tijdelijk werden ingevoerd.</al>
								</lid>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>13</nr>
								</kop>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>1</lidnr>
									<al>De in artikel 12 neergelegde verplichting tot wederuitvoer geldt niet ten aanzien van voertuigen welke ernstig beschadigd zijn ten gevolge van een ongeval, waarvan op afdoende wijze wordt aangetoond dat het heeft plaatsgehad, mits, al naar gelang de douaneautoriteiten zulks vorderen, de voertuigen</al>
									<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." type="expliciet">
										<li>
											<li.nr>a)</li.nr>
											<al>of wel worden onderworpen aan de rechten en heffingen ter zake van de invoer verschuldigd;</al>
										</li>
										<li>
											<li.nr>b)</li.nr>
											<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
										</li>
										<li>
											<li.nr>c)</li.nr>
											<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
										
										</li>
									</lijst>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>2</lidnr>
									<al>Indien een voertuig dat tijdelijk ten invoer is toegelaten niet weder kan worden uitgevoerd als gevolg van inbeslagneming of beslaglegging, anders dan op vordering van particulieren tot stand gekomen, wordt de verplichting tot wederuitvoer binnen de geldigheidsduur van het Bewijs van tijdelijke invoer opgeschort voor de duur van het beslag.</al>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>3</lidnr>
									<al>Van de gevallen waarin de douane-autoriteiten voertuigen waarvoor de aansprakelijke organisaties Bewijzen van tijdelijke invoer hebben afgegeven, in beslag hebben genomen of hebben doen nemen, dan wel daarop beslag hebben gelegd of doen leggen, geven zij voor zover mogelijk kennis aan die organisaties. Zij doen voorts mededeling aan bedoelde organisaties van de maatregelen welke zij voornemens zijn te treffen.</al>
								</lid>
							<lid><lidnr>4</lidnr><al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
										</lid></artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>14</nr>
								</kop>
								<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>15</nr>
								</kop>
								<al>Zij die aanspraak kunnen maken op de tijdelijke invoer, mogen binnen de geldigheidsduur van de Bewijzen van tijdelijke invoer de daarop vermelde voertuigen invoeren zo vaak als nodig is, mits zij bij elke grensoverschrijding (binnenkomen en uitgaan) de Bewijzen door de betrokken douane-ambtenaren doen aftekenen voor zover de douane-autoriteiten zulks vorderen. Er kunnen echter Bewijzen worden afgegeven voor &#xE9;&#xE9;n enkele reis.</al>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>16</nr>
								</kop>
								<al>Indien gebruik wordt gemaakt van Bewijzen van tijdelijke invoer welke niet zijn voorzien van stroken die bij elke grensoverschrijding kunnen worden uitgescheurd, hebben de aftekeningen door de douane tussen de eerste binnenkomst en het laatste uitgaan een voorlopig karakter. Indien de laatste aftekening een voorlopige aftekening voor uitgaan is, wordt die aftekening niettemin toegelaten als bewijs van de wederuitvoer van de tijdelijk ingevoerde voertuigen of losse onderdelen.</al>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>17</nr>
								</kop>
								<al>Indien gebruik wordt gemaakt van Bewijzen van tijdelijke invoer welke voorzien zijn van stroken die bij elke grensoverschrijding kunnen worden uitgescheurd, brengt elke bevinding van binnenkomst met zich mede dat het Bewijs door de douane voor invoer moet worden afgetekend, en wordt het Bewijs door iedere vaststelling van latere uitvoer definitief gezuiverd, onverminderd de bepalingen van artikel 18.</al>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>18</nr>
								</kop>
								<al>Indien het Bewijs van tijdelijke invoer blijkens de daarop voorkomende aantekeningen van de douane-autoriteiten van een land definitief en zonder voorbehoud is gezuiverd, kunnen die autoriteiten van de aansprakelijke organisatie de betaling van de rechten en heffingen ter zake van de invoer niet meer vorderen, tenzij de zuivering ten onrechte of op frauduleuze wijze werd verkregen.</al>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>19</nr>
								</kop>
								<al>Het aftekenen van Bewijzen van tijdelijke invoer welke op de voet van dit Verdrag worden gebruikt, geeft geen aanleiding tot betaling van kosten als vergoeding voor de verrichtingen van de douane gedurende de uren van openstelling van de douanekantoren.</al>
							</artikel>
						</hoofdstuk>
						<hoofdstuk>
							<kop>
								<label>HOOFDSTUK</label>
								<nr>VI</nr>
								<titel>Verlenging van de geldigheidsduur en vernieuwing van de Bewijzen van tijdelijke invoer</titel>
							</kop>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>20</nr>
								</kop>
								<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>21</nr>
								</kop>
								<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>22</nr>
								</kop>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>1</lidnr>
									<al>Aanvragen tot verlenging van de geldigheidsduur van Bewijzen van tijdelijke invoer moeten, behoudens in geval van overmacht, v&#xF3;&#xF3;r het verstrijken van de geldigheidsduur bij de bevoegde douane-autoriteiten worden ingediend. Indien het Bewijs van tijdelijke invoer is afgegeven door een gemachtigde organisatie, moet het verzoek om verlenging door de aansprakelijke organisatie worden ingediend.</al>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>2</lidnr>
									<al>Verlenging van de geldigheidsduur voor de tijd welke nodig is voor de wederuitvoer van de tijdelijk ingevoerde voertuigen of losse onderdelen, wordt toegestaan indien de belanghebbenden ten genoegen van de douane-autoriteiten kunnen aantonen dat zij door overmacht verhinderd zijn bedoelde voertuigen of losse onderdelen binnen de gestelde termijn weder uit te voeren.</al>
								</lid>
							<lid><lidnr>3</lidnr><al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al></lid></artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>23</nr>
								</kop>
								<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
							</artikel>
						</hoofdstuk>
						<hoofdstuk>
							<kop>
								<label>HOOFDSTUK</label>
								<nr>VII</nr>
								<titel>Regularisatie van Bewijzen van tijdelijke invoer</titel>
							</kop>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>24</nr>
								</kop>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>1</lidnr>
									<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>2</lidnr>
									<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>3</lidnr>
									<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>4</lidnr>
									<al>Indien een voertuig is gestolen nadat het weder uit het land van invoer is uitgevoerd zonder dat van het uitgaan op regelmatige wijze aantekening is gesteld op het Bewijs van tijdelijke invoer en zonder dat het Bewijs door de douane-autoriteiten van de landen waar het voertuig vervolgens heeft gereden, voor invoer is afgetekend, kan het Bewijs niettemin worden geregulariseerd, mits het wordt overgelegd door de aansprakelijke organisatie en deze de diefstal voldoende aannemelijk maakt. Indien de geldigheidsduur van het Bewijs niet is verstreken, kunnen de douane-autoriteiten vorderen dat het wordt overgelegd.</al>
								</lid>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>25</nr>
								</kop>
								<al>De douane-autoriteiten behouden zich het recht voor in de gevallen bedoeld in artikel 24 kosten voor regularisatie te heffen.</al>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Artikel</label><nr>25 bis</nr></kop><al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al></artikel><artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>26</nr>
								</kop>
								<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>27</nr>
								</kop>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>1</lidnr>
									<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>2</lidnr>
									<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>3</lidnr>
									<al>In de landen welker voorschriften niet voorzien in consignatie of voorlopige betaling van rechten en heffingen ter zake van de invoer, hebben de betalingen die overeenkomstig de bepalingen van het vorige lid zijn gedaan een definitief karakter, met dien verstande evenwel, dat de betaalde bedragen kunnen worden teruggegeven indien aan de voorwaarden van dit artikel is voldaan.</al>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>4</lidnr>
									<al>Indien het Bewijs van tijdelijke invoer niet is gezuiverd, kan de aansprakelijke organisatie niet worden verplicht meer te betalen dan het bedrag van de rechten en heffingen ter zake van de invoer die verschuldigd zijn voor het voertuig of voor de losse onderdelen, welke niet weder werden uitgevoerd, eventueel vermeerderd met de rente wegens achterstallige betaling.</al>
								</lid>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>28</nr>
								</kop>
								<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
							</artikel>
						</hoofdstuk>
						<hoofdstuk>
							<kop>
								<label>HOOFDSTUK</label>
								<nr>VIII</nr>
								<titel>Verschillende bepalingen</titel>
							</kop>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>29</nr>
								</kop>
								<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>30</nr>
								</kop>
								<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>31</nr>
								</kop>
								<al>Elke inbreuk op de bepalingen van dit Verdrag, elke verwisseling, valse verklaring of handeling, die tot gevolg heeft dat ten aanzien van een persoon of een voorwerp de in dit Verdrag neergelegde bepalingen met betrekking tot de tijdelijke invoer ten onrechte worden toegepast, stelt de overtreder in het land waar de overtreding is begaan, bloot aan de straffen welke zijn voorzien in de wetgeving van dat land.</al>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>32</nr>
								</kop>
								<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
							</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>32 bis</nr></kop><al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al></artikel></hoofdstuk>
						<hoofdstuk>
							<kop>
								<label>HOOFDSTUK</label>
								<nr>IX</nr>
								<titel>Slotbepalingen</titel>
							</kop>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>33</nr>
								</kop>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>1</lidnr>
									<al>Dit Verdrag staat tot en met 31 december 1954 open voor ondertekening namens iedere Staat die lid is van de Organisatie van de Verenigde Naties en namens elke andere Staat die is uitgenodigd deel te nemen aan de Conferentie van de Verenigde Naties nopens douaneformaliteiten met betrekking tot de tijdelijke invoer van voertuigen gebezigd in het toeristenverkeer en met betrekking tot het toeristenverkeer, welke Conferentie in mei en juni 1954 te New York is gehouden en die hierna zal worden aangeduid als &#x201E;de Conferentie&#x201D;.</al>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>2</lidnr>
									<al>Dit Verdrag is onderworpen aan bekrachtiging en de akten van bekrachtiging zullen worden nedergelegd bij de Secretaris-Generaal van de Verenigde Naties.</al>
								</lid>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>34</nr>
								</kop>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>1</lidnr>
									<al>Van 1 januari 1955 af kan elke Staat, bedoeld in het eerste lid van artikel 33, en elke andere Staat die hiertoe wordt uitgenodigd door de Economische en Sociale Raad van de Verenigde Naties, tot dit Verdrag toetreden. Toetreding zal eveneens mogelijk zijn namens elk trustgebied waarvoor de Organisatie van de Verenigde Naties de beherende Autoriteit is.</al>
								</lid>
								<lid><lidnr>1bis</lidnr><al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al></lid><lid>
									<lidnr>2</lidnr>
									<al>De toetreding geschiedt door nederlegging van een akte van toetreding bij de Secretaris-Generaal van de Verenigde Naties.</al>
								</lid>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>35</nr>
								</kop>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>1</lidnr>
									<al>Dit Verdrag treedt in werking op de negentigste dag na de datum van nederlegging van de vijftiende akte van bekrachtiging of van toetreding, hetzij zonder voorbehoud, hetzij onder voorbehoud dat overeenkomstig de bepalingen van artikel 39 is aanvaard.</al>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>2</lidnr>
									<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
								</lid>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>36</nr>
								</kop>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>1</lidnr>
									<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>2</lidnr>
									<al>De opzegging zal van kracht worden vijftien maanden na de datum van ontvangst van de kennisgeving van opzegging door de Secretaris-Generaal van de Verenigde Naties.</al>
								</lid>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>37</nr>
								</kop>
								<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>38</nr>
								</kop>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>1</lidnr>
									<al>Elke Staat kan ten tijde der nederlegging van zijn akte van bekrachtiging of van toetreding of te eniger tijd daarna door middel van een aan de Secretaris-Generaal van de Verenigde Naties gerichte kennisgeving verklaren, dat dit Verdrag van toepassing zal zijn ten aanzien van alle of een deel van de gebieden, welker internationale betrekkingen hij behartigt. Het Verdrag zal van toepassing zijn ten aanzien van de in de kennisgeving genoemde gebieden met ingang van de negentigste dag na ontvangst van die kennisgeving door de Secretaris-Generaal, indien de kennisgeving is gedaan zonder voorbehoud, of met ingang van de negentigste dag nadat de kennisgeving ingevolge artikel 39 van kracht zal zijn geworden, dan wel op de datum waarop het Verdrag ten aanzien van de desbetreffende Staat in werking treedt, zijnde de laatste van deze tijdstippen beslissend.</al>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>2</lidnr>
									<al>Elke Staat die overeenkomstig het voorgaande lid een verklaring heeft afgelegd waardoor dit Verdrag van toepassing wordt ten aanzien van een gebied welks internationale betrekkingen hij behartigt, kan het Verdrag overeenkomstig de bepalingen van artikel 36 met betrekking tot dit gebied afzonderlijk opzeggen.</al>
								</lid>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>39</nr>
								</kop>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>1</lidnr>
									<al>Een voorbehoud met betrekking tot dit Verdrag, gemaakt v&#xF3;&#xF3;r de ondertekening van de Slotakte, wordt toegelaten indien het door de Conferentie bij meerderheid van stemmen is aanvaard en in de Slotakte is neergelegd.</al>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>2</lidnr>
									<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>3</lidnr>
									<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>4</lidnr>
									<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>5</lidnr>
									<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>6</lidnr>
									<al>Een voorbehoud dat overeenkomstig dit artikel is aanvaard, kan te allen tijde worden ingetrokken door een daartoe strekkende, aan de Secretaris-Generaal gerichte kennisgeving.</al>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>7</lidnr>
									<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
								</lid>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>40</nr>
								</kop>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>1</lidnr>
									<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>2</lidnr>
									<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>3</lidnr>
									<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
								</lid>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>41</nr>
								</kop>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>1</lidnr>
									<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>2</lidnr>
									<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>3</lidnr>
									<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
								</lid>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>42</nr>
								</kop>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>1</lidnr>
									<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>2</lidnr>
									<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
								</lid>
								<lid>
									<lidnr>3</lidnr>
									<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
								</lid>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>43</nr>
								</kop>
								<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
								<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." type="expliciet">
									<li>
										<li.nr>a)</li.nr>
										<al>Ondertekeningen, bekrachtigingen en toetredingen welke zijn ontvangen overeenkomstig de artikelen 33 en 34;</al>
									</li>
									<li><li.nr>a) bis</li.nr><al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al></li><li>
										<li.nr>b)</li.nr>
										<al>De datum waarop dit Verdrag overeenkomstig artikel 35 in werking zal treden;</al>
									</li>
									<li>
										<li.nr>c)</li.nr>
										<al>Opzeggingen welke zijn ontvangen overeenkomstig artikel 36;</al>
									</li>
									<li>
										<li.nr>d)</li.nr>
										<al>De intrekking van dit Verdrag overeenkomstig artikel 37;</al>
									</li>
									<li>
										<li.nr>e)</li.nr>
										<al>Kennisgevingen welke zijn ontvangen overeenkomstig artikel 38;</al>
										
									</li>
								<li>
												<li.nr>f)</li.nr>
												<al>De inwerkingtreding van elke wijziging overeenkomstig artikel 42.</al>
											</li></lijst>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<label>Artikel</label>
									<nr>44</nr>
								</kop>
								<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
							</artikel>
						</hoofdstuk>
					</wettekst>
					<wetsluiting status="goed">
						<slotformulering>
							<al>TEN BLIJKE WAARVAN de ondergetekenden, daartoe behoorlijk gevolmachtigd, dit Verdrag hebben ondertekend.</al>
							<al>GEDAAN te New York, de vierde juni negentienhonderd vierenvijftig, in &#xE9;&#xE9;n exemplaar, in de Engelse, Spaanse en Franse taal, zijnde de drie teksten gelijkelijk authentiek.</al>
							<al>Aan de Secretaris-Generaal is verzocht van dit Verdrag een rechtskracht hebbende vertaling in de Chinese en Russische taal op te maken en deze Chinese en Russische teksten te voegen bij de Engelse, Spaanse en Franse teksten, wanneer hij de in artikel 44 van dit Verdrag bedoelde gewaarmerkte afschriften aan de Staten doet toekomen.</al>
							
							
						</slotformulering>
					</wetsluiting>
				</verdragtekst>
				<verdragtekst>
					<kop>
						<label>Bijlage</label>
						<nr>1</nr>
						<titel>&#x201E;CARNET DE PASSAGES EN DOUANE&#x201D;</titel>
					</kop>
					<vrije-tekst>
						<tekst status="goed">
							<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
							
						</tekst>
					</vrije-tekst>
				</verdragtekst>
				<verdragtekst>
					<kop>
						<label>Bijlage</label>
						<nr>2</nr>
						<titel>TRIPTIEK</titel>
					</kop>
					<vrije-tekst>
						<tekst status="goed">
							<al>Alle gedrukte aanwijzingen op de triptiek zijn gesteld in de taal van het land van invoer; zij kunnen er bovendien nog in een andere taal op voorkomen.</al>
							<al>De afmetingen zijn 13 X 29,5 cm.</al>
							<plaatje>
								<illustratie bin-id="10000055073" formaat="gif" kleur="nee" naam="TRB-1956-110_06.gif" url="http://wetten.overheid.nl/Illustration/10000055073"/>
							</plaatje>
							
							<plaatje>
								<illustratie bin-id="10000055074" formaat="gif" kleur="nee" naam="TRB-1956-110_07.gif" url="http://wetten.overheid.nl/Illustration/10000055074"/>
							</plaatje>
							
						</tekst>
					</vrije-tekst>
				</verdragtekst>
				
				<verdragtekst>
					<kop>
						<label>Bijlage</label>
						<nr>3</nr>
						<titel>VERLENGING VAN DE GELDIGHEIDSDUUR VAN HET &#x201E;CARNET DE PASSAGES EN DOUANE&#x201D; </titel>
					</kop>
					<vrije-tekst>
						<tekst status="goed">
							
						<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al></tekst>
					</vrije-tekst>
				</verdragtekst>
				<verdragtekst>
					<kop>
						<label>Bijlage</label>
						<nr>4</nr>
						<titel>MODEL VAN CERTIFICAAT VOOR DE REGULARISATIE VAN NIET-GEZUIVERDE, TENIET GEGANE, VERLOREN GERAAKTE OF GESTOLEN BEWIJZEN VAN TIJDELIJKE INVOER</titel>
					</kop>
					<vrije-tekst>
						<tekst status="goed">
							<al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de veratling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al>
							
						</tekst>
					</vrije-tekst>
				</verdragtekst>
			</verdrag></wetgeving>
  	