<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE wetgeving SYSTEM "http://wetten.overheid.nl/dtd/bwb-plus-meta-1_61w.dtd">
<wetgeving bwb-id="BWBV0004940" dtdversie="2.0" id="10000044149" sleutel="V4403" verdragnummer="008448" soort="verdrag">
  
  
  
  <intitule>Overeenkomst inzake gezamenlijke financiering van bepaalde diensten voor de luchtvaartnavigatie in IJsland</intitule>
  
  <verdrag status="goed" tekst="authentiek" xml:lang="en">
    <verdragtekst>
      <kop>
        <titel status="officieel">Agreement on the joint financing of certain Air Navigation Services in Iceland</titel>
      </kop>
      <aanhef>
        <preambule>
          <al>The Governments of Belgium, Canada, Denmark, France, The Federal Republic of Germany, Iceland, Israel, Italy, The Netherlands, Norway, Sweden, Switzerland, The United Kingdom of Great Britain, and Northern Ireland and The United States of America, being members of the International Civil Aviation Organization,</al>
          <al>DESIRING to conclude an agreement for the joint financing, in accordance with the terms and subject to the provisions of Chapter XV of the Convention on International Civil Aviation, of certain Air Navigation Services to be provided by the Government of Iceland,</al>
        </preambule>
        <afkondiging>
          <al>HAVE AGREED as follows:</al>
        </afkondiging>
      </aanhef>
      <wettekst>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">I</nr>
          </kop>
          <al>For the purposes of this Agreement:</al>
          <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
            <li>
              <li.nr>(a)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x201C;Organization&#x201D; means the International Civil Aviation Organization;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>(b)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x201C;Council&#x201D; means the Council of the Organization;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>(c)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x201C;Secretary General&#x201D; means the Secretary General of the Organization;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>(d)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x201C;Services&#x201D; means the services specified in Annex I to this Agreement and any additional services which may from time to time be provided pursuant to this Agreement.</al>
            </li>
          </lijst>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">II</nr>
          </kop>
          <al>The Government of Iceland shall provide, operate and maintain the Services and, in consideration of special benefits derived from the Services, shall bear five per cent of the approved actual costs thereof.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">III</nr>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>The Government of Iceland shall operate and maintain the Services without interruption, in an efficient manner and with the greatest degree of economy consistent therewith and, so far as practicable, in accordance with the applicable Standards, Recommended Practices, Procedures and Specifications of the Organization.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>Subject to the provisions of Annex I to this Agreement, the manner of taking meteorological observations and of making and disseminating meteorological reports shall be in accordance with the appropriate procedures and specifications promulgated by the World Meteorological Organization.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al>The Government of Iceland shall notify the Secretary General immediately of any emergency necessitating any temporary change or curtailment of the Services and that Government and the Secretary General shall thereupon consult on the measures to be taken to minimize any adverse effect of such change or curtailment.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">IV</nr>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>The Secretary General shall generally supervise the operation of the Services and may at any time arrange for the inspection of the Services, including any equipment used in connection therewith.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>The Government of Iceland shall, at the request of the Secretary General, and to the extent practicable, furnish such reports on the operation of the Services as the Secretary General considers desirable.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al>The Secretary General shall, at the request of the Government of Iceland, provide, to the extent practicable, such advice as that Government may reasonably require in regard to the discharge of its obligations under this Agreement.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr>
            <al>In the event of any failure by the Government of Iceland efficiently to operate and maintain any of the Services, there shall be consultation between that Government and the Secretary General for the purpose of agreeing upon remedial measures.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">V</nr>
          </kop>
          <al>The total costs of the Services computed in accordance with Annexes II and III to this Agreement shall not, for any one calendar year, exceed 4 321 166 United States dollars. This limit may be increased by the Council either with the consent of all the Contracting Governments or as a result of the application of the provisions of Article VI.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">VI</nr>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>For the purpose only of establishing, operating and maintaining services which have not otherwise been provided for pursuant to this Agreement, the limit determined pursuant to the provisions of Article V may be increased by a stated amount with the consent of Contracting Governments responsible in the aggregate for not less than ninety per cent of the total assessments made under the provisions of paragraphs 3, 4, 5 and 6 of Article VII in respect of the last calendar year for which assessments have been made.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>

            <al>Subject to the provisions of Article II, any expenditure attributable to the services referred to in paragraph 1 of this Article, or any expenditure made possible under the provisions of paragraph 2 (<nadruk type="cur">a</nadruk>) of Article XIII as a result of the inclusion of the said services within this Agreement, shall be borne solely by the Contracting Governments so consenting, in shares having the same relative proportion to each other as the shares of those Governments in the total assessments for the relevant year, and no part of the Reserve Fund referred to in Article X not attributable to those services shall be used for purposes to which those Governments alone have consented.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">VII</nr>
          </kop>
          <lid>
<lidnr>1</lidnr><al>Subject to the provisions of Article V and paragraph 2 of Article VI, the Contracting Governments agree to share ninety-five per cent of the approved actual costs of the Services, as determined pursuant to the provisions of Article VIII, in proportion to the aeronautical benefit derived therefrom by each Contracting Government. Such proportion shall be determined for each Contracting Government in respect of each calendar year by the number of crossings between Europe and North America any portion of which lies north of the 45th parallel North between the meridians of 15&#xB0; West and 50&#xB0; West performed in that year by its civil aircraft. In addition:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>a)</li.nr><al>a crossing between only Greenland and Canada, Greenland and the United States of America, Greenland and Iceland or Iceland and Europe shall be counted as one-third of a crossing;</al></li><li><li.nr>b)</li.nr><al>a crossing between only Greenland and Europe, Iceland and Canada or Iceland and the United States of America shall be counted as two-thirds of a crossing; and</al></li><li><li.nr>c)</li.nr><al>a crossing to or from Europe or Iceland which does not cross the coast of North America but crosses the meridian of 30&#xB0; West north of the 45th parallel North shall be counted as one-third of a crossing.</al></li></lijst></lid><lid><lidnr>2</lidnr><al>For the purposes of paragraph 1 of this Article:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>a)</li.nr><al>a crossing shall be counted even if the point of take-off or landing is not in the territories mentioned in that paragraph; and</al></li><li><li.nr>b)</li.nr><al>&#x201C;Europe&#x201D; does not include Iceland or the Azores.</al></li></lijst></lid><lid><lidnr>3</lidnr><al>On or before 20 November each year the Council shall assess the Contracting Governments for the purpose of providing advances for the following year. For the year 1983 the assessments shall be on the basis of the number of crossings in 1981 and ninety-five per cent of the estimated costs for 1983. The assessment of each Contracting Government shall be adjusted to take into account any difference between the amounts paid by it to the Organization as advances in respect of 1981 and its share, as determined by its crossings in 1981, of ninety-five per cent of the approved actual costs in 1981. The adjusted assessment of each Contracting Government shall be reduced by its share, as determined by its crossings in 1981, of the estimated revenues from user charges to be remitted under Article XIV to Iceland in 1983.</al></lid><lid><lidnr>4</lidnr><al>The procedure set forth in paragraph 3 of this Article shall apply to the assessments for the year 1984 with appropriate changes of year.</al></lid><lid><lidnr>5</lidnr><al>For 1985 the procedure in paragraph 3 of this Article shall apply, with appropriate changes of year, and, in addition, the assessment of each Contracting Government shall be further adjusted to take into account any difference between its share of the estimated revenues from user charges for 1983 and its share, as determined by its crossings in 1983, of the audited actual user charge revenues remitted to Iceland in 1983.</al></lid><lid><lidnr>6</lidnr><al>The procedure for 1985 shall apply in subsequent years with appropriate changes of year.</al></lid><lid><lidnr>7</lidnr><al>On 1 January and 1 July of each calendar year starting on 1 January 1983, each Contracting Government shall pay to the Organization, in half-yearly instalments, the amount assessed to it in respect of advances for the current calendar year, adjusted and reduced as provided in paragraphs 3, 4, 5 and 6 of this Article.</al></lid><lid><lidnr>8</lidnr><al>In the event of termination of this Agreement, the Council shall undertake adjustments so as to accomplish the objectives of this Article in respect of any period for which, at the date of termination of the Agreement, payments have not been adjusted pursuant to paragraphs 3, 4, 5 and 6 of this Article.</al></lid><lid><lidnr>9</lidnr><al>On or before 1 May of each year, each Contracting Government shall furnish to the Secretary General, in such form as the Secretary General may prescribe, full particulars of the crossings to which this Article applies performed during the preceding calendar year.</al></lid><lid><lidnr>10</lidnr><al>The Contracting Governments may agree that the particulars referred to in paragraph 9 on this Article will be furnished to the Secretary General on their behalf by another Government.</al></lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">VIII</nr>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>The Government of Iceland shall furnish to the Secretary General, on or before 15 September of each year, estimates, expressed in United States dollars, of the costs of the Services for the following calendar year. The estimates shall be drawn up in accordance with Article III and with Annexes II and III to this Agreement.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>The Government of Iceland shall furnish to the Secretary General, not later than six months after the end of each calendar year, a statement of the actual costs of the Services during that year. The Secretary General shall subject the statement to such audit and other examination as he deems appropriate and shall furnish to the Government of Iceland a report of the audit.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al>The Government of Iceland shall furnish to the Secretary General such additional information relating to any estimates of costs or statement of actual costs as the Secretary General may require, as well as any available information as to the extent to which the Services are being used by aircraft of any nationality.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr>
            <al>The statements of actual costs for each year shall be subject to approval by the Council.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">5</lidnr>
            <al>The statement of actual costs approved by the Council pursuant to the provisions of paragraph 4 of this Article shall be circulated to the Contracting Governments.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">IX</nr>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>The Government of Iceland shall be reimbursed for ninety-five per cent of the actual costs, as approved by the Council, of providing, operating and maintaining the Services.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>The Council shall, after having satisfied itself that the estimates submitted by the Government of Iceland in accordance with paragraph 1 of Article VIII have been drawn up in accordance with Article III and with Annexes II and III to this Agreement, authorize the Secretary General to make payments to that Government in respect of each quarter, not later than the first day of the second month of that quarter. The payments shall be based on the estimates referred to and shall constitute advances, subject to adjustment as provided under paragraph 3 of this Article. The total amount of such payments shall not exceed, in respect of any one year, the limit determined pursuant to the provisions of Article V. With effect from 1 January 1983, the Government of Iceland shall treat all net revenues from user charges, collected from all civil aircraft operators under a system operated pursuant to Article XIV, as part of the advances for the year in which those revenues are received.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al>After the approval by the Council of the statement of actual costs, the Secretary-General shall make adjustments in any subsequent quarterly payments to the Government of Iceland to take account of any differences between the payments made under paragraph 2 of this Article in respect of any year and the approved actual costs for that year.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr>
            <al>Contracting Governments not represented on the Council shall be invited to participate in the consideration by the Council or any of its bodies of the estimates furnished by the Government of Iceland pursuant to the provisions of paragraph 1 of Article VIII.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">5</lidnr>
            <al>The estimates of costs as approved by the Council, pursuant to the provisions of paragraph 2 of this Article, shall be circulated to the Contracting Governments.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">X</nr>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>The payments received by the Organization from the Contracting Governments pursuant to the provisions of Article VII shall, to the extent that they are not from time to time needed for making current payments to the Government of Iceland pursuant to this Agreement, constitute a Reserve Fund to be used by the Organization for the purposes of this Agreement.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>The Secretary General may arrange for short-term investment of the Reserve Fund. The Organization shall apply the interest derived therefrom to cover the extraordinary expenses of the Organization incidental to this Agreement. If such interest is insufficient to cover such expenses, the difference remaining shall be considered as an additional part of the actual costs of the Services and shall be reimbursed to the Organization from payments made by the Contracting Governments.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">XI</nr>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>The annual assessments of Contracting Governments shall be expressed in United States dollars.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>Each of the Contracting Governments shall make payments to the Organization pursuant to the provisions of Article VII in United States dollars or in sterling or, provided that the Government of Iceland consents thereto, in Icelandic kronur. The procedure for determining the rate of exchange applicable to a payment made in sterling or Icelandic kronur shall be determined by the Council in consultation with the Governments concerned.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al>The Secretary General shall, subject to the Organization being reimbursed in United States dollars for its extraordinary expenses, make payments to the Government of Iceland pursuant to the provisions of Articles IX and XII in the currencies in which Contracting Governments have made their payments to the Organization and which remain available.</al>
          </lid>
          
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">XII</nr>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>The obligation of the Secretary General to make payments to the Government of Iceland under this Agreement shall be limited to amounts actually received by the Organization and available in accordance with the terms of this Agreement.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>The Secretary General may, nevertheless, pending receipt of payments from Contracting Governments and in accordance with the Financial Regulations of the Organization, advance payments which are due to the Government of Iceland in cases where he considers such advances essential for the inauguration or uninterrupted continuance of the Services.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al>No Contracting Government shall have a claim against the Organization because of failure of any other Contracting Government to make any payment under this Agreement.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">XIII</nr>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>The Council may, subject to the provisions of Article V and paragraph 2 of Article VI and in agreement with the Government of Iceland, include under this Agreement new capital expenditure necessary for the proper operation of the Services.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>The Council may, subject to the provisions of Articles V and VI and in agreement with the Government of Iceland, include under this Agreement services in addition to those set out in Annex I hereto and new capital expenditure in respect of such services, provided that any one of the following conditions is fulfilled:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>a)</li.nr><al>the total amount of such expenditure in any one year does not exceed 3.5 per cent of the cost limit approved under Article V; or</al></li><li><li.nr>b)</li.nr><al>such services are those to which all Contracting Governments have consented; or</al></li><li><li.nr>c)</li.nr><al>such services are those to which Contracting Governments responsible in the aggregate for not less than ninety per cent of the total assessments made under the provisions of paragraphs 3, 4, 5 and 6 of Article VII have consented and in respect of which the provisions of Article VI have been applied.</al></li></lijst>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al>For the purposes of paragraphs 1 and 2 of this Article, renewal of buildings and equipment from payments received on account of depreciation shall not be regarded as new capital expenditure.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr>
            <al>If new capital expenditure or additional services are proposed by the Government of Iceland or by the Council, that Government shall furnish to the Secretary General an estimate of the costs thereof, together such specifications, plans and other information as may be required in regard thereto, and shall consult with the Secretary General concerning the methods of supply, design or construction to be adopted.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">5</lidnr>
            <al>The Council may, in agreement with the Government of Iceland, exclude from this Agreement any part of the Services.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">6</lidnr>
            <al>When action has been taken pursuant to paragraphs 1, 2 or 5 of this Article, the Council shall amend the Annexes to this Agreement accordingly.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">XIV</nr>
          </kop>
          <al>The Government of Iceland shall operate a system of user charges for the Services provided for all civil aircraft making crossings as defined in Article VII. These charges shall be calculated in accordance with Annex III to this Agreement. The net revenues from these charges shall be offset against payments due to the Government of Iceland pursuant to the provisions of this Agreement. Except with the consent of the Council, the Government of Iceland shall not impose any additional charges for the Services on other than its own nationals.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">XV</nr>
          </kop>
          <al>The Government of Iceland shall not make any international arrangement for the provision, operation, maintenance, development or financing of any or all of the Services without the approval of the Council.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">XVI</nr>
          </kop>
          <al>The Government of Iceland shall, to the fullest possible extent, cooperate with the representatives of the Organization in respect of the purposes of this Agreement and shall accord to such representatives the privileges and immunities to which they are entitled under the General Convention on the Privileges and Immunities of the Specialized Agencies, including Annex III (2) thereto.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">XVII</nr>
          </kop>
          <al>The Council shall convene a conference of all the Governments concerned:</al>
          <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
            <li>
              <li.nr>(a)</li.nr>
              <al>when requested by two or more of the Contracting Governments or by the Government of Iceland, or by any one of the Contracting Governments if such a conference has not been held during the previous five years;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>(b)</li.nr>
              <al>when failure of any Contracting Government to make payments under this Agreement necessitates a revision of the assessments which cannot otherwise be satisfactorily settled; or</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>(c)</li.nr>
              <al>when, for any other reason, the Council considers such a conference necessary.</al>
            </li>
          </lijst>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">XVIII</nr>
          </kop>
          <al>Any dispute relating to the interpretation or application of this Agreement or the Annexes thereto which is not settled by negotiation shall, upon the request of any Contracting Government party to the dispute, be referred to the Council for its recommendation.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">XIX</nr>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>This Agreement shall remain open until 1 December 1956 for signature by the Governments named in the Preamble.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>This Agreement shall be subject to acceptance by the signatory Governments. Instruments of acceptance shall be deposited as soon as possible with the Secretary General, who shall inform all signatory and acceding Governments of the date of deposit of each such instrument.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">XX</nr>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>This Agreement shall be open for accession by the Government of any State member of the United Nations or of a Specialized Agency in relationship therewith. Accessions shall be effected by the deposit of a formal instrument with the Secretary General.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>The Council may initiate consultations with any Government, not a party to this Agreement, whose civil aircraft benefit from the Services, for the purpose of obtaining its accession to the Agreement.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al>Notwithstanding the provisions of paragraph 2 of this Article, the Council may conclude arrangements for contributions from any Government which does not become a party to this Agreement. Any such contributions received shall be applied to the purposes of this Agreement as determined by the Council.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">XXI</nr>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>This Agreement shall come into force not earlier than 1 January 1957, when instruments of acceptance or of accession have been deposited by Governments responsible in the aggregate for initial assessments of not less than ninety per cent of the initial maximum cost figure laid down in Article V. As regards those Governments, deposit of an instrument of acceptance or of accession shall be deemed to constitute consent to the system of assessments, payments and adjustments under this Agreement for the period between 1 January 1957 and the entry into force of this Agreement.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>As regards any Government whose instrument of acceptance or of accession is deposited after the entry into force of this Agreement, the Agreement shall come into force on the date of such deposit. Each such Government shall consent to the system of assessments, payments and adjustments under this Agreement with effect at least from the beginning of the calendar year during which the instrument of acceptance or of accession is deposited. Each such Government may elect to be assessed for its appropriate share of the actual approved costs of any Services in respect of which the provisions of Article VI have been applied and as to which, at the date of accession of such Government, the consents of all Contracting Governments have not been given.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">XXII</nr>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
              <li>
                <li.nr>(a)</li.nr>
                <al>This Agreement may be terminated by the Government of Iceland on 31 December in any year by notice in writing given to the Secretary General not later than 1 January of that year.</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>(b)</li.nr>
                <al>If at any time it proves impossible for the Government of Iceland to perform the Services within the limit determined pursuant to the provisions of Article V, that Government shall immediately notify the Secretary General in writing of such fact and shall furnish to the Secretary General a detailed estimate of the additional amount required. The Secretary General shall promptly examine such estimate and, after any necessary consultation with that Government, determine the amount needed in excess of the aforesaid limit. The Secretary General shall then approach the Contracting Governments with a view to obtaining their consent as required pursuant to the provisions of Article V. Unless, within three months after the Secretary General has determined the additional amount required, he notifies the Government of Iceland that the Contracting Governments have given their consent, the Government of Iceland may thereafter terminate this Agreement on three months&#x2019; notice in writing given to the Secretary General.</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>(c)</li.nr>
                <al>This Agreement may be terminated on 31 December in any year by Contracting Governments other than the Government of Iceland responsible for current assessments in the aggregate of not less than ten per cent of the limit determined pursuant to the provisions of Article V by notice in writing given to the Secretary General not later than 1 January of that year.</al>
              </li>
            </lijst>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>Upon receipt of a notice of notices of desire to terminate this Agreement in accordance with paragraph 1 of this Article, the Secretary General shall notify the Contracting Governments.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">XXIII</nr>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>

            <al>Notwithstanding the provisions of Article XXII, any Contracting Government other than the Government of Iceland, whose current assessment is less than ten per cent of the limit determined pursuant to the provisions of. Article V, may withdraw from participation in this Agreement on 31 December in any year by notice in writing given to the Secretary General not later than 1 January of that year of its intention to terminate its participation. Any such notice shall, for the purpose of paragraph 1 (<nadruk type="cur">c</nadruk>) of Article XXII, be deemed also to constitute a notice of desire to terminate this Agreement.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>Following receipt of notice of withdrawal from any Contracting Government, the Secretary General shall notify the other Contracting Governments.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">XXIV</nr>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>In the event of termination of this Agreement by the Government of Iceland pursuant to the provisions of paragraph 1 of Article XXII, that Government shall pay to the Organization, or the Organization may offset against payments due to that Government hereunder, a sum representing equitable compensation for benefits to it from its acquisition, for its own purposes, of moveable or immoveable property, the cost of which has been partially or wholly reimbursed to that Government under the provisions of this Agreement.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>In the event of any termination of this Agreement by Contracting Governments other than the Government of Iceland, the Government of Iceland shall be paid out of the Reserve Fund or, if the Fund is insufficient, by all the Contracting Governments through the Organization, an equitable amount by way of compensation for capital expenditures undertaken by that Government and not wholly reimbursed pursuant to this Agreement. Any payments required from Contracting Governments for this purpose shall be computed on the basis of the most recent assessment figures and shall be due as of the time of termination. The Organization shall have the right to take over any moveable property for which compensation is paid pursuant to this paragraph. Any waiver of such right shall be taken into account in determining the compensation.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al>The provisions of paragraph 2 of this Article shall apply correspondingly in respect of any part of the Services which may be excluded from the Agreement pursuant to the provisions of paragraph 5 of Article XIII.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr>
            <al>The amount of any payments under this Article shall be determined by agreement between the Council and the Government of Iceland.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">XXV</nr>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>Subject to the provisions of paragraph 2 of Article X, any balance of the Reserve Fund and of interest thereon held by the Organization on the date when this Agreement ceases to be in force shall be apportioned among and refunded to those Governments which were still parties to this Agreement immediately before that date on the basis of their most recent annual assessments.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
              <li>
                <li.nr>(a)</li.nr>
                <al>Any Government which has withdrawn from participation in this Agreement in accordance with the provisions of Article XXIII shall pay to or receive from the Organization any difference between the amount it has paid to the Organization in accordance with Article VII and its appropriate share of the approved actual costs in respect of the period of its participation.</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>(b)</li.nr>
                <al>Any Government which has so withdrawn shall pay to the Organization its share of capital expenditures which have been undertaken by the Government of Iceland and which have not been wholly reimbursed pursuant to this Agreement. The amount payable shall be computed on the basis of the most recent assessment figure in respect of the Government which has withdrawn. Payment shall be due as of the time of withdrawal.</al>
              </li>
            </lijst>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">XXVI</nr>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>This Agreement may be amended by mutual agreement between the Contracting Governments.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>The Council shall, subject to the provisions of Article V and paragraph 2 of Article VI, revise the list of Contracting Governments and the amounts set opposite their names in paragraph 2 of Article VII to the extent necessary in order to:</al>
            <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
              <li>
                <li.nr>(a)</li.nr>
                <al>accommodate any non-signatory Government acceding to this Agreement in accordance with paragraph 1 of Article XX;</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>(b)</li.nr>
                <al>counterbalance any shortcomings in payments resulting from the failure of any Government named in the Preamble to become a party to this Agreement; or</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>(c)</li.nr>
                <al>take into account services brought within this Agreement pursuant to the provisions of Article XIII.</al>
              </li>
            </lijst>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al>The Council may, in cases additional to those specified in paragraph 6 of Article XIII, amend the Annexes to this Agreement, subject always to the terms and conditions of the Agreement and the consent of the Government of Iceland.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
      </wettekst>
      <wetsluiting status="goed">
        <slotformulering>
          <al>IN WITNESS WHEREOF, the undersigned, being duly authorized thereto, have, on behalf of their respective Governments, signed this Agreement on the dates appearing opposite their signatures.</al>
          <al>DONE in Geneva on the twenty-fifth day of September of the year nineteen hundred and fifty-six in the English, French and Spanish languages, all three texts being equally authoritative, in a single copy which shall be deposited with the International Civil Aviation Organization with which, in accordance with Article XIX hereof, it shall remain open for signature, and the Secretary General of the Organization shall send certified copies thereof to all signatory and acceding Governments.</al>
        </slotformulering>
      </wetsluiting>
    </verdragtekst>
    <verdragtekst>
      <kop>
        <label>ANNEX</label>
        <nr status="officieel">I</nr>
        <titel>&#x2013; THE SERVICES</titel>
      </kop>
      <wettekst>
        <deel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>PART </label>
            <nr status="officieel">I</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">&#x2013; AIR TRAFFIC SERVICES</titel>
          </kop>
          <structuurtekst status="goed">
            <al>An area control centre located at Reykjavik (6408N 2156W) to be in continuous operation to safeguard the North Atlantic international operations through the Reykjavik control area, including pilot/controller VHF communications through a station at Bl&#xE1;fjoell, and the extraction, transmission and display of information from secondary surveillance radar (SSR) stations at Keflavik and Stokksnes.</al>
          </structuurtekst>
        </deel>
        <deel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>PART</label>
            <nr status="officieel"> II</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">&#x2013; METEOROLOGICAL SERVICES</titel>
          </kop>
          <artikel status="goed">
<kop>
<nr>A</nr>
</kop>
<al>Surface and upper-air synoptic observations to be made at the following meteorological stations in accordance with the following table and the reports to be transmitted to Reykjavik as designated in Part III:</al><table frame="topbot">
						<tgroup cols="6" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
							<colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="1.92*"/><colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="1.00*"/><colspec colname="col3" colnum="3" colwidth="1.97*"/><colspec colname="col04" colnum="4" colwidth="1.95*"/><colspec colname="col4" colnum="5" colwidth="1.98*"/><tbody>
								<row>
									<entry colsep="0" morerows="1" rowsep="1">
										<al>
											<nadruk type="cur">Meteorological stations and their locations</nadruk><sup>1</sup>)   </al>
									</entry>
									<entry colsep="0" morerows="1" rowsep="1">
										<al>
											<nadruk type="cur">Surface synoptic observations 3-hourly (at 00, 03, 06, 09, 12, 15, 18 and 21 GMT)</nadruk>   
										</al>
									
										
										
										
										
									</entry>
									<entry colsep="0" morerows="1" rowsep="1">
										<al>
											<nadruk type="cur">Hourly observations</nadruk>   
										</al>
									</entry>
									<entry colsep="0" nameend="col4" namest="col04" rowsep="1">
										<al>
											<nadruk type="cur">Upper-air observations (at 00 and 12 GMT)</nadruk>   
										</al>
										
									</entry>
									
								</row>
								<row>
									
									
									
									<entry colname="col04" colsep="0" rowsep="1">
										<al>
											<nadruk type="cur">Radiosonde</nadruk>   
										</al>
									</entry>
									<entry colsep="0" rowsep="1">
										<al>
											<nadruk type="cur">Radiowind</nadruk>   
										</al>
									</entry>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">
										<al>1. Galtarviti </al><al>6610N2334W</al>
									</entry>
									<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">
										<al>8</al>
									</entry>
									<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
									<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
									<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">
										<al>2. Hjardarnes </al><al>6417N 1513W</al>
									</entry>
									<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0">
										<al>8</al>
									</entry>
									<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
									<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
									<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
								</row>
								<row>
									<entry colsep="0" rowsep="1">
										<al>3. Keflavik </al><al>6359N 2237W</al>
									</entry>
									<entry colsep="0" rowsep="1">
										<al>8</al>
									</entry>
									<entry colsep="0" rowsep="1">
										<al>24<sup>2</sup>)</al>
									</entry>
									<entry colsep="0" rowsep="1">
										<al>
											2</al>
									</entry>
									<entry colsep="0" rowsep="1">
										<al>2</al>
									</entry>
								</row>
							</tbody>
						</tgroup>
					</table><al><sup>1</sup>) The above stations may be moved by the Icelandic Authorities within
25 km from the specified positions as long as neither the capital nor the operating
costs with which this Agreement is concerned are thereby increased. Where
such costs whould be increased, the proposed relocation shall be submitted to
the Council for prior approval.</al><al><sup>2</sup>) Plus any necessary special observations.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed">
<kop>
<nr>B</nr>
</kop>
<al>The following services by the meteorological office located at Reykjavik (6408N 2154W):</al>
					<lijst><li><li.nr>1.</li.nr><al>provision of routine aerodrome forecasts and necessary amendments for Keflavik and Reykjavik;</al></li><li><li.nr>2.</li.nr><al>provision of area meteorological watch for the newly expanded Reykjavik FIR including the issue of SIGMET information.</al></li></lijst></artikel>
        </deel>
        <deel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>PART </label>
            <nr status="officieel">III</nr>
            <titel>&#x2013; AERONAUTICAL AND METEOROLOGICAL COMMUNICATIONS SERVICES</titel>
          </kop>
          <structuurtekst status="goed">
            <al>Telecommunication services to be provided as follows:</al><al><nadruk type="cur">A. Reykjavik</nadruk></al>
					<lijst><li><li.nr>1.</li.nr><al>Collection of meteorological reports from jointly financed synoptic stations in Iceland and their re-transmission to Regional Telecommunications Hub Bracknell.</al></li><li><li.nr>2.</li.nr><al>Reception of meteorological reports from jointly financed synoptic stations in Greenland and their re-transmission to Regional Telecommunications Hub Bracknell.<noot id="f1e4380524" type="voet">
							<noot.nr>1
													</noot.nr>
							<noot.al>Reception performed using the AFTN Retransmission to Regional Telecommunications Hub Bracknell using the circuit listed in A 7.</noot.al>
						</noot>
					</al></li><li><li.nr>3.</li.nr><al>Reception of meteorological messages originating in Europe and North America (except Greenland) from Regional Telecommunications Hub Bracknell.</al></li><li><li.nr>4.</li.nr><al>Aeronautical mobile service with aircraft on VHF.</al></li><li><li.nr>5.</li.nr><al>Landline teletypewriter services:</al><lijst><li><li.nr>a)</li.nr><al>MET Kaflavik - MET receiving unit Reykjavik.</al></li><li><li.nr>b)</li.nr><al>Reykjavik cable office - MET receiving unit Reykjavik.</al></li></lijst></li><li><li.nr>6.</li.nr><al> Telephone services:</al><lijst><li><li.nr>a)</li.nr><al>ATC Reykjavik - approach control/aerodrome control tower Keflavik.</al></li><li><li.nr>b)</li.nr><al>ATC Reykjavik - MET Reykjavik.</al></li><li><li.nr>c)</li.nr><al>MET Reykjavik - MET Keflavik.</al></li><li><li.nr>d)</li.nr><al>ATC Reykjavik - ATC Gander (S&#xF8;ndre Stremfj&#xF8;rd) - (omnibus).<noot><noot.nr>2
													</noot.nr>
<noot.al>The services listed under A 6 d), e), f) and g) and B 6 a), b) and c) are to be
provided by landlines from ATC Reykjavik and COM Gufunes to the Civil
Communications Centre of the PTT in Reykjavik, and from there by
microwave radio links to the Earth Station Skyggnir, where connexion is
made with the United Kingdom and Canada through the INTELSAT System.</noot.al></noot></al></li><li><li.nr>e)</li.nr><al> ATC Reykjavik - OAC Prestwick/Shanwick - (omnibus).<noot id="f2e4380524" type="voet">
<noot.nr>2</noot.nr>

<noot.al>The services listed under A 6 d), e), f) and g) and B 6 a), b) and c) are to be
provided by landlines from ATC Reykjavik and COM Gufunes to the Civil
Communications Centre of the PTT in Reykjavik, and from there by
microwave radio links to the Earth Station Skyggnir, where connexion is
made with the United Kingdom and Canada through the INTELSAT System.</noot.al></noot> </al></li><li><li.nr>f)</li.nr><al>ATC Reykjavik - ATC Gander (Edmonton).<noot id="f3e4380524" type="voet">
<noot.nr>2</noot.nr>

<noot.al>The services listed under A 6 d), e), f) and g) and B 6 a), b) and c) are to be
provided by landlines from ATC Reykjavik and COM Gufunes to the Civil
Communications Centre of the PTT in Reykjavik, and from there by
microwave radio links to the Earth Station Skyggnir, where connexion is
made with the United Kingdom and Canada through the INTELSAT System.</noot.al></noot></al></li><li><li.nr>g)</li.nr><al>ATC Reykjavik - ATC Prestwick/Scottish - (Stavanger) - (Bod&#xF8;).<noot id="f4e4380524" type="voet">
<noot.nr>2</noot.nr>

<noot.al>The services listed under A 6 d), e), f) and g) and B 6 a), b) and c) are to be
provided by landlines from ATC Reykjavik and COM Gufunes to the Civil
Communications Centre of the PTT in Reykjavik, and from there by
microwave radio links to the Earth Station Skyggnir, where connexion is
made with the United Kingdom and Canada through the INTELSAT System.</noot.al></noot></al></li></lijst></li><li><li.nr>7.</li.nr><al>Satellite, telegraph and data services:</al><lijst><li><li.nr>a)</li.nr><al>Regional Telecommunications Hub Bracknell - MET receiving unit Reykjavik.</al></li><li><li.nr>b)</li.nr><al>Reykjavik OACC - Prestwick/Shanwick OACC.<noot id="f5e4380524" type="voet">
<noot.nr>2</noot.nr>

<noot.al>The services listed under A 6 d), e), f) and g) and B 6 a), b) and c) are to be
provided by landlines from ATC Reykjavik and COM Gufunes to the Civil
Communications Centre of the PTT in Reykjavik, and from there by
microwave radio links to the Earth Station Skyggnir, where connexion is
made with the United Kingdom and Canada through the INTELSAT System.</noot.al></noot></al></li><li><li.nr>c)</li.nr><al>Reykjavik OACC - Gander OACC.<noot id="f6e4380524" type="voet">
<noot.nr>2</noot.nr>

<noot.al>The services listed under A 6 d), e), f) and g) and B 6 a), b) and c) are to be
provided by landlines from ATC Reykjavik and COM Gufunes to the Civil
Communications Centre of the PTT in Reykjavik, and from there by
microwave radio links to the Earth Station Skyggnir, where connexion is
made with the United Kingdom and Canada through the INTELSAT System.</noot.al></noot></al></li></lijst></li></lijst>
					
					
					
					
					
					
					
					
					
					
					
					
					
					
					<tussenkop>
						<nadruk type="cur">B. Gufunes</nadruk>
					</tussenkop>
					<lijst><li><li.nr>1.</li.nr><al>Aeronautical mobile service with aircraft on HF and VHF extended range. The VHF extended range system comprises stations at Hafell, Thorbjorn, Gagnheidi and Thverfjall as well as the lines necessary for their remote control from Gufunes.</al></li><li><li.nr>2.</li.nr><al>Landline teletypewriter services:<noot id="f50e4380524" type="voet">
							<noot.nr>4
													</noot.nr>
							<noot.al>The Gufunes (Reykjavik) AFTN station is to provide automatic relaying
of message traffic.</noot.al>
						</noot>
					</al><lijst><li><li.nr>a)</li.nr><al>Gufunes - ATC Reykjavik.</al></li><li><li.nr>b)</li.nr><al>Gufunes - flight operations Keflavik.</al></li><li><li.nr>c)</li.nr><al>Gufunes - MET Reykjavik.</al></li><li><li.nr>d)</li.nr><al>Gufunes - MET Keflavik.</al></li><li><li.nr>e)</li.nr><al>Gufunes - COM Keflavik.</al></li></lijst></li><li><li.nr>3.</li.nr><al> Telephone services:</al><lijst><li><li.nr>a)</li.nr><al>Gufunes - ATC Reykjavik.</al></li><li><li.nr>b)</li.nr><al>Gufunes - Rjupnahaed.</al></li><li><li.nr>c)</li.nr><al>Gufunes - MET Reykjavik.</al></li></lijst></li><li><li.nr>4.</li.nr><al>Remote keying services:</al><lijst><li><li.nr>a)</li.nr><al> Gufunes - Rjupnahaed: 15 lines.</al></li></lijst></li><li><li.nr>5.</li.nr><al>VHF communications between Gufunes, ATC Reykjavik and Keflavik aerodrome to supplement the above inter-communication services in the event of landline failure.</al></li><li><li.nr>6.</li.nr><al> Satellite telegraph services:<noot id="f9e4380524" type="voet">
<noot.nr>4</noot.nr>
<noot.al>The Gufunes (Reykjavik) AFTN station is to provide automatic relaying of message traffic.</noot.al>
</noot></al><lijst><li><li.nr>a)</li.nr><al>Duplex teletypewriter service between the Gufunes (Reykjavik) AFTN station and the AFTN station at S&#xF8;ndre Str&#xF8;mfjord.<noot id="f10e4380524" type="voet">
<noot.nr>3</noot.nr>
<noot.al>Service performed using landlines from Gufunes to Keflavik and tropo scatter from there to S&#xF8;ndre Str&#xF8;mfjord.</noot.al>
</noot></al></li><li><li.nr>b)</li.nr><al>Duplex teletypewriter service between the Gufunes (Reykjavik) AFTN station and the AFTN station at Montreal.<noot id="f11e4380524" type="voet">
<noot.nr>2</noot.nr>
<noot.al>The services listed under A 6 d), e), f) and g) and B 6 a), b) and c) are to be
provided by landlines from ATC Reykjavik and COM Gufunes to the Civil
Communications Centre of the PTT in Reykjavik, and from there by
microwave radio links to the Earth Station Skyggnir, where connexion is
made with the United Kingdom and Canada through the INTELSAT System.</noot.al>
</noot></al></li><li><li.nr>c)</li.nr><al>Duplex teletypewriter service between the Gufunes (Reykjavik) AFTN station and the AFTN station at London.<noot id="f12e4380524" type="voet">
<noot.nr>2</noot.nr>
<noot.al>The services listed under A 6 d), e), f) and g) and B 6 a), b) and c) are to be provided by landlines from ATC Reykjavik and COM Gufunes to the Civil Communications Centre of the PTT in Reykjavik, and from there by microwave radio links to the Earth Station Skyggnir, where connexion is made with the United Kingdom and Canada through the INTELSAT System.</noot.al>
</noot></al></li></lijst></li></lijst>
					
					
					
					
					
					
					
					
					
					
					
					
					
					
					
					
					

					<tussenkop>
						<nadruk type="cur">C. Rjupnahead</nadruk>
					</tussenkop>
					<al>HF transmitting station.</al>
          </structuurtekst>
        </deel>
        <deel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>PART</label>
            <nr status="officieel"> IV</nr>
            <titel status="officieel"> &#x2014; RADIO NAVIGATION AIDS</titel>
          </kop>
          <structuurtekst status="goed">
            <al>Radio navigation aids to be provided as follows:</al>
            <al>
              <nadruk type="cur">Loran</nadruk>  at Vik with the following specification:</al>
            <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
              <li>
                <li.nr>i)</li.nr>
                <al>A standard Loran Slave Station complete with monitoring facilities at Vik providing in association with a Double Master Station at Skuvanes (Faroe Islands) and a Slave Station at Mangerstar (Hebrides) a continuous radio navigation service using Loran rate 1L5 in the North Eastern Atlantic Area, the station to be equipped and maintained for the provision of this service with a minimum of interruption due to failure of its component parts.</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>ii)</li.nr>
                <al>All communication facilities necessary to the operation of the station, including fixed service radio communication with the Master Station at Skuvanes.</al>
              </li>
            </lijst>
          </structuurtekst>
        </deel>
      </wettekst>
    </verdragtekst>
    <verdragtekst>
      <kop><label>ANNEX</label><nr>II</nr><titel>&#x2013; INVENTORY</titel></kop>
      <vrije-tekst>
        <tekst status="goed">
							
						<al>Station: ATC Reykjavik</al><tussenkop><nadruk type="cur">(Calculated in U.S. Dollars)</nadruk></tussenkop>
<table frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="8" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="1.10*"/><colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="2.19*"/><colspec colname="col3" colnum="3" colwidth="2.21*"/><colspec colname="col4" colnum="4" colwidth="2.21*"/><colspec colname="col5" colnum="5" colwidth="2.21*"/><colspec colname="col06" colnum="6" colwidth="3.44*"/><colspec colname="col6" colnum="7" colwidth="1.00*"/><tbody>
<row>
<entry><al><nadruk type="cur">Items</nadruk></al></entry>
<entry nameend="col5" namest="col2" rowsep="1"><al><nadruk type="cur">From JS-WP/1429 - Audited actual costs for 1986</nadruk></al></entry>

<entry nameend="col6" namest="col06" rowsep="1"><al><nadruk type="cur">Subject to audit</nadruk></al></entry>

</row>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry/>
<entry><al><nadruk type="cur">Initial value for purposes of annual depreciation 31/12/86</nadruk></al></entry>
<entry><al><nadruk type="cur">Depreciation received to 31/12/86</nadruk> </al></entry>
<entry><al><nadruk type="cur">Renewals from depreciation to 31/12/86</nadruk></al></entry>
<entry><al><nadruk type="cur">Residual value as of 31/12/86</nadruk></al></entry>
<entry><al><nadruk type="cur">Approved new capital for implementation 31/12/86</nadruk></al></entry>
<entry><al><nadruk type="cur">Renewals from depreciation after 31/12/86</nadruk></al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>1. Buildings and appurtenances thereto</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>2. Antenna towers and counterpoises</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>3. Machinery and tools</al></entry>
<entry><al>14 443</al></entry>
<entry><al>3 065</al></entry>
<entry><al>177</al></entry>
<entry><al>11 555</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>4. Communications equipment</al></entry>
<entry><al>330 234</al></entry>
<entry><al>151 180</al></entry>
<entry><al>257</al></entry>
<entry><al>179 311</al></entry>
<entry><al>33 000<sup>1</sup></al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>5. SSR</al></entry>
<entry><al>624 009</al></entry>
<entry><al>20 571</al></entry>
<entry><al>20 571</al></entry>
<entry><al>624 009</al></entry>
<entry><al>714 000<sup>2, 3</sup></al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>6. Meteorological equipment</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>7. Vehicles</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>8. Office and housing equipment</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
</row>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry><al>9. Cables</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>TOTAL</al></entry>
<entry><al>968 686</al></entry>
<entry><al>174 816</al></entry>
<entry><al>21 005</al></entry>
<entry><al>814 875</al></entry>
<entry><al>747 000</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table><al><sup>1</sup> Tape recorder (C-WP/7720).</al><al><sup>2</sup>  Extension of SSR radar coverage South-east of Iceland (C-WP/7957).</al><al><sup>3</sup> Speech circuit switch (C-WP/8495).</al><al>Station: MET Reykjavik</al><tussenkop><nadruk type="cur">(Calculated in U.S. Dollars)</nadruk></tussenkop>
<table frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="8" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/><colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="2.00*"/><colspec colname="col3" colnum="3" colwidth="2.00*"/><colspec colname="col4" colnum="4" colwidth="2.00*"/><colspec colname="col5" colnum="5" colwidth="2.00*"/><colspec colname="col06" colnum="6" colwidth="2.00*"/><colspec colname="col6" colnum="7" colwidth="2.00*"/><tbody>
<row>
<entry><al><nadruk type="cur">Items</nadruk></al></entry>
<entry nameend="col5" namest="col2" rowsep="1"><al><nadruk type="cur">From JW-WP/1429 - Audited actual costs for 1986</nadruk></al></entry>

<entry nameend="col6" namest="col06" rowsep="1"><al><nadruk type="cur">Subject to audit</nadruk></al></entry>

</row>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry/>
<entry><al><nadruk type="cur">Initial value for purposes of annual depreciation 31/12/86</nadruk></al></entry>
<entry><al><nadruk type="cur">Depreciation received to 31/12/86</nadruk></al></entry>
<entry><al><nadruk type="cur">Renewals from depreciation to 31/12/86</nadruk></al></entry>
<entry><al><nadruk type="cur">Residual value as of 31/12/86</nadruk></al></entry>
<entry><al><nadruk type="cur">Approved new capital for implementation 31/12/86</nadruk></al></entry>
<entry><al><nadruk type="cur">Renewals from depreciation after 31/12/86</nadruk></al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>1. Buildings and appurtenances thereto</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>2. Antenna towers and counterpoises</al></entry>
<entry><al>16</al></entry>
<entry><al>16</al></entry>
<entry><al>0</al></entry>
<entry><al>0</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>3. Machinery and tools</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>4. Communications equipment</al></entry>
<entry><al>87</al></entry>
<entry><al>87</al></entry>
<entry><al>0</al></entry>
<entry><al>0</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>5. Cables</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>6. Meteorological equipment</al></entry>
<entry><al>1 372</al></entry>
<entry><al>411</al></entry>
<entry><al>0</al></entry>
<entry><al>961</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>7. Vehicles</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
</row>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry><al>8. Office and housing equipment</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>TOTAL</al></entry>
<entry><al>1 475</al></entry>
<entry><al>514</al></entry>
<entry><al>0</al></entry>
<entry><al>961</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table><al>Station: MET Keflavik</al><tussenkop><nadruk type="cur">(Calculated in U.S. Dollars)</nadruk></tussenkop>
<table frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="8" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/><colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="2.00*"/><colspec colname="col3" colnum="3" colwidth="2.00*"/><colspec colname="col4" colnum="4" colwidth="2.00*"/><colspec colname="col5" colnum="5" colwidth="2.00*"/><colspec colname="col06" colnum="6" colwidth="2.00*"/><colspec colname="col6" colnum="7" colwidth="2.00*"/><tbody>
<row>
<entry><al><nadruk type="cur">Items</nadruk></al></entry>
<entry colsep="1" nameend="col5" namest="col2"><al><nadruk type="cur">From JS-WP/1429 - Audited actual costs for 1986</nadruk></al></entry>

<entry colsep="1" nameend="col6" namest="col06"><al><nadruk type="cur">Subject to audit</nadruk></al></entry>

</row>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry/>
<entry><al><nadruk type="cur">Initial value for purposes of annual depreciation 31/12/86</nadruk></al></entry>
<entry><al><nadruk type="cur">Depreciation received to 31/12/86</nadruk></al></entry>
<entry><al><nadruk type="cur">Renewals front depreciation to 31/12/86</nadruk></al></entry>
<entry><al><nadruk type="cur">Residual value as of 31/12/86 </nadruk></al></entry>
<entry><al><nadruk type="cur">Approved new capital for implementation 31/12/86</nadruk></al></entry>
<entry><al><nadruk type="cur">Renewals from depreciation after 31/12/86</nadruk></al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>l. Buildings and appurtenances thereto</al></entry>
<entry><al>667</al></entry>
<entry><al>667</al></entry>
<entry><al>0</al></entry>
<entry><al>0</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>2. Antenna towers and counterpoises</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>3. Machinery and tools</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>4. Communications equipment</al></entry>
<entry><al>15</al></entry>
<entry><al>15</al></entry>
<entry><al>0</al></entry>
<entry><al>0</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>5. Cables</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>6. Meteorological equipment</al></entry>
<entry><al>9 347</al></entry>
<entry><al>1 047</al></entry>
<entry><al>0</al></entry>
<entry><al>8 300</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>7. Vehicles</al></entry>
<entry><al>4 983</al></entry>
<entry><al>2 991</al></entry>
<entry><al>0</al></entry>
<entry><al>1 992</al></entry>
<entry><al>7 217<sup>1</sup></al></entry>
<entry><al>4 983<sup>1</sup></al></entry>
</row>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry><al>8. Office and housing equipment</al></entry>
<entry><al>938</al></entry>
<entry><al>285</al></entry>
<entry><al>172</al></entry>
<entry><al>825</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>TOTAL</al></entry>
<entry><al>15 950</al></entry>
<entry><al>5 005</al></entry>
<entry><al>172</al></entry>
<entry><al>11 117</al></entry>
<entry><al>7 217</al></entry>
<entry><al>4 983</al></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table><al><sup>1</sup> One vehicle to renew 1982 LADA (C-WP/8309).</al><al>Station: COM Rjupnahaed</al><tussenkop><nadruk type="cur">(Calculated in U.S. Dollars)</nadruk></tussenkop>
<table frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="8" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/><colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="2.00*"/><colspec colname="col3" colnum="3" colwidth="2.00*"/><colspec colname="col4" colnum="4" colwidth="2.00*"/><colspec colname="col5" colnum="5" colwidth="2.00*"/><colspec colname="col06" colnum="6" colwidth="2.00*"/><colspec colname="col6" colnum="7" colwidth="2.00*"/><tbody>
<row>
<entry><al><nadruk type="cur">Items</nadruk></al></entry>
<entry nameend="col5" namest="col2" rowsep="1"><al><nadruk type="cur">From JS-WP/1429 - Audited actual costs for 1986</nadruk></al></entry>

<entry nameend="col6" namest="col06" rowsep="1"><al><nadruk type="cur">Subject to audit</nadruk></al></entry>

</row>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry/>
<entry><al><nadruk type="cur">Initial value for purposes of annual depreciation 31/12/86</nadruk></al></entry>
<entry><al><nadruk type="cur">Depreciation received to 31/12/86</nadruk></al></entry>
<entry><al><nadruk type="cur">Renewals from depreciation to 31/12/86</nadruk></al></entry>
<entry><al><nadruk type="cur">Residual value as of 31/12/86</nadruk></al></entry>
<entry><al><nadruk type="cur">Approved new capital for implementation 31/12/86</nadruk>   </al></entry>
<entry><al><nadruk type="cur">Renewals from depreciation after 31/12/86</nadruk></al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>1. Buildings and appurtenances thereto</al></entry>
<entry><al>270 000</al></entry>
<entry><al>270 000</al></entry>
<entry><al>0</al></entry>
<entry><al>0</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>2. Antenna towers and counterpoises</al></entry>
<entry><al>19 305</al></entry>
<entry><al>14 486</al></entry>
<entry><al>891</al></entry>
<entry><al>5 710</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>104 000<sup>1</sup></al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>3. Machinery and tools</al></entry>
<entry><al>1 028</al></entry>
<entry><al>5 741</al></entry>
<entry><al>15 714</al></entry>
<entry><al>11 001</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>4. Communications equipment</al></entry>
<entry><al>328 214</al></entry>
<entry><al>32 388</al></entry>
<entry><al>32 032</al></entry>
<entry><al>327 858</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>111 500<sup>2, 3, 4</sup></al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>5. Cables</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>6. Meteorological equipment</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>7. Vehicles</al></entry>
<entry><al>9 619</al></entry>
<entry><al>2 105</al></entry>
<entry><al>905</al></entry>
<entry><al>8 419</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
</row>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry><al>8. Office and housing equipment</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>TOTAL</al></entry>
<entry><al>628 166</al></entry>
<entry><al>324 720</al></entry>
<entry><al>49 542</al></entry>
<entry><al>352 988</al></entry>
<entry/>
<entry><al>215 500</al></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table><al><sup>1</sup> Two HF antennas (C-WP/7905), one HF antenna (C-WP/8110).</al><al><sup>2</sup> HF receiver (transmission monitoring equipment (C-WP/8309).</al><al><sup>3</sup> Oscilloscope (C-WP/8309).</al><al><sup>4</sup> One HF SSB transmitter (replacing two old HF SSB transmitters) (C-WP/8495).</al><al>Station: COM Gufunes</al><tussenkop><nadruk type="cur">(Calculated in U.S. Dollars)</nadruk></tussenkop>
<table frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="8" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/><colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="2.00*"/><colspec colname="col3" colnum="3" colwidth="2.00*"/><colspec colname="col4" colnum="4" colwidth="2.00*"/><colspec colname="col5" colnum="5" colwidth="2.00*"/><colspec colname="col06" colnum="6" colwidth="2.00*"/><colspec colname="col6" colnum="7" colwidth="2.00*"/><tbody>
<row>
<entry><al><nadruk type="cur">Items</nadruk></al></entry>
<entry nameend="col5" namest="col2" rowsep="1"><al><nadruk type="cur">From JS-WP/1429 - Audited actual costs for 1986</nadruk></al></entry>

<entry nameend="col6" namest="col06" rowsep="1"><al><nadruk type="cur">Subject to audit</nadruk></al></entry>

</row>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry/>
<entry><al><nadruk type="cur">Initial value for purposes of annual depreciation 31/12/86</nadruk></al></entry>
<entry><al><nadruk type="cur">Depreciation received to 31/12/86</nadruk></al></entry>
<entry><al><nadruk type="cur">Renewals from depreciation to 31/12/86</nadruk></al></entry>
<entry><al><nadruk type="cur">Residual valueas of 31/12/86</nadruk></al></entry>
<entry><al><nadruk type="cur">Approved new capital for implementation 31/12/86</nadruk></al></entry>
<entry><al><nadruk type="cur">Renewals from depreciation after 31/12/86</nadruk></al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>1. Buildings and appurtenances thereto</al></entry>
<entry><al>6 390</al></entry>
<entry><al>6 331</al></entry>
<entry><al>82</al></entry>
<entry><al>141</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>2. Antenna towers and counterpoises</al></entry>
<entry><al>27 977</al></entry>
<entry><al>31 159</al></entry>
<entry><al>12 439</al></entry>
<entry><al>9 257</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>18 000<sup>1</sup></al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>3. Machinery and tools</al></entry>
<entry><al>710</al></entry>
<entry><al>753</al></entry>
<entry><al>43</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>4. Communications equipment</al></entry>
<entry><al>437 860</al></entry>
<entry><al>378 736</al></entry>
<entry><al>125 096</al></entry>
<entry><al>184 220</al></entry>
<entry><al>352 871<sup>2, 5, 6, 7</sup> </al></entry>
<entry><al>212 129<sup>2, 3, 4</sup>
</al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>5. Cables</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>6. Meteorological equipment</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>7. Vehicles</al></entry>
<entry><al>5 986</al></entry>
<entry><al>10 498</al></entry>
<entry><al>6 767</al></entry>
<entry><al>2 255</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>32 000<sup>8</sup></al></entry>
</row>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry><al>8. Office and housing equipment</al></entry>
<entry><al>2 182</al></entry>
<entry><al>109</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>2 073</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
<entry><al>-</al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry><al>TOTAL</al></entry>
<entry><al>481 105</al></entry>
<entry><al>427 586</al></entry>
<entry><al>144 427</al></entry>
<entry><al>197 946</al></entry>
<entry><al>352 871</al></entry>
<entry><al>262 129</al></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table><al><sup>1</sup> Four antennae multicouplers (C-WP/8110). Three antennae multicouplers (C-WP/8309).</al><al><sup>2</sup> Software for air/ground computer - CIDIN interfacing (C-WP/8309).</al><al><sup>3</sup> Two GP ER VHF transmitters/receivers (C-WP/8309).</al><al><sup>4</sup> Three radio receivers (C-WP/8309).</al><al><sup>5</sup> Renewal of a bus, 80% of costs (C-WP/8309).</al><al><sup>6</sup> Field strength meter (C-WP/8309).</al><al><sup>7</sup> Signature multimeter/analyser.</al><al><sup>8</sup> Enrom programming equipment (C-WP/8309).</al></tekst>
      </vrije-tekst>
    </verdragtekst>
    <verdragtekst>
      <kop>
        <label>Annex</label>
        <nr status="officieel">III</nr>
        <titel status="officieel">Financial</titel>
      </kop>
      <wettekst>
        <titeldeel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>SECTION</label>
            <nr status="officieel">I</nr>
          </kop>
          <artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<nr>1</nr>
								</kop>
								
								<al>Statements rendered by the Government of Iceland on the cost of operating and maintaining the Services set forth in Annex I shall be based on the elements enumerated in Parts A, B and C of Section II of this Annex. These estimates and accounts shall be rendered in accordance with a format and breakdown to be agreed upon between the Secretary General and the Government of Iceland. The Government of Iceland shall also provide, in a form agreed upon with the Secretary General, an annual statement showing any capital investment undertaken by Iceland in respect of the Services, including renewal of buildings or equipment met from provision for depreciation.</al>
							</artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<nr>2</nr>
								</kop>
								
								<al>The Government of Iceland shall not include, in the costs of the Services, customs or other duties on equipment or other materials imported for direct and exclusive application to the purposes of the Agreement.</al>
							</artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<nr>3</nr>
								</kop>
								
								<al>If in the year 1957 or any later year the use by the Government of Iceland of the Services for commercial purposes changes, that change shall be reflected by an appropriate change in the accounts.</al>
							</artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<nr>4</nr>
								</kop>
								
								<al>The number of regular personnel charged to the Services shall not exceed the following:</al>
								
							<table frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="5" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="col01" colnum="1" colwidth="1.00*"/><colspec colname="col1" colnum="2" colwidth="1.34*"/><colspec colname="col02" colnum="3" colwidth="1.55*"/><colspec colname="col2" colnum="4" colwidth="1.56*"/><colspec colname="col04" colnum="5" colwidth="1.57*"/><colspec colname="col4" colnum="6" colwidth="2.00*"/><tbody>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry colname="col01"/><entry colname="col1"/>
<entry colname="col02"><al><nadruk type="cur">Technical</nadruk></al></entry>
<entry colname="col2"><al><nadruk type="cur">Other</nadruk></al></entry>
<entry colname="col04"><al><nadruk type="cur">Total</nadruk></al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col01"><al>I. </al></entry><entry colname="col1"><al><nadruk type="cur">- Air traffic services:</nadruk></al></entry>
<entry colname="col02"/>
<entry colname="col2"/>
<entry colname="col04"/>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col01"/><entry colname="col1"><al>1) Reykjavik. . . . . . . . </al></entry>
<entry colname="col02"><al>38*</al></entry>
<entry colname="col2"><al>0</al></entry>
<entry colname="col04"><al>38</al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col01"><al>II. </al></entry><entry colname="col1"><al>II.  <nadruk type="cur">- Meteorological services:</nadruk></al></entry>
<entry colname="col02"/>
<entry colname="col2"/>
<entry colname="col04"/>
</row>

<row>
<entry colname="col01"/><entry colname="col1"><al>1) Keflavik. . . . . . . . </al></entry>
<entry colname="col02"><al>12</al></entry>
<entry colname="col2"><al>0</al></entry>
<entry colname="col04"><al>12</al></entry>
</row><row><entry colname="col01"/><entry colname="col1"><al>2) Reykjavik. . . . . . . . </al></entry><entry colname="col02"><al>8.5</al></entry><entry colname="col2"><al>0</al></entry><entry colname="col04"><al>8.5</al></entry></row><row><entry colname="col01"/><entry colname="col1"><al>3) Galtarviti. . . . . . . . </al></entry><entry colname="col02"><al>1**</al></entry><entry colname="col2"><al>0</al></entry><entry colname="col04"><al>1</al></entry></row><row><entry colname="col01"/><entry colname="col1"><al>4) Hjardarnes. . . . . . . . </al></entry><entry colname="col02"><al>1**</al></entry><entry colname="col2"><al>0</al></entry><entry colname="col04"><al>1</al></entry></row>


<row>
<entry colname="col01"><al>III. </al></entry><entry colname="col1"><al><nadruk type="cur">- Aeronautical and meteorological communication services:</nadruk></al></entry>
<entry colname="col02"/>
<entry colname="col2"/>
<entry colname="col04"/>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col01"/><entry colname="col1"><al>1) Reykjavik. . . . . . . . </al></entry>
<entry nameend="col04" namest="col02"><al>Staff included under I-1) and II-2) above</al></entry>


</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col01"/><entry colname="col1"><al>2) Gufunes. . . . . . . . </al></entry>
<entry colname="col02"><al>36</al></entry>
<entry colname="col2"><al>0</al></entry>
<entry colname="col04"><al>36</al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col01"/><entry colname="col1"><al>3) Rjupnahaed. . . . . . . . </al></entry>
<entry colname="col02"><al>6</al></entry>
<entry colname="col2"><al>0</al></entry>
<entry colname="col04"><al>6</al></entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="col01"><al>IV.</al></entry><entry colname="col1"><al>  <nadruk type="cur">- Radio navigation aids:</nadruk></al></entry>
<entry colname="col02"><al>0</al></entry>
<entry colname="col2"><al>0</al></entry>
<entry colname="col04"><al>0</al></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table><lijst><li><al>* The Government of Iceland may employ up to 3 additional persons on a
part-time basis to cope with peak period traffic in the ATC services from May
to September or when the regular air traffic controllers are on vacation, provided
that this is less expensive than the overtime rates in effect for the regular
air traffic controllers.</al></li><li><al>** Part-time including substitutes.</al></li></lijst></artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<nr>5</nr>
								</kop>
								
								<al>The Government of Iceland may only charge, in respect of certain costs listed below which are not directly separable from the cost of that Government's own services, the following percentages of the total cost:</al>
							<lijst><li><li.nr>5.1</li.nr><al>Air traffic services at Reykjavik: 100% of ATC salaries, 100% of the cost of the pilot/controller VHF service through Bl&#xE1;fjoell, 50% of the cost of extracting, remoting and displaying information derived from an SSR at Keflavik, 70% of all other direct costs, and depreciation on the above-stated percentages of capital improvements of these items.</al></li><li><li.nr>5.2</li.nr><al>Meteorological services at Reykjavik: 100% of 8V2 MET salaries, 88% of the direct costs as regards Icelandic synoptic messages, 50% of the direct costs as regards MET communications, except for salaries.</al></li><li><li.nr>5.3</li.nr><al>Communications services at Gufunes: 60% of the direct cost as regards basic MET messages, and 80% of the expenses incurred for fuel, heating, lighting, cleaning, stationery and miscellaneous supplies, land rent, snow removal, transportation and material used for maintenance of buildings, of machinery and tools, of storage tanks, of vehicles and of office and housing equipment, including special labour and capital expenditures related thereto.</al></li><li><li.nr>5.4</li.nr><al>Communications services at Rjupnahaed: 75% of the salaries of regular operating personnel and of the expenses incurred for fuel, heating, lighting, cleaning, stationery and miscellaneous supplies, land rent, snow removal, transportation and material used for maintenance of buildings, of machinery and tools, of storage tanks, of vehicles and of office and housing equipment, including special labour and capital expenditures related thereto.</al></li></lijst></artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<nr>6</nr>
								</kop>
								
								<al>Rental for the Iceland portion of the United Kingdom/Iceland satellite facilities may be charged at not more than prevailing commercial rates from 1 January 1988 onwards.</al>
							</artikel><artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<nr>7</nr>
								</kop>
								
								<al>Rental for the Iceland portion of the Canada/Iceland satellite facilities may be charged at not more than prevailing commercial rates from 1 January 1988 onwards.</al>
							</artikel><artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<nr>8</nr>
								</kop>
								
								<al>Only a portion of the Reykjavik-Sondrestrom AFTN circuit (i.e. line between Gufunes and Keflavik) may be charged from 1 January 1988 onwards.</al>
							</artikel><artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<nr>9</nr>
								</kop>
								
								<al>Rental for part of the Bracknell/Reykjavik data facsimile circuit - 15% chargeable to Joint Financing.</al>
							</artikel></titeldeel>
        <titeldeel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>SECTION</label>
            <nr status="officieel">II</nr>
          </kop>
          <structuurtekst status="goed">
            <al>The direct costs of operating and maintaining the Services which the
Government of Iceland may charge are categorized in Parts A and B
hereunder. The indirect costs which the Government of Iceland may
charge are set out in Part C hereunder.</al>
          </structuurtekst>
          <afdeling status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>PART </label>
              <nr status="officieel">A</nr>
              <titel status="officieel">&#x2014; OPERATIONAL EXPENSES</titel>
            </kop>
            <artikel status="goed">
              <kop>
                <nr status="officieel">1</nr>
              </kop>
              <al>Salaries of regular operating personnel.</al><al>(Basic salaries established by the Government of Iceland from time to time, plus any applicable allowances or other payments such as for cost of living, subsistence, night shift, overtime, personnel insurance, sickness, leave, etc.)</al></artikel>
            <artikel status="goed">
              <kop>
                <nr status="officieel">1a)</nr>
              </kop>
              <al>Payment to part-time observers on synoptic observation stations.</al>
            </artikel>
            <artikel status="goed">
              <kop>
                <nr status="officieel">2</nr>
              </kop>
              <al>Working expendables.</al><al>(Including, where applicable, fuel, provisions, radiosondes, balloons, hydrogen, etc.)</al></artikel>
            <artikel status="goed">
              <kop>
                <nr status="officieel">3</nr>
              </kop>
              <al> General operating expenses.</al><al>(Including, where applicable, charges for electric power, commercial communications charges, heating, lighting, cleaning, stationery and miscellaneous supplies, rents, etc.)</al></artikel>
            <artikel status="goed">
              <kop>
                <nr status="officieel">4</nr>
              </kop>
              <al>Transportation.</al><al>(Including, where applicable, transportation of personnel and goods, operational expenses of vehicles used in connexion therewith, etc.)</al></artikel>
            <artikel status="goed">
              <kop>
                <nr status="officieel">5</nr>
              </kop>
              <al> Miscellaneous additional necessary operating expenses.</al>
            </artikel>
          </afdeling>
          <afdeling status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>PART </label>
              <nr status="officieel">B</nr>
              <titel status="officieel">&#x2014; MAINTENANCE EXPENSES</titel>
            </kop>
            <artikel status="goed">
              <kop>
                <nr status="officieel">1</nr>
              </kop>
              <al>Salaries of regular maintenance personnel.</al><al>(Salaries to be included under Part A-1.)</al></artikel>
            <artikel status="goed">
              <kop>
                <nr status="officieel">2</nr>
              </kop>
              <al>Special experts employed in maintenance.</al><al>(Including, where applicable, experts employed on a temporary basis for special maintenance purposes.)</al></artikel>
            <artikel status="goed">
              <kop>
                <nr status="officieel">3</nr>
              </kop>
              <al>Material and labour needed for maintenance.</al><al>(Including, where applicable, spare parts, material and labour - excluding B-1 and B-2 - for maintenance of buildings and appurtenances thereto, antenna towers and counterpoises, machinery and tools, storage tanks, communications equipment, cables, meteorological equipment, vehicles, boats, office and housing equipment, etc.)</al></artikel>
            <artikel status="goed">
              <kop>
                <nr status="officieel">4</nr>
              </kop>
              <al>Miscellaneous additional necessary maintenance expenses.
</al><al>(Including any single item of new or renewed equipment totalling not
more than five hundred United States dollars, which it is not practicable
to amortize, contractual repairs away from a Station and transportation
connected therewith, etc.).</al></artikel>
          </afdeling>
          <afdeling status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>PART </label>
              <nr status="officieel">C</nr>
              <titel status="officieel">&#x2014; INDIRECT EXPENSES</titel>
            </kop>
            <artikel status="goed">
              <kop>
                <nr status="officieel">1</nr>
              </kop>
              <al>Miscellaneous overhead including administration. - For administration of the Services listed in Annex I, a charge of 10% on the total direct expenses on items listed in Parts A and B of this Annex. Except that for the amount specified in Section I, paragraphs 6, 7, 8, 9, 10 and 11 herein, only 5% may be charged.</al></artikel>
            <artikel status="goed">
              <kop>
                <nr status="officieel">2</nr>
                <titel status="officieel"/>
              </kop>
              <al>Depreciation. - Commencing with the calendar year following that in which implementation is completed depreciation shall be charged at the following rates, provided that it shall not be charged in respect of buildings and equipment which have been completely depreciated except when renewal of such buildings or equipment has been undertaken from provision for depreciation; in which case depreciation may be charged until the renewed buildings or equipment have also been depreciated.</al>
							
							
							<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." type="expliciet">
								<li>
									<li.nr>2.1.</li.nr>
									<al>Depreciation of the capital expenditures calculated in U.S. Dollars:</al>
									<lijst><li><li.nr>a)</li.nr><al>Automatic AFTN relay at Gufunes: $37 931 per annum for the years 1979 to 1988 inclusive.</al></li><li><li.nr>b)</li.nr><al>Automatic message distribution system at the Area Control Centre Reykjavik: $20 664 per annum from 1981 to 1989 inclusive and $20 666 in 1990.</al></li></lijst>
								</li>
							<li>
											<li.nr>2.2.</li.nr>
											<al>Buildings and appurtenances thereto at:</al>
											
											<table><tgroup cols="3"><colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="*"/><colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="*"/><colspec colname="col3" colnum="3" colwidth="*"/><tbody><row><entry colname="col1"/><entry colname="col2"><al>
																	<nadruk type="cur">Rate</nadruk>
																</al></entry><entry colname="col3"/></row><row><entry colname="col1"><al>Keflavik</al></entry><entry colname="col2"><al>6,66 <nadruk>%</nadruk></al></entry><entry colname="col3"/></row><row><entry colname="col1"><al>Gufunes</al></entry><entry colname="col2"><al>2 <nadruk type="cur">%</nadruk></al></entry><entry colname="col3"><al>(except for the building for extended range general purposes VHF facilities which is depreciated at 6,66<nadruk>%</nadruk>)</al></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table><al>per annum of the values specified as the basis for depreciation in Annex II.</al>
										</li><li>
											<li.nr>2.3.</li.nr>
											<al>All equipment at a rate of 10% per annum of the value specified as the basis for depreciation in Annex II, except:</al>
											<table frame="topbot">
												<tgroup cols="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
													<colspec colname="col01" colnum="1" colwidth="2.00*"/><colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="2.00*"/><colspec colname="col1" colnum="3" colwidth="1*"/><tbody>
														<row rowsep="1">
															<entry nameend="col1" namest="col01">
																<al>
																	<nadruk type="cur">Rate</nadruk>
																</al>
															</entry>
															
														</row>
														<row>
															<entry>
																<al>Office and housing equipment</al>
																<al>Cables, armoured</al>
																</entry><entry colname="col2"><al>}</al></entry>
															<entry colname="col1">
																<al>5%</al>
																<al>5%</al>
																
															</entry>
														</row><row><entry><al>Vehicles</al>
															</entry><entry colname="col2"/><entry colname="col1"><al>20%</al></entry></row>
													</tbody>
												</tgroup>
											</table>
										</li></lijst>
            </artikel>
            <artikel status="goed">
              <kop>
                <nr status="officieel">3</nr>
              </kop>
              <al>Interest. - Interest on unamortized capital expenditures at Gufunes in paragraph 2.1 a) is to be calculated in U.S. Dollars at an interest rate equal to the LIBO (London Inter Bank Offer) rate applicable to the respective interest payment periods plus 1%. In all other cases, interest on capital invested in buildings and equipment is not to be charged in excess of 10% per annum and not exceeding the official prevailing rate in Iceland of the value specified for depreciation in Annex II, as adjusted by annual depreciation and taking into account renewals of buildings and equipment met from provision for depreciation.</al>
							<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." type="expliciet">
								<li>
									<li.nr>3.1.</li.nr>
									<al>Interest on renewals and new capital investment will be charged commencing with the year following that in which implementation is completed. In respect of the period preceding the commencement of depreciation, an amount will be included in the total capital cost to be shown in the inventory. Such amount will be equivalent to 6 months' interest when implementation is completed within one calendar year, to 12 months' interest when implementation is completed within two calendar years, to 18 months' interest when implementation is completed within three calendar years, etc.</al>
									
									
								</li>
							</lijst>
            </artikel>
            
          <artikel status="goed"><kop><nr>4</nr></kop><al>Residual value. - The residual value of fixed assets disposed of should be charged to depreciation in the year of disposition and the proceeds from disposition, if any, should be credited under sub-heading &#x201C;Proceeds from sale of inventory items&#x201D; in the same year.</al></artikel></afdeling>
        <afdeling><kop><label>PART</label><nr>D</nr><titel>&#x2014; UNAMORTIZED CAPITAL EXPENDITURES RELATED TO THE TWENTY-YEAR CABLE CIRCUIT LEASES</titel></kop><artikel status="goed"><kop><nr>1</nr></kop><al>Cancellation charges for the 20-year leases for the rental of the cable circuits referred to in Section I hereto are based on and do not exceed the unamortized part of the capital expenditures related to these leased cable circuits. In the event of termination of the Agreement or withdrawal from participation by a Contracting Government prior to the expiry of the said leases, cancellation charges are payable on the unamortized part of the capital expenditures pursuant to Article XXIV, para. 2, and XXV respectively, in accordance with the following tabulation, but may be increased by an amount corresponding to any inescapable expenditures caused by the cancellation. The following tabulation of the unamortized capital expenditures is based on the sinking fund (annuity) method using an interest rate of six per cent.</al><table frame="none">
<tgroup cols="4" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<tbody>
<row valign="top">
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>After</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>0 year</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al><nadruk type="vet">US $</nadruk></al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>2,144,730</al></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>&#x201D;</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>1 year</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>2,086,434</al></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>&#x201D;</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>2 years</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>2,024,634</al></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>&#x201D;</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>3 &#x201E;</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>1,959,132</al></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>&#x201D;</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>4 &#x201E;</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>1,889,685</al></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>After</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>5 years</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>1,816,068</al></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>&#x201D;</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>6 &#x201E;</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>1,738,056</al></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>&#x201D;</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>7 &#x201E;</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>1,655,351</al></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>&#x201D;</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>8 &#x201E;</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>1,567,672</al></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>&#x201D;</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>9 &#x201E;</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>1,474,758</al></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>After</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>10 years</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>1,376,252</al></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>&#x201D;</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>11 &#x201E;</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>1,271,838</al></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>&#x201D;</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>12 .&#x201E;</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>1,161,160</al></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>&#x201D;</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>13 &#x201E;</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>1,043,843</al></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>&#x201D;</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>14 &#x201E;</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>919,478</al></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>After</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>15 years</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>787,670</al></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>&#x201D;</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>16 &#x201E;</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>647,933</al></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>&#x201D;</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>17 &#x201E;</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>499,820</al></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>&#x201D;</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>18 &#x201E;</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>342,824</al></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>&#x201D;</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>19 &#x201E;</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>176,405</al></entry>
</row>
<row valign="top">
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>&#x201D;</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>20 &#x201E;</al></entry>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"/>
<entry colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>0</al></entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><nr>2</nr></kop><al>Notwithstanding the cancellation charges stated in paragraph 1 above in calculating the sum due to the cable companies in the event of cancellation of the leases, account should be taken of the possibility that the companies can economically make use of the leased cables and, further, of any utilization in excess of 2 voice circuits and eight duplex teletypewriter circuits (or their revenue equivalent at the rate of: Greenland/Iceland $ 436,012) in the period up to the time of cancellation.</al></artikel></afdeling></titeldeel>
      <titeldeel><kop><label>SECTION</label><nr>III</nr><titel>USER CHARGES</titel></kop><artikel status="goed">
<kop>
<nr>1</nr>
</kop>
<al>Pursuant to Article XIV of this Agreement, on or before 20 November 1982 the Council shall determine a single user charge per civil aircraft crossing for the calendar year 1983 for the Jointly Financed Services. The charge shall be calculated by dividing ninety-five per cent of the approved estimated costs, expressed in United States dollars, allocable to civil aviation for 1983 (as defined in paragraph 6 below) plus an adjustment for under-recovery or minus an adjustment for overrecovery in 1981 (calculated in accordance with paragraphs 3, 4 and 5 below) by the total number of crossings in 1981, rounded off to the nearest United States dollar.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<nr>2</nr>
</kop>
<al>The provisions of paragraph 1 above, with appropriate revision of the years mentioned therein, shall govern the calculation of the user charge per civil aircraft crossing for the calendar year 1984 and thereafter.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<nr>3</nr>
</kop>
<al>The over- or under-recovery referred to in paragraph 1 above is the difference between the amount subject to collection in any year (paragraph 4 below) and the total amounts billed to users in that year (paragraph 5 below).</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<nr>4</nr>
</kop>
<al>The amount subject to collection in 1981 (for calculation of the 1983 user charge) is eighty per cent of ninety-five per cent of the approved costs allocable to civil aviation in 1981 plus the under-recovery in 1979. In 1982 it is ninety-five per cent of the approved costs allocable to civil aviation in 1982 plus the under-recovery in 1980. For 1983 and thereafter the amount subject to collection will be ninety-five per cent of the approved costs allocable to civil aviation in that year, less the over-recovery or plus the under-recovery of two years earlier.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<nr>5</nr>
</kop>
<al>In calculating the user charge for 1983, the amounts billed to users for 1981 (required to establish the over-or under-recovery for 1981) shall be calculated by multiplying that portion of the 1981 user charge in pounds sterling pertaining to this Agreement by the number of crossings in 1981, then converting to United States dollars at the rates of exchange agreed for 1981. In subsequent years the amounts billed to users shall be calculated in the same way with appropriate changes of year.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<nr>6</nr>
</kop>
<al>For the purpose of calculation of user charges, the following percentages of the jointly financed costs (i.e. ninety-five per cent of the total costs) are allocable to international civil aviation:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>a)</li.nr><al>100 per cent of Air Traffic Services;</al></li><li><li.nr>b)</li.nr><al>30 per cent of the Meteorological Services (surface and upper-air synoptic observations) and related meteorological telecommunication services;</al></li><li><li.nr>c)</li.nr><al>100 per cent of the international aviation function of the Meteorological Office at Reykjavik;</al></li><li><li.nr>d)</li.nr><al>100 per cent of Aeronautical Communication and the Cable Services (excluding MET/COM).</al></li></lijst></artikel></titeldeel><titeldeel><kop><label> SECTION</label><nr>IV</nr><titel>ACTUAL COST REPORTS</titel></kop><structuurtekst><al>The statement of actual costs of the Services referred to in paragraph
2 of Article VIII of this Agreement shall be furnished in United States
dollars. For this purpose, actual Kronur expenditures in each calendar
month shall be converted to United States dollars using the midmarket
rate of exchange as provided by the Central Bank of Iceland for the first
day of that month. These conversions shall be included in the audit
referred to in paragraph 2 of Article VIII.</al></structuurtekst></titeldeel></wettekst>
    </verdragtekst>
  </verdrag>
  <verdrag status="goed" tekst="vertaling" xml:lang="nl">
    <verdragtekst>
      <kop>
        <titel status="officieel">Overeenkomst inzake gezamenlijke financiering van bepaalde diensten voor de luchtvaartnavigatie in IJsland</titel>
      </kop>
      <aanhef>
        <preambule>
          <al>De Regeringen van Belgi&#xEB;, Canada, Denemarken, Frankrijk, de Bondsrepubliek Duitsland, IJsland, Isra&#xEB;l, Itali&#xEB;, Nederland, Noorwegen, Zweden, Zwitserland, het Verenigd Koninkrijk van Groot-Britanni&#xEB; en Noord-Ierland en de Verenigde Staten van Amerika, welke lid zijn van de Internationale Burgerlijke Luchtvaart Organisatie,</al>
          <al>VERLANGEND overeenkomstig de voorwaarden en met inachtneming van de bepalingen van hoofdstuk XV van het Verdrag inzake de Internationale Burgerlijke Luchtvaart een overeenkomst te sluiten inzake de gezamenlijke financiering van bepaalde diensten voor de luchtvaartnavigatie welke door de Regering van IJsland zullen worden verschaft:</al>
        </preambule>
        <afkondiging>
          <al>ZIJN OVEREENGEKOMEN als volgt:</al>
        </afkondiging>
      </aanhef>
      <wettekst>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Artikel</label>
            <nr status="officieel">I</nr>
          </kop>
          <al>In deze Overeenkomst wordt verstaan onder:</al>
          <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
            <li>
              <li.nr>(a)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x201E;Organisatie&#x201D;: de Internationale Burgerlijke Luchtvaart Organisatie;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>(b)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x201E;Raad&#x201D;: de Raad van de Organisatie;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>(c)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x201E;Secretaris-Generaal&#x201D;: de Secretaris-Generaal van de Organisatie;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>(d)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x201E;Diensten&#x201D;: de in Bijlage I van deze Overeenkomst omschreven diensten en alle bijkomende diensten die van tijd tot tijd ingevolge deze Overeenkomst verschaft kunnen worden.</al>
            </li>
          </lijst>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Artikel</label>
            <nr status="officieel">II</nr>
          </kop>
          <al>De Regering van IJsland verschaft, exploiteert en onderhoudt de Diensten en zal in verband met speciale voordelen, voortvloeiende uit de Diensten, vijf procent van de goedgekeurde werkelijke kosten daarvan dragen.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Artikel</label>
            <nr status="officieel">III</nr>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>De Regering van IJsland exploiteert en onderhoudt de Diensten zonder onderbreking, op doelmatige wijze en zo economisch mogelijk en, voor zover uitvoerbaar, overeenkomstig de van toepassing zijnde maatstaven, aanbevolen werkwijzen, procedures en specificaties van de Organisatie.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>Met inachtneming van de bepalingen van Bijlage I van deze Overeenkomst zal de wijze waarop meteorologische waarnemingen worden verricht en waarop meteorologische rapporten worden gemaakt en verspreid in overeenstemming zijn met de desbetreffende procedures en specificaties, voorgeschreven door de Wereld Meteorologische Organisatie.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al>De Regering van IJsland zal de Secretaris-Generaal onmiddellijk kennis geven van enige onvoorziene omstandigheid die enige tijdelijke wijziging of beperking van de Diensten noodzakelijk maakt en die Regering en de Secretaris-Generaal zullen daarop overleg plegen over de maatregelen die genomen moeten worden om enige nadelige invloed van een dergelijke wijziging of beperking tot het minimum te beperken.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Artikel</label>
            <nr status="officieel">IV</nr>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>De Secretaris-Generaal heeft het algemeen toezicht op de exploitatie van de Diensten en kan te allen tijde maatregelen treffen voor de inspectie van de Diensten, met inbegrip van alle apparatuur of uitrusting die in verband hiermede wordt gebruikt.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>De Regering van IJsland zal op verzoek van de Secretaris-Generaal en voor zover uitvoerbaar die rapporten betreffende de exploitatie van de Diensten overleggen, die de Secretaris-Generaal wenselijk acht.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al>De Secretaris-Generaal zal op verzoek van de Regering van IJsland voor zover uitvoerbaar zulke inlichtingen verschaffen als die Regering redelijkerwijs kan verlangen met betrekking tot de nakoming van haar verplichtingen ingevolge deze Overeenkomst.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr>
            <al>Ingeval de Regering van IJsland op enigerlei wijze in gebreke blijft enige van de Diensten op doelmatige wijze te exploiteren of te onderhouden, zal er overleg plaats hebben tussen die Regering en de Secretaris-Generaal teneinde tot overeenstemming te komen met betrekking tot de daartegen te nemen maatregelen.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Artikel</label>
            <nr status="officieel">V</nr>
          </kop>
          <al>De totale kosten van de Diensten, berekend overeenkomstig de Bijlagen II en III van deze Overeenkomst, mogen voor een kalenderjaar een bedrag van 4.321.166 Amerikaanse dollar niet te boven gaan. Deze limiet mag door de Raad verhoogd worden hetzij met toestemming van alle Overeenkomstsluitende Regeringen, hetzij als resultaat van de toepassing van het bepaalde in artikel VI.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Artikel</label>
            <nr status="officieel">VI</nr>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>Slechts voor het oprichten, exploiteren en onderhouden van diensten waarin overigens ingevolge deze Overeenkomst niet wordt voorzien kan de ingevolge de bepalingen van artikel V vastgestelde limiet worden verhoogd met een bepaald bedrag met toestemming van de Overeenkomstsluitende Regeringen die gezamenlijk verantwoordelijk zijn voor niet minder dan negentig procent van de totale aanslagen, vastgesteld met inachtneming van de bepalingen van de leden 3, 4, 5 en 6 van artikel VII met betrekking tot het laatste kalenderjaar waarvoor aanslagen zijn vastgesteld.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>

            <al>Met inachtneming van de bepalingen van artikel II zullen alle uitgaven ingevolge de diensten, genoemd in lid 1 van dit artikel, of alle uitgaven, mogelijk gemaakt ingevolge de bepalingen van lid 2 (<nadruk type="cur">a</nadruk>) van artikel XIII als gevolg van het opnemen van die diensten in deze Overeenkomst, alleen worden gedragen door de Overeenkomstsluitende Regeringen die hiertoe hun toestemming hebben verleend, in aandelen die tot elkaar in dezelfde relatieve verhouding staan als de aandelen van die Regeringen in de genoemde totale aanslagen voor het betreffende jaar, en geen gedeelte van het Reserve Fonds, genoemd in artikel X, dat niet toewijsbaar is aan die diensten, zal worden gebruikt voor doeleinden voor welke slechts die Regeringen hun toestemming hebben gegeven.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Artikel</label>
            <nr status="officieel">VII</nr>
          </kop>
          <lid>
<lidnr>1</lidnr><al>Met inachtneming van het bepaalde in artikel V en artikel VI, tweede lid, komen de Overeenkomstsluitende Regeringen overeen deel te nemen in vijfennegentig procent van de goedgekeurde werkelijke kosten van de Diensten, als bepaald overeenkomstig de bepalingen van artikel VIII, naar verhouding van het nut voor haar luchtvaart dat iedere Overeenkomstsluitende Regering daarvan heeft. Deze verhouding wordt voor elke Overeenkomstsluitende Regering voor elk kalenderjaar bepaald door het aantal vluchten tussen Europa en Noord-Amerika, waarvan een gedeelte ligt ten noorden van de 45ste Noordelijke breedtegraad tussen 15&#xB0; en 50&#xB0; Westerlengte, in dat jaar met haar burgerluchtvaartuigen verricht. Daarnaast:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>a)</li.nr><al>wordt een vlucht tussen alleen Groenland en Canada, Groenland en de Verenigde Staten van Amerika, Groenland en IJsland of IJsland en Europa gerekend als een derde van een vlucht;</al></li><li><li.nr>b)</li.nr><al>wordt een vlucht tussen alleen Groenland en Europa, IJsland en Canada of IJsland en de Verenigde Staten van Amerika gerekend als twee derde van een vlucht; en</al></li><li><li.nr>c)</li.nr><al>wordt een vlucht naar of van Europa of IJsland waarbij niet over de kust van Noord-Amerika wordt gevlogen, maar over 30&#xB0; Westerlengte ten noorden van de 45ste Noordelijke breedtegraad wordt gevlogen, gerekend als een derde van een vlucht.</al></li></lijst></lid><lid><lidnr>2</lidnr><al>Voor de toepassing van het eerste lid van dit artikel:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>a)</li.nr><al>wordt een vlucht gerekend, zelfs wanneer het punt van opstijgen of landen niet in de in dat lid vermelde gebieden is gelegen; en</al></li><li><li.nr>b)</li.nr><al>omvat &#x201E;Europa&#x201D; niet IJsland of de Azoren.</al></li></lijst></lid><lid><lidnr>3</lidnr><al>Elk jaar op of v&#xF3;&#xF3;r 20 november slaat de Raad de Overeenkomstsluitende Regeringen aan ten einde te voorzien in voorschotten voor het volgende jaar. Voor het jaar 1983 zijn de aanslagen op basis van het aantal vluchten in 1981 en vijfennegentig procent van de geraamde kosten voor 1983. De aanslag van elke Overeenkomstsluitende Regering wordt gecorrigeerd om rekening te houden met eventuele verschillen tussen de door haar aan de Organisatie betaalde bedragen als voorschotten voor 1981 en haar aandeel, zoals bepaald door haar vluchten in 1981, in de vijfennegentig procent van de goedgekeurde werkelijke kosten in 1981. De gecorrigeerde aanslag van elke Overeenkomstsluitende Regering wordt verminderd met haar aandeel, zoals bepaald door haar vluchten in 1981, in de geraamde inkomsten uit de heffingen aan gebruikers die ingevolge artikel XIV in 1983 aan IJsland moeten worden overgemaakt.</al></lid><lid><lidnr>4</lidnr><al>De in het derde lid van dit artikel uiteengezette procedure geldt voor de aanslagen voor het jaar 1984 met passende wijzigingen wat het jaar betreft.</al></lid><lid><lidnr>5</lidnr><al>Voor 1985 geldt de in het derde lid van dit artikel bedoelde procedure, met passende wijzigingen wat het jaar betreft, en daarnaast wordt de aanslag van elke Overeenkomstsluitende Regering nader gecorrigeerd om rekening te houden met eventuele verschillen tussen haar aandeel in de geraamde inkomsten uit de heffingen aan gebruikers over 1983 en haar aandeel, zoals bepaald door haar vluchten in 1983, in de door accountants gecontroleerde werkelijke heffingen aan gebruikers die in 1983 aan IJsland zijn overgemaakt.</al></lid><lid><lidnr>6</lidnr><al>De procedure voor 1985 geldt in de volgende jaren met passende wijzigingen wat het jaar betreft.</al></lid><lid><lidnr>7</lidnr><al>Te beginnen op 1 januari 1983, betaalt elke Overeenkomstsluitende Regering, op 1 januari en 1 juli van elk kalenderjaar, in halfjaarlijkse termijnen aan de Organisatie het bedrag waarvoor zij is aangeslagen met betrekking tot de voorschotten voor het lopende kalenderjaar, gecorrigeerd en verminderd zoals bepaald in het derde, vierde, vijfde en zesde lid van dit artikel.</al></lid><lid><lidnr>8</lidnr><al>In geval van be&#xEB;indiging van deze Overeenkomst past de Raad een verrekening toe, ten einde aan het bepaalde in dit artikel te voldoen met betrekking tot enige periode waarvoor de betalingen op het tijdstip van be&#xEB;indiging van de Overeenkomst, nog niet zijn verrekend overeenkomstig het derde, vierde, vijfde en zesde lid van dit artikel.</al></lid><lid><lidnr>9</lidnr><al>Elk jaar op of v&#xF3;&#xF3;r 1 mei verstrekt elke Overeenkomstsluitende Regering aan de Secretaris-Generaal, in de door de Secretaris-Generaal voor te schrijven vorm, volledige gegevens over de vluchten waarop dit artikel van toepassing is, die zijn gemaakt in het voorgaande kalenderjaar.</al></lid><lid><lidnr>10</lidnr><al>De Overeenkomstsluitende Regeringen kunnen overeenkomen dat de in het negende lid van dit artikel bedoelde gegevens namens hen door een andere Regering aan de Secretaris-Generaal worden verstrekt.</al></lid></artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Artikel</label>
            <nr status="officieel">VIII</nr>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>De Regering van IJsland legt op of v&#xF3;&#xF3;r 15 september van elk jaar aan de Secretaris-Generaal begrotingen over, uitgedrukt in Amerikaanse dollars, van de kosten van de Diensten voor het volgende kalenderjaar. De begrotingen worden opgesteld overeenkomstig artikel III en de Bijlagen II en III van deze Overeenkomst.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>De Regering van IJsland zal aan de Secretaris-Generaal, niet later dan zes maanden na het eind van elk kalenderjaar, een opgave verstrekken van de werkelijk gemaakte kosten van de Diensten gedurende dat jaar. De Secretaris-Generaal zal de opgave aan zodanige verificatie en ander onderzoek onderwerpen als hij geschikt acht en zal aan de Regering van IJsland een rapport van de verificatie overleggen.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al>De Regering van IJsland zal aan de Secretaris-Generaal zulke aanvullende inlichtingen verstrekken met betrekking tot enige raming van de kosten of opgave van werkelijke kosten, als de Secretaris-Generaal wenselijk acht, evenals alle beschikbare inlichtingen over de mate waarin van de Diensten wordt gebruik gemaakt door vliegtuigen van enige nationaliteit.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr>
            <al>De opgave van de werkelijke kosten voor elk jaar is onderworpen aan de goedkeuring van de Raad.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">5</lidnr>
            <al>De opgave van de werkelijke kosten, goedgekeurd door de Raad overeenkomstig de bepalingen van lid 4 van dit artikel, zal worden rondgezonden aan de Overeenkomstsluitende Regeringen.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Artikel</label>
            <nr status="officieel">IX</nr>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>Vijf en negentig procent van de door de Raad goedgekeurde werkelijke kosten voor het verschaffen, exploiteren en onderhouden van de Diensten zal aan de Regering van IJsland worden terugbetaald.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>Nadat de Raad zich ervan heeft overtuigd dat de door de Regering van IJsland overeenkomstig artikel VIII, eerste lid, ingediende begrotingen zijn opgesteld overeenkomstig artikel III en de Bijlagen II en III van deze Overeenkomst, machtigt hij de Secretaris-Generaal betalingen te doen aan die Regering met betrekking tot elk kwartaal, niet later dan de eerste dag van de tweede maand van dat kwartaal. De betalingen zijn gebaseerd op genoemde begrotingen en vormen voorschotten, onderworpen aan verrekening als bepaald in het derde lid van dit artikel. Het totale bedrag van deze betalingen overschrijdt voor geen enkel jaar de ingevolge de bepalingen van artikel V vastgestelde limiet. Met ingang van 1 januari 1983 behandelt de Regering van IJsland alle netto inkomsten uit heffingen aan gebruikers, ge&#xEF;nd van alle exploitanten van burgerluchtvaartuigen volgens een krachtens artikel XIV gehanteerd systeem, als deel van de voorschotten voor het jaar waarin deze inkomsten zijn ontvangen.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al>Na goedkeuring door de Raad van de opgave van de werkelijke kosten zal de Secretaris-Generaal in alle opeenvolgende kwartaalbetalingen aan de Regering van IJsland correcties aanbrengen, teneinde alle verschillen tussen de volgens lid 2 van dit artikel gedane betalingen over enig jaar en de goedgekeurde werkelijke kosten voor dat jaar te verrekenen.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr>
            <al>De Overeenkomstsluitende Regeringen die niet in de Raad zijn vertegenwoordigd zullen worden uitgenodigd deel te nemen aan de behandeling in de Raad of een van zijn onderafdelingen van de door de Regering van IJsland overeenkomstig de bepalingen van artikel VIII, lid 1, verstrekte opgaven.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">5</lidnr>
            <al>De kostenramingen, goedgekeurd door de Raad overeenkomstig de bepalingen van lid 2 van dit artikel, zullen aan de Overeenkomstsluitende Regeringen worden rondgezonden.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Artikel</label>
            <nr status="officieel">X</nr>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>De door de Organisatie overeenkomstig de bepalingen van artikel VII van de Overeenkomstsluitende Regeringen ontvangen betalingen zullen, voor zover zij niet van tijd tot tijd ingevolge deze Overeenkomst nodig zijn voor lopende betalingen aan de Regering van IJsland, een Reserve Fonds vormen, dat door de Organisatie voor de doeleinden van deze Overeenkomst zal worden aangewend.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>De Secretaris-Generaal kan er voor zorgdragen dat het Reserve Fonds voor korte termijn ge&#xEF;nvesteerd wordt. De Organisatie zal recht hebben op de daaruit voortvloeiende interest. Indien deze interest onvoldoende is om de buitengewone uitgaven van de Organisatie te dekken, die uit deze Overeenkomst voortvloeien, zal het overblijvende verschil worden beschouwd als een bijkomend gedeelte van de werkelijke kosten van de Diensten en aan de Organisatie worden terugbetaald uit de door de Overeenkomstsluitende Regeringen gedane betalingen.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Artikel</label>
            <nr status="officieel">XI</nr>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>De jaarlijkse aanslagen van de Overeenkomstsluitende Regeringen worden uitgedrukt in Amerikaanse dollars.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>Elk der Overeenkomstsluitende Regeringen doet betalingen aan de Organisatie overeenkomstig de bepalingen van artikel VII in Amerikaanse dollars of in ponden sterling of, mits de Regering van IJsland daarmede instemt, in IJslandse kronen. De procedure voor de bepaling van de op een in ponden sterling of IJslandse kronen verrichte betaling toepasselijke wisselkoers wordt vastgesteld door de Raad in overleg met de betrokken Regeringen.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al>De Secretaris-Generaal zal, behoudens dat de buitengewone uitgaven van de Organisatie in Amerikaanse dollars aan deze worden terugbetaald, aan de Regering van IJsland, overeenkomstig de bepalingen, vervat in de artikelen IX en XII, betalingen doen in de valuta waarin de Overeenkomstsluitende Regeringen hun betalingen hebben gedaan aan de Organisatie, voor zover beschikbaar.</al>
          </lid>
          
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Artikel</label>
            <nr status="officieel">XII</nr>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>De verplichting van de Secretaris-Generaal, ingevolge deze Overeenkomst aan de Regering van IJsland betalingen te doen, zal beperkt zijn tot de bedragen die werkelijk door de Organisatie zijn ontvangen en volgens de bepalingen van deze Overeenkomst beschikbaar zijn.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>De Secretaris-Generaal kan niettemin, in afwachting van de ontvangst van betalingen van de Overeenkomstsluitende Regeringen en in  overeenstemming met de financi&#xEB;le bepalingen van de Organisatie, voorschotten verstrekken voor aan de Regering van IJsland verschuldigde betalingen, in gevallen waarin hij zulke voorschotten onontbeerlijk acht voor de instelling en ononderbroken voortzetting van de Diensten.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al>Geen Overeenkomstsluitende Regering zal de Organisatie aansprakelijk kunnen stellen wegens het feit dat enige andere Overeenkomstsluitende Regering haar betalingen met betrekking tot deze Overeenkomst niet verricht.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Artikel</label>
            <nr status="officieel">XIII</nr>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>De Raad kan, met inachtneming van de bepalingen van artikel V en lid 2 van artikel VI en in overeenstemming met de Regering van IJsland, in deze Overeenkomst nieuwe kapitaalsuitgaven opnemen, die noodzakelijk zijn voor de goede exploitatie van de Diensten.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>De Raad kan, met inachtneming van de bepalingen van de artikelen V en VI en in overeenstemming met de Regering van IJsland, in deze Overeenkomst, naast de in Bijlage I genoemde Diensten, diensten en nieuwe kapitaalsuitgaven met betrekking tot deze diensten opnemen, mits aan &#xE9;&#xE9;n van de volgende voorwaarden wordt voldaan:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>a)</li.nr><al>het totale bedrag van dergelijke uitgaven in enig jaar gaat 3,5 procent van de ingevolge artikel V goedgekeurde kostenlimiet niet te boven; of</al></li><li><li.nr>b)</li.nr><al>alle Overeenkomstsluitende Regeringen hebben tot dergelijke diensten hun toestemming gegeven; of</al></li><li><li.nr>c)</li.nr><al>de Overeenkomstsluitende Regeringen die gezamenlijk verantwoordelijk zijn voor niet minder dan negentig procent van de totale aanslagen, vastgesteld ingevolge de bepalingen van het derde, vierde, vijfde en zesde lid, van artikel VII hebben toegestemd tot dergelijke diensten en de bepalingen van artikel VI zijn erop toegepast.</al></li></lijst>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al>Voor de toepassing van de leden 1 en 2 van dit artikel zal vernieuwing van gebouwen en uitrusting uit betalingen, ontvangen op grond van depreciatie, niet als nieuwe kapitaalsuitgave worden beschouwd.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr>
            <al>Indien nieuwe kapitaalsuitgaven of additionele diensten worden voorgesteld door de Regering van IJsland of door de Raad, zal die Regering aan de Secretaris-Generaal een kostenraming daarvan verstrekken, alsmede die specificaties, plannen en andere inlichtingen welke met betrekking daartoe vereist kunnen zijn, en zal zij met de Secretaris-Generaal overleg plegen betreffende de wijze waarop hierin zal worden voorzien of het ontwerp of de constructie welke dient te worden toegepast.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">5</lidnr>
            <al>De Raad kan in overeenstemming met de Regering van IJsland ieder gedeelte van de Diensten van de Overeenkomst uitsluiten.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">6</lidnr>
            <al>Wanneer lid 1, 2 of 5 van dit artikel is toegepast, zal de Raad de Bijlagen van deze Overeenkomst dienovereenkomstig wijzigen.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Artikel</label>
            <nr status="officieel">XIV</nr>
          </kop>
          <al>De Regering van IJsland hanteert een systeem van heffingen aan gebruikers voor de Diensten verschaft aan alle burgerluchtvaartuigen die vluchten maken zoals omschreven in artikel VII. Deze heffingen worden berekend overeenkomstig Bijlage III van deze Overeenkomst. De netto inkomsten uit deze heffingen worden in mindering gebracht op ingevolge de bepalingen van deze Overeenkomst aan de Regering van IJsland verschuldigde betalingen. Behalve met toestemming van de Raad heft de Regering van IJsland geen bijkomende heffingen voor de Diensten, van anderen dan haar eigen onderdanen.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Artikel</label>
            <nr status="officieel">XV</nr>
          </kop>
          <al>De Regering van IJsland zal geen enkele internationale regeling treffen voor het verschaffen, de exploitatie, het onderhouden, ontwikkelen of financieren van enige of alle van de Diensten zonder de goedkeuring van de Raad.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Artikel</label>
            <nr status="officieel">XVI</nr>
          </kop>
          <al>De Regering van IJsland zal zoveel mogelijk samenwerken met de vertegenwoordigers van de Organisatie tot verwezenlijking van de doelstellingen van deze Overeenkomst en zal aan die vertegenwoordigers de voorrechten en immuniteiten toekennen waar zij recht op hebben volgens het Algemeen Verdrag nopens de Voorrechten en Immuniteiten van de Gespecialiseerde Organisaties van de Verenigde Naties, met inbegrip van Aanhangsel III (2) daarvan.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Artikel</label>
            <nr status="officieel">XVII</nr>
          </kop>
          <al>De Raad zal een conferentie bijeenroepen van alle belanghebbende Overeenkomstsluitende Regeringen:</al>
          <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
            <li>
              <li.nr>(a)</li.nr>
              <al>op verzoek van twee of meer van de Overeenkomstsluitende Regeringen of van de Regering van IJsland, of van een van de Overeenkomstsluitende Regeringen indien een dergelijke conferentie gedurende de vijf voorgaande jaren niet is gehouden;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>(b)</li.nr>
              <al>wanneer het verzuim van een der Overeenkomstsluitende Regeringen haar betalingen te doen met betrekking tot deze Overeenkomst een herziening van de aanslagen noodzakelijk maakt, welke niet anders op bevredigende wijze kan worden geregeld, of</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>(c)</li.nr>
              <al>wanneer de Raad om enige andere reden een dergelijke conferentie noodzakelijk acht.</al>
            </li>
          </lijst>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Artikel</label>
            <nr status="officieel">XVIII</nr>
          </kop>
          <al>Elk geschil betreffende de uitlegging of toepassing van deze Overeenkomst of van de Bijlagen daarvan, dat niet door onderhandelingen is beslecht, zal op verzoek van een Overeenkomstsluitende Regering die partij is bij het geschil om advies naar de Raad worden verwezen.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Artikel</label>
            <nr status="officieel">XIX</nr>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>Deze Overeenkomst zal tot 1 december 1956 open blijven voor ondertekening door in de preambule genoemde Regeringen.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>Deze Overeenkomst zal onderworpen zijn aan aanvaarding door de ondertekenende Regeringen. De akten van aanvaarding zullen zo spoedig mogelijk bij de Secretaris-Generaal worden nedergelegd, die alle ondertekenende en toetredende Regeringen in kennis zal stellen van de datum van nederlegging van elke zodanige akte.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Artikel</label>
            <nr status="officieel">XX</nr>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>Tot deze Overeenkomst kan toetreden de Regering van elke Staat die lid is van de Verenigde Naties of van een daarmede verbonden Gespecialiseerde Organisatie. Toetreding geschiedt door nederlegging van een formele akte bij de Secretaris-Generaal.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>De Raad kan overleg openen met elke geen partij bij deze Overeenkomst zijnde Regering welker burgerluchtvaartlijnen profiteren van de Diensten, teneinde haar toetreding tot de Overeenkomst te bewerkstelligen.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al>Onverminderd de bepalingen van lid 2 van dit artikel kan de Raad overeenkomsten sluiten inzake bijdragen van enige Regering die geen partij wordt bij deze Overeenkomst. Alle ontvangen zodanige bijdragen zullen worden aangewend voor de doeleinden van deze Overeenkomst, als bepaald door de Raad.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Artikel</label>
            <nr status="officieel">XXI</nr>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>Deze Overeenkomst treedt &#x2014; niet eerder dan 1 januari 1957 &#x2014; in werking, wanneer akten van aanvaarding of toetreding zijn nedergelegd door Regeringen die gezamenlijk verantwoordelijk zijn voor eerste aanslagen tot een bedrag van niet minder dan negentig procent van het aanvankelijke maximum kostencijfer bepaald in artikel V. Wat die Regeringen betreft, wordt de nederlegging van een akte van aanvaarding of van toetreding geacht de toestemming te vormen tot het systeem van aanslagen, betalingen en verrekeningen ingevolge deze Overeenkomst voor de periode tussen 1 januari 1957 en de inwerkingtreding van deze Overeenkomst.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>Ten aanzien van iedere Regering welker akte van aanvaarding of van toetreding wordt nedergelegd na de inwerkingtreding van deze Overeenkomst wordt deze Overeenkomst van kracht op de datum van zodanige nederlegging. Elk van deze Regeringen stemt in met het systeem van aanslagen, betalingen en verrekeningen ingevolge deze Overeenkomst ingaande bij het begin van het kalenderjaar, waarin de akte van aanvaarding of van toetreding is nedergelegd. Elk van deze Regeringen kan desgewenst ermede instemmen, aangeslagen te worden voor haar deel van de goedgekeurde werkelijke kosten van alle diensten met betrekking tot welke de bepalingen van artikel VI zijn toegepast en tot welke op de datum van aanvaarding door zodanige Regering nog niet alle Overeenkomstsluitende Regeringen hebben toegestemd.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Artikel</label>
            <nr status="officieel">XXII</nr>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
              <li>
                <li.nr>(a)</li.nr>
                <al>Deze Overeenkomst kan worden be&#xEB;indigd door de Regering van IJsland op 31 december van enig jaar door schriftelijke kennisgeving, gedaan aan de Secretaris-Generaal niet later dan 1 januari van dat jaar.</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>(b)</li.nr>
                <al>Indien het te enigertijd de Regering van IJsland onmogelijk blijkt, de Diensten uit te voeren binnen de krachtens de bepalingen van artikel V gestelde limiet, zal die Regering de Secretaris-Generaal daarvan onmiddellijk schriftelijk in kennis stellen en zal zij aan de Secretaris-Generaal een gespecificeerde raming van het vereiste additionele bedrag verschaffen. De Secretaris-Generaal zal zodanige raming dadelijk aan een onderzoek onderwerpen en, na eventueel noodzakelijk overleg met die Regering, het boven de genoemde limiet benodigde bedrag bepalen. De Secretaris-Generaal zal daarop de Overeenkomstsluitende Regeringen benaderen teneinde hun toestemming te verkrijgen, als vereist ingevolge de bepalingen van artikel V. Tenzij binnen drie maanden, nadat de Secretaris-Generaal het vereiste additionele bedrag heeft bepaald, hij de Regering van IJsland mededeelt dat de Overeenkomstsluitende Regeringen hun toestemming hebben gegeven, kan de Regering van IJsland daarna deze Overeenkomst be&#xEB;indigen door schriftelijke kennisgeving aan de Secretaris-Generaal met inachtneming van een termijn van drie maanden.</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>(c)</li.nr>
                <al>Deze Overeenkomst kan op 31 december van enig jaar worden be&#xEB;indigd door andere Overeenkomstsluitende Regeringen dan de Regering van IJsland, welke verantwoordelijk zijn voor lopende aanslagen welke gezamenlijk niet minder bedragen dan tien procent van de krachtens artikel V bepaalde limiet, door schriftelijke kennisgeving aan de Secretaris-Generaal niet later dan 1 januari van dat jaar.</al>
              </li>
            </lijst>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>Na ontvangst van de mededeling van enige Overeenkomstwens, deze Overeenkomst in overeenstemming met lid 1 van dit artikel te be&#xEB;indigen, zal de Secretaris-Generaal de Overeenkomstsluitende Regeringen daarvan verwittigen.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Artikel</label>
            <nr status="officieel">XXIII</nr>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>

            <al>Onverminderd de bepalingen van artikel XXII kan elke andere Overeenkomstsluitende Regering dan de Regering van IJsland, waarvan de lopende aanslag minder bedraagt dan tien procent van de krachtens de bepalingen van artikel V bepaalde limiet, ophouden partij te zijn bij deze Overeenkomst op 31 december van enig jaar, door schriftelijke kennisgeving aan de Secretaris-Generaal, niet later dan 1 januari van dat jaar, van haar voornemen haar deelneming te be&#xEB;indigen. Elke zodanige kennisgeving zal ook worden beschouwd als een kennisgeving van de wens deze Overeenkomst te be&#xEB;indigen, voor de toepassing van artikel XXII, lid 1 (<nadruk type="cur">c</nadruk>).</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>Na ontvangst van een kennisgeving of kennisgevingen van de sluitende Regering, dat zij haar deelneming be&#xEB;indigt, zal de Secretaris-Generaal de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Regeringen daarvan verwittigen.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Artikel</label>
            <nr status="officieel">XXIV</nr>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>Ingeval van be&#xEB;indiging van deze Overeenkomst door de Regering van IJsland ingevolge de bepalingen van lid 1 van artikel XXII zal deze Regering aan de Organisatie betalen of kan de Organisatie van de aan die Regering krachtens deze Overeenkomst verschuldigde betalingen aftrekken een bedrag hetwelk een billijke vergoeding vormt voor voordelen, voortvloeiende uit het verkrijgen voor eigen doeleinden van roerende of onroerende goederen waarvan de kosten geheel of gedeeltelijk aan die Regering zijn terugbetaald ingevolge de bepalingen van deze Overeenkomst.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>Ingeval van be&#xEB;indiging van deze Overeenkomst door andere Overeenkomstsluitende Regeringen dan de Regering van IJsland, zal aan de Regering van IJsland uit het Reserve Fonds, of, indien het Fonds niet toereikend is, door de Overeenkomstsluitende Regeringen via de Organisatie, een billijk bedrag worden betaald bij wijze van vergoeding voor kapitaalsuitgaven welke die Regering heeft gedaan en die niet geheel zijn terugbetaald ingevolge deze Overeenkomst. Alle betalingen die voor dit doel van de Overeenkomstsluitende Regeringen worden gevorderd zullen worden berekend op basis van de meest recente aanslagcijfers en zullen verschuldigd zijn vanaf de datum van be&#xEB;indiging. De Organisatie zal het recht hebben alle roerende goederen over te nemen voor welke een vergoeding is betaald overeenkomstig dit lid. Met elke afstand van een dergelijk recht zal rekening worden gehouden bij het bepalen van de vergoeding.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al>De bepalingen van lid 2 van dit artikel zullen overeenkomstig van toepassing zijn met betrekking tot enig gedeelte van de Diensten, dat uitgesloten is van de Overeenkomst ingevolge de bepalingen van lid 5 van artikel XIII.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr>
            <al>Het bedrag van alle betalingen ingevolge dit artikel zal bij Overeenkomst tussen de Raad en de Regering van IJsland worden bepaald.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Artikel</label>
            <nr status="officieel">XXV</nr>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>Met inachtneming van de bepalingen van lid 2 van artikel X zullen alle saldi van het Reserve Fonds en van rente daarover, berustende onder de Organisatie op de datum dat deze Overeenkomst ophoudt van kracht te zijn, worden verdeeld onder en terugbetaald aan die Regeringen welke onmiddellijk v&#xF3;&#xF3;r die datum nog partij waren bij deze Overeenkomst, op basis van hun meest recente jaarlijkse aanslagen.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
              <li>
                <li.nr>(a)</li.nr>
                <al>Elke Regering die opgehouden heeft partij te zijn bij deze Overeenkomst ingevolge de bepalingen van artikel XXII zal alle verschillen tussen het aan de Organisatie overeenkomstig artikel VII door haar betaalde bedrag en het haar betreffende aandeel in de goedgekeurde werkelijke kosten met betrekking tot de periode van haar deelname betalen aan of ontvangen van de Organisatie.</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>(b)</li.nr>
                <al>Elke Regering die aldus opgehouden heeft partij te zijn zal aan de Organisatie haar aandeel in kapitaalsuitgaven betalen, welke zijn gedaan door de Regering van IJsland en welke niet geheel zijn terugbetaald overeenkomstig deze Overeenkomst. Het te betalen bedrag zal berekend worden op basis van het meest recente aanslagcijfer met betrekking tot de Regering welke heeft opgehouden partij te zijn. De betaling zal verschuldigd zijn vanaf het tijdstip van het ophouden partij te zijn.</al>
              </li>
            </lijst>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Artikel</label>
            <nr status="officieel">XXVI</nr>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>Deze Overeenkomst kan worden gewijzigd bij wederzijdse overeenstemming tussen de Overeenkomstsluitende Regeringen.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>De Raad zal, met inachtneming van de bepalingen van artikel V en artikel VI, lid 2, voor zover noodzakelijk de lijst van Overeenkomstsluitende Regeringen en de achter hun namen vermelde bedragen in artikel VII, lid 2, herzien, teneinde:</al>
            <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
              <li>
                <li.nr>(a)</li.nr>
                <al>op te nemen elke Regering die niet heeft ondertekend en toetreedt tot deze Overeenkomst, overeenkomstig lid 1 van artikel XX;</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>(b)</li.nr>
                <al>te compenseren alle betalingstekorten, voortvloeiende uit het feit dat een in lid 2 van artikel VII genoemde Regering geen partij wordt bij deze Overeenkomst, of</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>(c)</li.nr>
                <al>rekening te houden met diensten welke onder deze Overeenkomst zijn gebracht overeenkomstig de bepalingen van artikel XIII.</al>
              </li>
            </lijst>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al>De Raad kan ook in andere gevallen dan in die, genoemd in lid 6 van artikel XIII, de Bijlagen van deze Overeenkomst wijzigen, mits in overeenstemming met de in de Overeenkomst gestelde voorwaarden en met toestemming van de Regering van IJsland.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
      </wettekst>
      <wetsluiting status="goed">
        <slotformulering>
          <al>TEN BLIJKE WAARVAN de ondergetekenden, daartoe behoorlijk gemachtigd, namens hun onderscheiden Regeringen deze Overeenkomst hebben ondertekend op de achter hun handtekeningen vermelde data.</al>
          <al>GEDAAN te Gen&#xE8;ve, de vijfentwintigste dag van september van het jaar negentienhonderd zesenvijftig, in de Engelse, de Franse en de Spaanse taal, welke drie teksten gelijkelijk authentiek zijn, in een enkel exemplaar, dat zal worden nedergelegd bij de Internationale Burgerlijke Luchtvaart Organisatie, waar het overeenkomstig artikel XIX open zal blijven voor ondertekening. De Secretaris-Generaal van de Organisatie zal gewaarmerkte afschriften van deze Overeenkomst aan alle ondertekenende en toetredende Regeringen zenden.</al>
        </slotformulering>
      </wetsluiting>
    </verdragtekst>
  <verdragtekst><kop><nr status="officieel">I</nr></kop><vrije-tekst><tekst status="goed"><al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al></tekst></vrije-tekst></verdragtekst><verdragtekst><kop><nr status="officieel">II</nr></kop><vrije-tekst><tekst status="goed"><al><redactie type="vervanging">De tekst van de vertaling is niet beschikbaar.</redactie></al></tekst></vrije-tekst></verdragtekst><verdragtekst><kop><label>Bijlage</label><nr status="officieel">III</nr></kop><wettekst><titeldeel><kop><label>DEEL</label><nr>I</nr></kop><structuurtekst><al><redactie type="vervanging">Niet opgenomen.</redactie></al></structuurtekst></titeldeel><titeldeel><kop><label>DEEL</label><nr>II</nr></kop><structuurtekst><al><redactie type="vervanging">Niet opgenomen.</redactie></al></structuurtekst></titeldeel><titeldeel><kop><label>DEEL</label><nr>III</nr><titel>HEFFINGEN AAN GEBRUIKERS</titel></kop><artikel status="goed"><kop><nr>1</nr></kop><al>Ingevolge artikel XIV van deze Overeenkomst stelt de Raad op of v&#xF3;&#xF3;r 20 november 1982 voor het kalenderjaar 1983 voor de gezamenlijk gefinancierde diensten &#xE9;&#xE9;n enkele heffing aan de gebruiker vast per burgerluchtvaartuig dat een vlucht maakt. De heffing wordt berekend door vijfennegentig procent van de goedgekeurde geraamde kosten, uitgedrukt in Amerikaanse dollars, te bestemmen voor de burgerluchtvaart voor 1983 (zoals omschreven in paragraaf 6 hieronder), plus een correctie voor te weinig ontvangen terugbetaling of minus een correctie voor te veel ontvangen terugbetaling in 1981 (berekend overeenkomstig de paragrafen 3, 4 en 5 hieronder) te delen door het totaal aantal vluchten in 1981, afgerond tot de naaste hele Amerikaanse dollar.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><nr>2</nr></kop><al>De bepalingen in paragraaf 1 hierboven, met passende herziening van de daarin genoemde jaren, gelden voor de berekening van de heffing aan de gebruiker per vlucht van een burgerluchtvaartuig voor het kalenderjaar 1984 en de jaren daarna.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><nr>3</nr></kop><al>De in paragraaf 1 hierboven bedoelde te veel of te weinig ontvangen terugbetaling is het verschil tussen het in een jaar te innen bedrag (paragraaf 4 hieronder) en de totale bedragen die gebruikers in dat jaar in rekening worden gebracht (paragraaf 5 hieronder).</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><nr>4</nr></kop><al>Het in 1981 te innen bedrag (voor de berekening van de heffing aan de gebruiker in 1983) is tachtig procent van vijfennegentig procent van de goedgekeurde kosten te bestemmen voorde burgerluchtvaart in 1981, vermeerderd met de te weinig ontvangen terugbetaling in 1979. In 1982 is het vijfennegentig procent van de goedgekeurde kosten te bestemmen voor de burgerluchtvaart in 1982, vermeerderd met de te weinig ontvangen terugbetaling in 1980. Voor 1983 en de jaren daarna is het te innen bedrag vijfennegentig procent van de goedgekeurde kosten te bestemmen voor de burgerluchtvaart in dat jaar, verminderd met de te veel ontvangen terugbetaling of vermeerderd met de te weinig ontvangen terugbetaling twee jaar tevoren.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><nr>5</nr></kop><al>Bij de berekening van de heffing aan de gebruiker voor 1983 worden de aan gebruikers voor 1981 in rekening gebrachte bedragen (vereist om de te veel of te weinig ontvangen terugbetaling voor 1981 vast te stellen) berekend door dat deel van de heffing aan de gebruiker voor 1981 in ponden sterling dat onder deze Overeenkomst valt te vermenigvuldigen met het aantal vluchten in 1981, dit dan om te rekenen in Amerikaanse dollars volgens de voor 1981 overeengekomen wisselkoersen. In volgende jaren worden de aan de gebruikers in rekening gebrachte bedragen op dezelfde wijze berekend met passende wijzigingen wat het jaar betreft.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><nr>6</nr></kop><al>Ten behoeve van de berekening van de heffingen aan gebruikers, zijn de onderstaande percentages van de gezamenlijk gefinancierde kosten (d.w.z. vijfennegentig procent van de totale kosten) die kunnen worden bestemd voor de internationale burgerluchtvaart:</al><lijst><li><li.nr>a)</li.nr><al>100% van de luchtverkeersdiensten;</al></li><li><li.nr>b)</li.nr><al>30 procent van de Meteorologische Diensten (synoptische waarnemingen op de grond en in de hogere luchtlagen) en daarmede samenhangende meteorologische telecommunicatiediensten;</al></li><li><li.nr>c)</li.nr><al>100% van de taak ten behoeve van de internationale luchtvaart van het Meteorologisch Instituut te Reykjavik;</al></li><li><li.nr>d)</li.nr><al>100 procent van de luchtvaartkundige communicatie en de telegraafdiensten (met uitzondering van MET/COM).</al></li></lijst></artikel></titeldeel><titeldeel><kop><label>DEEL</label><nr>IV</nr><titel>VERSLAGEN INZAKE DE WERKELIJK GEMAAKTE KOSTEN</titel></kop><structuurtekst><al>De opgave van de werkelijk gemaakte kosten van de Diensten bedoeld in het tweede lid van artikel VIII van deze Overeenkomst geschiedt in Amerikaanse dollars. Hiertoe worden de feitelijke uitgaven in IJslandse kronen in elke kalendermaand omgerekend in Amerikaanse dollars met gebruikmaking van de middenkoers op de valutamarkt zoals opgegeven door de Centrale Bank van IJsland voor de eerste dag van die maand. Deze omrekeningen worden opgenomen in het rapport van de verificatie, bedoeld in het tweede lid van artikel VIII.</al></structuurtekst></titeldeel></wettekst></verdragtekst></verdrag>
</wetgeving>
  	