<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE wetgeving SYSTEM "http://wetten.overheid.nl/dtd/bwb-plus-meta-1_61w.dtd">
<wetgeving bwb-id="BWBV0003903" dtdversie="2.0" id="10000033779" verdragnummer="002412" soort="verdrag">
  
  <alias-titels><alias-titel>Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of Crimes against Internationally protected Persons, including Diplomatic Agents</alias-titel></alias-titels>
  <intitule>Verdrag inzake de voorkoming en bestraffing van misdrijven tegen internationaal beschermde personen, met inbegrip van diplomaten</intitule>
  
  <verdrag tekst="authentiek" xml:lang="en"><verdragtekst>
<kop>
<titel status="officieel">Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of Crimes against Internationally protected Persons, including Diplomatic Agents</titel>
</kop><aanhef><preambule><al>The States Parties to this Convention,</al><al>Having in mind the purposes and principles of the <extref status="actief" doc="1.0:v:BWBV0004143" compleet="nee">Charter of the United Nations</extref> concerning the maintenance of international peace and the promotion of friendly relations and co-operation among States,</al><al>Considering that crimes against diplomatic agents and other internationally protected persons jeopardizing the safety of these persons create a serious threat to the maintenance of normal international relations which are necessary for co-operation among States,</al><al>Believing that the commission of such crimes is a matter of grave concern to the international community,</al><al>Convinced that there is an urgent need to adopt appropriate and effective measures for the prevention and punishment of such crimes,</al></preambule><afkondiging><al>Have agreed as follows:</al></afkondiging></aanhef><wettekst><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">1</nr>
</kop><al>For the purposes of this Convention:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>1.</li.nr><al>&#x201C;internationally protected person&#x201D; means:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>a Head of State, including any member of a collegial body performing the functions of a Head of State under the constitution of the State concerned, a Head of Government or a Minister for Foreign Affairs, whenever any such person is in a foreign State, as well as members of his family who accompany him;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>any representative or official of a State or any official or other agent of an international organization of an intergovernmental character who, at the time when and in the place where a crime against him, his official premises, his private accommodation or his means of transport is committed, is entitled pursuant to international law to special protection from any attack on his person, freedom or dignity, as well as members of his family forming part of his household;</al></li></lijst></li><li><li.nr>2.</li.nr><al>&#x201C;alleged offender&#x201D; means a person as to whom there is sufficient evidence to determine prima facie that he has committed or participated in one or more of the crimes set forth in article 2.</al></li></lijst></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">2</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>The intentional commission of:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>a murder, kidnapping or other attack upon the person or liberty of an internationally protected person;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>a violent attack upon the official premises, the private accommodation or the means of transport of an internationally protected person likely to endanger his person or liberty;</al></li><li><li.nr>(c)</li.nr><al>a threat to commit any such attack;</al></li><li><li.nr>(d)</li.nr><al>an attempt to commit any such attack; and</al></li><li><li.nr>(e)</li.nr><al>an act constituting participation as an accomplice in any such attack</al></li></lijst><al>shall be made by each State Party a crime under its internal law.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Each State Party shall make these crimes punishable by appropriate penalties which take into account their grave nature.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>Paragraphs 1 and 2 of this article in no way derogate from the obligations of States Parties under international law to take all appropriate measures to prevent other attacks on the person, freedom or dignity of an internationally protected person.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">3</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Each State Party shall take such measures as may be necessary to establish its jurisdiction over the crimes, set forth in article 2 in the following cases:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>when the crime is committed in the territory of that State or on board a ship or aircraft registered in that State;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>when the alleged offender is a national of that State;</al></li><li><li.nr>(c)</li.nr><al>when the crime is committed against an internationally protected person as defined in article 1 who enjoys his status as such by virtue of functions which he exercises on behalf of that State.</al></li></lijst></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Each State Party shall likewise take such measures as may be necessary to establish its jurisdiction over these crimes in cases where the alleged offender is present in its territory and it does not extradite him pursuant to article 8 to any of the States mentioned in paragraph 1 of this article.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>This Convention does not exclude any criminal jurisdiction exercised in accordance with internal law.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">4</nr>
</kop><al>States Parties shall co-operate in the prevention of the crimes set forth in article 2, particularly by:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>taking all practicable measures to prevent preparations in their respective territories for the commission of those crimes within or outside their territories;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>exchanging information and co-ordinating the taking of administrative and other measures as appropriate to prevent the commission of those crimes.</al></li></lijst></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">5</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>The State Party in which any of the crimes set forth in article 2 has been committed shall, if it has reason to believe that an alleged offender has fled from its territory, communicate to all other States concerned, directly or through the Secretary-General of the United Nations, all the pertinent facts regarding the crime committed and all available information regarding the identity of the alleged offender.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Whenever any of the crimes set forth in article 2 has been committed against an internationally protected person, any State Party which has information concerning the victim and the circumstances of the crime shall endeavour to transmit it, under the conditions provided for in its internal law, fully and promptly to the State Party on whose behalf he was exercising his functions.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">6</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Upon being satisfied that the circumstances so warrant, the State Party in whose territory the alleged offender is present shall take the appropriate measures under its internal law so as to ensure his presence for the purpose of prosecution or extradition. Such measures shall be notified without delay directly or through the Secretary-General of the United Nations to:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>the State where the crime was committed;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>the State or States of which the alleged offender is a national or, if he is a stateless person, in whose territory he permanently resides;</al></li><li><li.nr>(c)</li.nr><al>the State or States of which the internationally protected person concerned is a national or on whose behalf he was exercising his functions;</al></li><li><li.nr>(d)</li.nr><al>all other States concerned; and</al></li><li><li.nr>(e)</li.nr><al>the international organization of which the internationally protected person concerned is an official or an agent.</al></li></lijst></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Any person regarding whom the measures referred to in paragraph 1 of this article are being taken shall be entitled:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>to communicate without delay with the nearest appropriate representative of the State of which he is a national or which is otherwise entitled to protect his rights or, if he is a stateless person, which he requests and which is willing to protect his rights; and</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>to be visited by a representative of that State.</al></li></lijst></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">7</nr>
</kop><al>The State Party in whose territory the alleged offender is present shall, if it does not extradite him, submit, without exception whatsoever and without undue delay, the case to its competent authorities for the purpose of prosecution, through proceedings in accordance with the laws of that State.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">8</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>To the extent that the crimes set forth in article 2 are not listed as extraditable offences in any extradition treaty existing between States Parties, they shall be deemed to the included as such therein. States Parties undertake to include those crimes as extraditable offences in every future extradition treaty to be concluded between them.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>If a State Party which makes extradition conditional on the existence of a treaty receives a request for extradition from another State Party with which it has no extradition treaty, it may, if it decides to extradite, consider this Convention as the legal basis for extradition in respect of those crimes. Extradition shall be subject to the procedural provisions and the other conditions of the law of the requested State.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>States Parties which do not make extradition conditional on the existence of a treaty shall recognize those crimes as extraditable offences between themselves subject to the procedural provisions and the other conditions of the law of the requested State.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr><al>Each of the crimes shall be treated, for the purpose of extradition between States Parties, as if it has been committed not only in the place in which it occurred but also in the territories of the States required to establish their jurisdiction in accordance with paragraph 1 of article 3.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">9</nr>
</kop><al>Any person regarding whom proceedings are being carried out in connexion with any of the crimes set forth in article 2 shall be guaranteed fair treatment at all stages of the proceedings.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">10</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>States Parties shall afford one another the greatest measure of assistance in connexion with criminal proceedings brought in respect of the crimes set forth in article 2, including the supply of all evidence at their disposal necessary for the proceedings.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>The provisions of paragraph 1 of this article shall not affect obligations concerning mutual judicial assistance embodied in any other treaty.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">11</nr>
</kop><al>The State Party where an alleged offender is prosecuted shall communicate the final outcome of the proceedings to the Secretary-General of the United Nations, who shall transmit the information to the other States Parties.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">12</nr>
</kop><al>The provisions of this Convention shall not affect the application of the Treaties on Asylum, in force at the date of the adoption of this Convention, as between the States which are parties to those Treaties; but a State Party to this Convention may not invoke those Treaties with respect to another State Party to this Convention which is not a party to those Treaties.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">13</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Any dispute between two or more States Parties concerning the interpretation or application of this Convention which is not settled by negotiation shall, at the request of one of them, be submitted to arbitration. If within six months from the date of the request for arbitration the parties are unable to agree on the organization of the arbitration, any one of those parties may refer the dispute to the International Court of Justice by request in conformity with the <extref status="actief" doc="1.0:v:BWBV0005509" compleet="nee">Statute of the Court</extref>.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Each State Party may at the time of signature or ratification of this Convention or accession thereto declare that it does not consider itself bound by paragraph 1 of this article. The other States Parties shall not be bound by paragraph 1 of this article with respect to any State Party which has made such a reservation.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>Any State Party which has made a reservation in accordance with paragraph 2 of this article may at any time withdraw that reservation by notification to the Secretary-General of the United Nations.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">14</nr>
</kop><al>This Convention shall be open for signature by all States, until 31 December 1974 at United Nations Headquarters in New York.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">15</nr>
</kop><al>This Convention is subject to ratification. The instruments of ratification shall be deposited with the Secretary-General of the United Nations.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">16</nr>
</kop><al>This Convention shall remain open for accession by any State. The instruments of accession shall be deposited with the Secretary-General of the United Nations.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">17</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>This Convention shall enter into force on the thirtieth day following the date of deposit of the twenty-second instrument of ratification or accession with the Secretary-General of the United Nations.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>For each State ratifying or acceding to the Convention after the deposit of the twenty-second instrument of ratification or accession, the Convention shall enter into force on the thirtieth day after deposit by such State of its instrument of ratification or accession.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">18</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Any State Party may denounce this Convention by written notification to the Secretary-General of the United Nations.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Denunciation shall take effect six months following the date on which notification is received by the Secretary-General of the United Nations.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">19</nr>
</kop><al>The Secretary-General of the United Nations shall inform all States, inter alia:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>of signatures to this Convention, of the deposit of instruments of ratification or accession in accordance with articles 14, 15 and 16 and of notifications made under article 18.</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>of the date on which this Convention will enter into force in accordance with article 17.</al></li></lijst></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">20</nr>
</kop><al>The original of this Convention, of which the Chinese, English, French, Russian and Spanish texts are equally authentic, shall be deposited with the Secretary-General of the United Nations, who shall send certified copies thereof to all States.</al></artikel></wettekst><wetsluiting status="goed"><slotformulering><al>IN WITNESS WHEREOF the undersigned, being duly authorized thereto by their respective Governments, have signed this Convention, opened for signature at New York on 14 December 1973.</al></slotformulering></wetsluiting></verdragtekst><verdragtekst><kop><label/></kop><aanhef><preambule><al>The General Assembly,</al><al>Considering that the codification and progressive development of international law contributes to the implementation of the purposes and principles set forth in <extref status="actief" doc="1.0:v:BWBV0004143&amp;artikel=1" compleet="nee">Articles 1</extref> and <extref status="actief" doc="1.0:v:BWBV0004143&amp;artikel=2" compleet="nee">2 of the Charter of the United Nations</extref>,</al><al>Recalling that in response to the request made in General Assembly resolution 2780 (XXVI) of 3 December 1971, the International Law Commission, at its twenty fourth session, studied the question of the protection and inviolability of diplomatic agents and other persons entitled to special protection under international law and prepared draft, articles on the prevention and punishment of crimes against such persons,</al><al>Having considered the draft articles and also the comments and observations thereon submitted by States, specialized agencies and other intergovernmental organizations in response to the invitation extended by the General Assembly in its resolution 2926 (XXVII) of 28 November 1972,</al><al>Convinced of the importance of securing international agreement on appropriate and effective measures for the prevention and punishment of crimes against diplomatic agents and other internationally protected persons in view of the serious threat to the maintenance and promotion of friendly relations and co-operation among States created by the commission of such crimes,</al><al>Having elaborated for that purpose the provisions contained in the Convention annexed hereto,</al></preambule></aanhef><vrije-tekst><tekst status="goed"><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>1.</li.nr><al>Adopts the Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of Crimes against Internationally Protected Persons, including Diplomatic Agents, annexed to the present resolution;</al></li><li><li.nr>2.</li.nr><al>Re-emphasizes the great importance of the rules of international law concerning the inviolability of and special protection to be afforded to internationally protected persons and the obligations of States in relation thereto;</al></li><li><li.nr>3.</li.nr><al>Considers that the annexed Convention will enable States to carry out their obligations more effectively;</al></li><li><li.nr>4.</li.nr><al>Recognizes also that the provisions of the annexed Convention could not in any way prejudice the exercise of the legitimate right to self-determination and independence, in accordance with the purposes and principles of the <extref status="actief" doc="1.0:v:BWBV0004143" compleet="nee">Charter of the United Nations</extref> and the Declaration on Principles of International Law concerning Friendly Relations and Co-operation among States in accordance with the Charter of the United Nations, by peoples struggling against colonialism, alien domination, foreign occupation, racial discrimination and apartheid;</al></li><li><li.nr>5.</li.nr><al>Invites States to become parties to the annexed Convention;</al></li><li><li.nr>6.</li.nr><al>Decides that the present resolution, whose provisions are related to the annexed Convention, shall always be published together with it.</al></li></lijst></tekst></vrije-tekst></verdragtekst></verdrag>
<verdrag tekst="vertaling" xml:lang="nl"><verdragtekst>
<kop>
<titel status="officieel">Verdrag inzake de voorkoming en bestraffing van misdrijven tegen internationaal beschermde personen, met inbegrip van diplomaten</titel>
</kop><aanhef><preambule><al>De Staten die partij zijn bij dit Verdrag,</al><al>Indachtig de doelstellingen en beginselen, vervat in het <extref status="actief" doc="1.0:v:BWBV0004143" compleet="nee">Handvest van de Verenigde Naties</extref>, betreffende de handhaving van de internationale vrede en de bevordering van vriendschappelijke betrekkingen en samenwerking tussen Staten,</al><al>Overwegende dat misdrijven tegen diplomaten en andere internationaal beschermde personen, waardoor de veiligheid van deze personen in gevaar wordt gebracht, een ernstige bedreiging vormen van handhaving van normale internationale betrekkingen die noodzakelijk zijn voor de samenwerking tussen Staten,</al><al>Van oordeel zijnde dat het plegen van zulke misdrijven een zaak van ernstige zorg is voor de internationale gemeenschap,</al><al>Ervan overtuigd dat het dringend noodzakelijk is passende en doeltreffende maatregelen inzake de voorkoming en bestraffing van zulke misdrijven te nemen,</al></preambule><afkondiging><al>Zijn als volgt overeengekomen:</al></afkondiging></aanhef><wettekst><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">1</nr>
</kop><al>Voor de toepassing van dit Verdrag:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>1.</li.nr><al>Wordt onder &#x201E;een internationaal beschermd persoon&#x201D; verstaan:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>een staatshoofd, met inbegrip van enig lid van een college dat de functies van een staatshoofd vervult krachtens de constitutie van de betrokken Staat, een hoofd van een regering of een minister van buitenlandse zaken, in alle gevallen waarin een zodanige persoon zich in een vreemde Staat bevindt, alsmede de hem vergezellende gezinsleden;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>een vertegenwoordiger of een functionaris van een Staat of een functionaris of een andere vertegenwoordiger van een internationale intergouvernementele organisatie, die, op het tijdstip waarop en ter plaatse waar een misdrijf tegen hemzelf, de door hem gebruikte offici&#xEB;le gebouwen, zijn particuliere woning of zijn vervoermiddel wordt gepleegd, ingevolge het internationale recht aanspraak kan maken op bijzondere bescherming tegen een aanslag op zijn persoon, vrijheid of waardigheid, alsmede de inwonende gezinsleden;</al></li></lijst></li><li><li.nr>2.</li.nr><al>wordt onder &#x201E;vermoedelijke dader&#x201D; verstaan een persoon tegen wie voldoende bewijs aanwezig is om prima facie vast te stellen dat hij een of meer van de in artikel 2 vermelde misdrijven heeft gepleegd of daaraan heeft deelgenomen.</al></li></lijst></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">2</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Het opzettelijk plegen van:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>een moord, een ontvoering van, of een andere aanslag op de persoon of de vrijheid van een internationaal beschermd persoon;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>een gewelddadige aanslag op de offici&#xEB;le gebouwen, de particuliere woning of het vervoermiddel van een internationaal beschermd persoon, zodanig dat daardoor zijn persoon of vrijheid in gevaar wordt gebracht;</al></li><li><li.nr>(c)</li.nr><al>een dreiging een zodanige aanslag te plegen;</al></li><li><li.nr>(d)</li.nr><al>een poging een zodanige aanslag te plegen;</al></li><li><li.nr>(e)</li.nr><al>een handeling die medeplichtigheid aan een zodanige aanslag oplevert</al></li></lijst><al>wordt door elke Staat die partij is bij dit Verdrag, in zijn interne wetten strafbaar gesteld.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Elke Staat die partij is bij dit Verdrag, stelt deze misdrijven strafbaar met passende straffen, rekening houdend met het ernstige karakter van die misdrijven.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>Het eerste en het tweede lid van dit artikel doen in geen enkel opzicht afbreuk aan de krachtens het volkenrecht op de Staten die partij zijn bij dit Verdrag rustende verplichtingen om alle passende maatregelen te nemen ter voorkoming van andere aanslagen op de persoon, de vrijheid of de waardigheid van een internationaal beschermd persoon.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">3</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Elke Staat die partij is bij dit Verdrag, neemt de maatregelen die nodig zijn om zijn bevoegdheid tot kennisneming van de in artikel 2 vermelde misdrijven vast te leggen in de volgende gevallen:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>wanneer het misdrijf is gepleegd op het grondgebied van deze  Staat of aan boord van een in deze Staat ingeschreven vaartuig of luchtvaartuig;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>wanneer de vermoedelijke dader onderdaan van deze Staat is;</al></li><li><li.nr>(c)</li.nr><al>wanneer het misdrijf is gepleegd tegen een onder de begripsomschrijving van artikel 1 vallende internationaal beschermde persoon, indien deze zijn status als zodanig ontleent aan de functies die hij namens deze Staat uitoefent.</al></li></lijst></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Elke Staat die partij is bij dit Verdrag, neemt voorts de maatregelen die nodig zijn om zijn bevoegdheid tot kennisneming van deze misdrijven vast te leggen in gevallen waarin de vermoedelijke dader zich op zijn grondgebied bevindt en deze Staat hem niet uitlevert ingevolge het bepaalde in artikel 8 aan een van de in het eerste lid van dit artikel bedoelde Staten.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>Dit Verdrag sluit geen enkele bevoegdheid in strafzaken uit, die wordt uitgeoefend krachtens de nationale wet.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">4</nr>
</kop><al>De Staten die partij zijn bij dit Verdrag, werken samen ter voorkoming van de in artikel 2 vermelde misdrijven, in het bijzonder door:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>alle praktisch uitvoerbare maatregelen te nemen om te voorkomen dat op hun onderscheiden grondgebieden voorbereidingen worden getroffen voor het plegen van deze misdrijven binnen of buiten hun grondgebied;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>inlichtingen uit te wisselen en administratieve en andere maatregelen, al naar gelang het geval, ter voorkoming van het plegen van deze misdrijven te co&#xF6;rdineren.</al></li></lijst></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">5</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>De Staat die partij is bij dit Verdrag, en op het grondgebied waarvan een van de in artikel 2 vermelde misdrijven is gepleegd, stelt, indien die Staat op goede gronden kan aannemen dat een vermoedelijke dader van zijn grondgebied is gevlucht, alle andere betrokken Staten, rechtstreeks of via de Secretaris-Generaal van de Verenigde Naties, in kennis van alle terzake doende op het gepleegde misdrijf betrekking hebbende feiten en van alle beschikbare gegevens omtrent de identiteit van de vermoedelijke dader.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>In alle gevallen waarin een van de in artikel 2 vermelde misdrijven is gepleegd tegen een internationaal beschermd persoon, doet iedere Staat die partij is bij dit Verdrag en die over gegevens beschikt omtrent het slachtoffer en de omstandigheden waaronder het misdrijf heeft plaatsgevonden, al het mogelijke om deze informatie overeenkomstig de voorwaarden waarin zijn interne recht voorziet, volledig en onverwijld door te geven aan de Staat die partij is bij dit Verdrag en namens welke de betrokkene zijn functies uitoefende.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">6</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Indien de Staat die partij is bij dit Verdrag, en op het grondgebied waarvan de vermoedelijke dader zich bevindt, ervan overtuigd is dat de omstandigheden zulks wettigen, neemt deze Staat passende maatregelen overeenkomstig zijn interne recht om diens aanwezigheid ten behoeve van vervolging of uitlevering te verzekeren. Van deze maatregelen wordt onverwijld, rechtstreeks of via de Secretaris-Generaal van de Verenigde Naties, kennis gegeven aan:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>de Staat waar het misdrijf werd gepleegd;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>de Staat of de Staten waarvan de vermoedelijke dader onderdaan is of, indien hij staatloos is, op het grondgebied waarvan hij zijn vaste verblijfplaats heeft;</al></li><li><li.nr>(c)</li.nr><al>de Staat of de Staten waarvan de betrokken persoon onder internationale bescherming onderdaan is of namens welke hij zijn functies uitoefende;</al></li><li><li.nr>(d)</li.nr><al>alle andere betrokken Staten; en</al></li><li><li.nr>(e)</li.nr><al>internationale organisatie waarvan de betrokken persoon onder internationale bescherming een functionaris of een vertegenwoorr is.</al></li></lijst></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Elke persoon ten aanzien van wie de in het eerste lid van dit artikel bedoelde maatregelen worden genomen, heeft het recht:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>onverwijld in contact te treden met de dichtstbijzijnde bevoegde vertegenwoordiger van de Staat waarvan hij onderdaan is of die anderszins is gerechtigd zijn rechten te beschermen of, indien hij staatloos is, waaraan hij verzoekt en die bereid is zijn rechten te beschermen; en</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>bezoek van een vertegenwoordiger van die Staat te ontvangen.</al></li></lijst></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">7</nr>
</kop><al>De Staat die partij is bij dit Verdrag, en op het grondgebied waarvan de vermoedelijke dader zich bevindt, draagt, indien deze Staat hem niet uitlevert, zonder enige uitzondering en zonder onnodig uitstel, de zaak voor vervolging over aan zijn bevoegde autoriteiten volgens de in zijn wetten voorziene procedures.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">8</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Voor zover de in artikel 2 vermelde misdrijven niet zijn vermeld als uitleveringsdelicten in een uitleveringsverdrag, bestaande tussen Staten die partij zijn bij dit Verdrag, worden zij geacht als zodanig daarin te zijn begrepen. De Staten die partij zijn bij dit Verdrag, verplichten zich ertoe deze misdrijven op te nemen als uitleveringsdelicten in elk uitleveringsverdrag dat in de toekomst tussen hen wordt gesloten.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Indien een Staat die partij is bij dit Verdrag en die uitlevering afhankelijk stelt van het bestaan van een verdrag, een verzoek om uitlevering ontvangt van een andere Staat die partij is bij dit Verdrag, maar waarmee hij geen uitleveringsverdrag heeft gesloten, kan deze Staat, indien hij tot uitlevering besluit, dit Verdrag beschouwen als de wettelijke basis voor uitlevering wegens deze misdrijven. De uitlevering is onderworpen aan de procedurele bepalingen en de overige voorwaarden waarin het recht van de aangezochte Staat voorziet.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>De Staten die partij zijn bij dit Verdrag en die uitlevering niet afhankelijk stellen van het bestaan van een verdrag, erkennen onderling deze misdrijven als uitleveringsdelicten, onderworpen aan de procedurele bepalingen en de overige voorwaarden waarin het recht van de aangezochte Staat voorziet.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr><al>Elk van de misdrijven wordt, ten behoeve van uitlevering tussen de Staten die partij zijn bij dit Verdrag beschouwd als begaan niet alleen op de plaats waar het is gepleegd, maar ook op het grondgebied van de Staten die hun bevoegdheid dienen vast te leggen overeenkomstig het eerste lid van artikel 3.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">9</nr>
</kop><al>Een ieder tegen wie een strafvervolging wordt gevoerd in verband met een van de in artikel 2 vermelde misdrijven, wordt een rechtvaardige behandeling gewaarborgd gedurende elk stadium van deze procedure.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">10</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>De Staten die partij zijn bij dit Verdrag, verlenen elkaar de ruimst mogelijke rechtshulp in strafzaken wegens de in artikel 2 omschreven misdrijven, met inbegrip van het verstrekken van het hun ter beschikking staande bewijsmateriaal dat nodig is in verband met de vervolging.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Het bepaalde in het eerste lid van dit artikel laat verplichtingen betreffende wederzijdse rechtshulp, vervat in enig ander verdrag, onverlet.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">11</nr>
</kop><al>De Staat die partij is bij dit Verdrag, en waar een vermoedelijke dader strafrechtelijk wordt vervolgd, brengt het eindresultaat van de strafzaak ter kennis van de Secretaris-Generaal van de Verenigde Naties, die de gegevens doorzendt aan de andere Staten die partij zijn bij dit Verdrag.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">12</nr>
</kop><al>Het bepaalde in dit Verdrag laat de toepassing van de Verdragen inzake asiel, die van kracht zijn op de datum waarop dit Verdrag is aangenomen, onverlet tussen de Staten die Partij zijn bij die Verdragen; een Staat die Partij is bij dit Verdrag, kan zich echter niet beroepen op die Verdragen ten aanzien van een andere Staat die Partij is bij dit Verdrag, maar niet bij die Verdragen.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">13</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Elk geschil tussen twee of meer Staten die partij zijn bij dit Verdrag, inzake de uitleg of de toepassing van dit Verdrag, dat niet wordt beslecht door onderhandelingen, wordt op verzoek van een van deze Staten onderworpen aan arbitrage. Indien de partijen er binnen zes maanden na de datum van het verzoek om arbitrage niet in zijn geslaagd overeenstemming te bereiken over de vorm van deze arbitrage kan ieder van deze Partijen het geschil voorleggen aan het Internationale Gerechtshof door middel van een verzoek overeenkomstig het <extref status="actief" doc="1.0:v:BWBV0005509" compleet="nee">Statuut van het Hof</extref>.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Elke Staat die partij is bij dit Verdrag, kan op het tijdstip van ondertekening of bekrachtiging van dit Verdrag, of van toetreding daartoe, verklaren zich niet gebonden te achten door het eerste lid van dit artikel. De andere Staten die partij zijn bij dit Verdrag, zijn niet gebonden door het eerste lid van dit artikel tegenover een Staat die partij is bij dit Verdrag en die een zodanig voorbehoud heeft gemaakt.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>Een Staat die partij is bij dit Verdrag, en die een voorbehoud heeft gemaakt overeenkomstig het tweede lid van dit artikel, kan dit voorbehoud te allen tijde intrekken door middel van een kennisgeving aan de Secretaris-Generaal van de Verenigde Naties.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">14</nr>
</kop><al>Dit Verdrag staat tot 31 december 1974 open voor ondertekening door alle Staten op de Zetel van de Verenigde Naties te New York.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">15</nr>
</kop><al>Dit Verdrag dient te worden bekrachtigd. De akten van bekrachtiging dienen te worden nedergelegd bij de Secretaris-Generaal van de Verenigde Naties.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">16</nr>
</kop><al>Dit Verdrag staat open voor toetreding door elke Staat. De akten van toetreding dienen te worden nedergelegd bij de Secretaris-Generaal van de Verenigde Naties.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">17</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Dit Verdrag treedt in werking op de dertigste dag na de datum van nederlegging van de twee&#xEB;ntwintigste akte van bekrachtiging of toetreding bij de Secretaris-Generaal van de Verenigde Naties.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Voor elke Staat die dit Verdrag bekrachtigt of daartoe toetreedt na de nederlegging van de twee&#xEB;ntwintigste akte van bekrachtiging of toetreding, treedt het Verdrag in werking op de dertigste dag na de nederlegging van zijn akte van bekrachtiging of toetreding.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">18</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Elke Staat die partij is bij dit Verdrag, kan dit Verdrag opzeggen door middel van een schriftelijke kennisgeving aan de Secretaris-Generaal van de Verenigde Naties.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>De opzegging wordt van kracht zes maanden na de datum waarop de kennisgeving door de Secretaris-Generaal van de Verenigde Naties is ontvangen.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">19</nr>
</kop><al>De Secretaris-Generaal van de Verenigde Naties geeft alle staten kennis van, onder andere:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>de ondertekeningen van dit Verdrag, de nederlegging van de akten van bekrachtiging of toetreding overeenkomstig de artikelen 14, 15 en 16, alsmede de krachtens artikel 18 gedane kennisgevingen;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>de datum waarop dit Verdrag overeenkomstig artikel 17 in werking treedt.</al></li></lijst></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">20</nr>
</kop><al>Het origineel van dit Verdrag, waarvan de Chinese, de Engelse, de Franse, de Russische en de Spaanse tekst gelijkelijk authentiek zijn, wordt nedergelegd bij de Secretaris-Generaal van de Verenigde Naties, die daarvan een voor eensluidend gewaarmerkt afschrift toezendt aan alle Staten.</al></artikel></wettekst><wetsluiting status="goed"><slotformulering><al>TEN BLIJKE WAARVAN de ondergetekenden, hiertoe naar behoren gemachtigd door hun onderscheiden Regeringen, dit Verdrag, dat op 14 december 1973 te New York voor ondertekening is opengesteld, hebben ondertekend.</al></slotformulering></wetsluiting></verdragtekst></verdrag></wetgeving>
  	