<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE wetgeving SYSTEM "http://wetten.overheid.nl/dtd/bwb-plus-meta-1_61w.dtd">
<wetgeving bwb-id="BWBV0003924" dtdversie="2.0" id="10000033989" verdragnummer="000982" soort="verdrag"> 
   
  <alias-titels><alias-titel>Protocol to the Agreement on the Importation of Educational, Scientific and Cultural Materials</alias-titel></alias-titels> 
  <intitule>Protocol bij de Overeenkomst inzake de invoer van voorwerpen van
	 opvoedkundige, wetenschappelijke of culturele aard</intitule> 
   
  <verdrag tekst="authentiek" xml:lang="en">
	 <verdragtekst>
		<kop>
		  <titel status="officieel"> Protocol to the Agreement on the Importation of Educational,
			 Scientific and Cultural Materials</titel>
		</kop>
		<aanhef>
		  <preambule>
			 <al>The contracting States parties to the Agreement on the
				Importation of Educational, Scientific and Cultural Materials, adopted by the
				General Conference of the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
				Organization at its fifth session held in Florence in 1950,</al>
			 <al>Reaffirming the principles on which the Agreement,
				hereinaftercalled &#x201C;the Agreement&#x201D;, is based,</al>
			 <al>Considering that this Agreement has proved to be an effective
				instrument in lowering customs barriers and reducing other economic
				restrictions that impede the exchange of ideas and knowledge,</al>
			 <al>Considering, nevertheless, that in the quarter of a century
				following the adoption of the Agreement, technical progress has changed the
				ways and means of transmitting information and knowledge, which is the
				fundamental objective of that Agreement,</al>
			 <al>Considering, further, that the developments that have taken place
				in the field of international trade during this period have, in general, been
				reflected in greater freedom of exchanges,</al>
			 <al>Considering that since the adoption of the Agreement, the
				international situation has changed radically owing to the development of the
				international community, in particular through the accession of many States to
				independence,</al>
			 <al>Considering that the needs and concerns of the developing
				countries should be taken into consideration, with a view to giving them easier
				and less costly access to education, science, technology and culture,</al>
			 <al>Recalling the provisions of the Convention on the means of
				prohibiting and preventing the illicit import, export and transfer of ownership
				of cultural property, adopted by the General Conference of UNESCO in 1970, and
				those of the Convention concerning the protection of the world cultural and
				natural heritage, adopted by the General Conference in 1972,</al>
			 <al>Recalling, moreover, the customs conventions concluded under
				theauspices of the Customs Co-operation Council, in consultation with the
				United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization, concerning
				the temporary importation of educational, scientific and cultural
				materials,</al>
			 <al>Convinced that new arrangements should be made and that such
				arrangements will contribute even more effectively to the development of
				education, science and culture which constitute the essential bases of economic
				and social progress,</al>
			 <al>Recalling resolution 4.112 adopted by the General Conference of
				UNESCO at its eighteenth session,</al>
		  </preambule>
		  <afkondiging>
			 <al>Have agreed as follows:</al>
		  </afkondiging>
		</aanhef>
		<vrije-tekst>
		  <divisie opmaak="default">
			 <kop><nr status="officieel">I</nr>
			 </kop>
			 <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
				<li><li.nr>1.</li.nr>
				  <al>The contracting States undertake to extend to the materials
					 listed in annexes A, B, D and E and also, where the annexes in question have
					 not been the subject of a declaration under paragraph 16 (a) below, annexes
					 C.1, F, G and H, to the present Protocol exemption from customs duties and
					 other charges on, or in connexion with, their importation, as set out in
					 article I, paragraph 1, of the Agreement, provided such materials fulfil the
					 conditions laid down in these annexes and are the products of another
					 contracting State.</al>
				</li>
				<li><li.nr>2.</li.nr>
				  <al>The provisions of paragraph 1 of this Protocol shall not
					 prevent any contracting State from levying on imported materials:</al>
				  <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
					 <li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr>
						<al>internal taxes or any other internal charges of any kind,
						  imposed at the time of importation or subsequently, not exceeding those applied
						  directly of indirectly to like domestic products;</al>
					 </li>
					 <li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr>
						<al>fees and charges, other than customs duties, imposed by
						  governmental or administrative authorities on, or in connexion with,
						  importation, limited in amount to the approximate cost of the services
						  rendered, and representing neither and indirect protection to domestic products
						  nor a taxation of imports for revenue purposes.</al>
					 </li>
				  </lijst>
				</li>
			 </lijst>
		  </divisie>
		  <divisie opmaak="default">
			 <kop><nr status="officieel">II</nr>
			 </kop>
			 <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
				<li><li.nr>3.</li.nr>
				  <al>Notwithstanding paragraph 2 (a) of this Protocol, the
					 contracting States undertake not to levy on the materials listed below any
					 internal taxes or other internal charges of any kind, imposed at the time of
					 importation or subsequently:</al>
				  <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
					 <li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr>
						<al>books and publications consigned to the libraries
						  referred to in paragraph 5 of this Protocol;</al>
					 </li>
					 <li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr>
						<al>official, parliamentary and administrative documents
						  published in their country of origin;</al>
					 </li>
					 <li><li.nr>(c)</li.nr>
						<al>books and publications of the United Nations or any of
						  its specialized agencies;</al>
					 </li>
					 <li><li.nr>(d)</li.nr>
						<al>books and publications received by the United Nations
						  Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization and distributed free of
						  charge by it or under its supervision;</al>
					 </li>
					 <li><li.nr>(e)</li.nr>
						<al>publications intended to promote tourist travel outside
						  the country of importation, sent and distributed free of charge;</al>
					 </li>
					 <li><li.nr>(f)</li.nr>
						<al>articles for the blind and other physically and mentally
						  handicapped persons:</al>
						<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
						  <li><li.nr>(i)</li.nr>
							 <al>books, publications and documents of all kinds in
								raised characters for the blind;</al>
						  </li>
						  <li><li.nr>(ii)</li.nr>
							 <al>other articles specially designed for the
								educational, scientificor cultural advancement of the blind and other
								physically or mentally handicapped persons which are imported directly by
								institutions or organizations concerned with the education of, or assistance to
								the blind and other physically or mentally handicapped persons approved by the
								competent authorities of the importing country for the purpose of duty-free
								entry of these types of articles.</al>
						  </li>
						</lijst>
					 </li>
				  </lijst>
				</li>
			 </lijst>
		  </divisie>
		  <divisie opmaak="default">
			 <kop><nr status="officieel">III</nr>
			 </kop>
			 <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
				<li><li.nr>4.</li.nr>
				  <al>The contracting States undertake not to levy on the articles
					 and materials referred to in the annexes to this Protocol any customs duties,
					 export duties or duties levied on goods leaving the country, or other internal
					 taxes of any kind, levied on such articles and materials when they are intended
					 for export to other contracting States.</al>
				</li>
			 </lijst>
		  </divisie>
		  <divisie opmaak="default">
			 <kop><nr status="officieel">IV</nr>
			 </kop>
			 <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
				<li><li.nr>5.</li.nr>
				  <al>The contracting States undertake to extend the granting of
					 the necessary licences and/or foreign exchange provided for in article II,
					 paragraph 1, of the Agreement, to the importation of the following
					 materials:</al>
				  <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
					 <li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr>
						<al>books and publications consigned to libraries serving the
						  public interest, including the following:</al>
						<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
						  <li><li.nr>(i)</li.nr>
							 <al>national libraries and other major research
								libraries;</al>
						  </li>
						  <li><li.nr>(ii)</li.nr>
							 <al>general and specialized academic libraries, including
								university libraries, college libraries, institute libraries and university
								extra-mural libraries;</al>
						  </li>
						  <li><li.nr>(iii)</li.nr>
							 <al>public libraries;</al>
						  </li>
						  <li><li.nr>(iv)</li.nr>
							 <al>school libraries;</al>
						  </li>
						  <li><li.nr>(v)</li.nr>
							 <al>special libraries serving a group of readers who form
								an entity, having particular and identifiable subjects of interest, such as
								government libraries, public authority libraries, industrial libraries and
								libraries of professional bodies;</al>
						  </li>
						  <li><li.nr>(vi)</li.nr>
							 <al>libraries for the handicapped and for readers who are
								unable to move around, such as libraries for the blind, hospital libraries and
								prison libraries;</al>
						  </li>
						  <li><li.nr>(vii)</li.nr>
							 <al>music libraries, including record libraries;</al>
						  </li>
						</lijst>
					 </li>
					 <li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr>
						<al>books adopted or recommended as textbooks in higher
						  educational establishments and imported by such establishments;</al>
					 </li>
					 <li><li.nr>(c)</li.nr>
						<al>books in foreign languages, with the exception of books
						  in the principal native language or languages of the importing country;</al>
					 </li>
					 <li><li.nr>(d)</li.nr>
						<al>films, slides, video-tapes and sound recordings of an
						  educationnal, scientific or cultural nature, imported by organizations approved
						  by the competent authorities of the importing country for the purpose of
						  duty-free entry of these types of articles.</al>
					 </li>
				  </lijst>
				</li>
			 </lijst>
		  </divisie>
		  <divisie opmaak="default">
			 <kop><nr status="officieel">V</nr>
			 </kop>
			 <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
				<li><li.nr>6.</li.nr>
				  <al>The contracting States undertake to extend the granting of
					 the facilities provided for in article III of the Agreement to materials and
					 furniture imported exclusively for showing at a public exhibition of objects of
					 an educational, scientific or cultural nature approved by the competent
					 authorities of the importing country and for subsequent re-exportation.</al>
				</li>
				<li><li.nr>7.</li.nr>
				  <al>Nothing in the foregoing paragraph shall prevent the
					 authorities of an importing country from taking such steps as may be necessary
					 to ensure that the materials and furniture in question will in fact be
					 re-exported at the close of the exhibition.</al>
				</li>
			 </lijst>
		  </divisie>
		  <divisie opmaak="default">
			 <kop><nr status="officieel">VI</nr>
			 </kop>
			 <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
				<li><li.nr>8.</li.nr>
				  <al>The contracting States undertake:</al>
				  <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
					 <li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr>
						<al>to extend to the importation of the articles covered by
						  the present Protocol the provisions of article IV of the Agreement;</al>
					 </li>
					 <li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr>
						<al>to encourage through appropriate measures the free flow
						  and distribution of educational, scientific and cultural objects and materials
						  produced in the developing countries.</al>
					 </li>
				  </lijst>
				</li>
			 </lijst>
		  </divisie>
		  <divisie opmaak="default">
			 <kop><nr status="officieel">VII</nr>
			 </kop>
			 <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
				<li><li.nr>9.</li.nr>
				  <al>Nothing in this Protocol shall affect the right of
					 contracting States to take measures, in conformity with their legislation, to
					 prohibit or limit the importation of articles, or their circulation after
					 importation, on grounds relating directly to national security, public order or
					 public morals.</al>
				</li>
				<li><li.nr>10.</li.nr>
				  <al>Notwithstanding other provisions of this Protocol, a
					 developing country, which is defined as such by the practice established by the
					 General Assembly of the United Nations and which is a party to the Protocol,
					 may suspend or limit the obligations under this Protocol relating to
					 importation of any object or material if such importation causes or threatens
					 to cause serious injury to the nascent indigenous industry in that developing
					 country. The country concerned shall implement such action in a
					 non-discriminatory manner. It shall notify the Director-General of the United
					 Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization of any such action,
					 as far as practicable in advance of implementation, and the Director-General of
					 the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization shall
					 notify all Parties to the Protocol.</al>
				</li>
				<li><li.nr>11.</li.nr>
				  <al>This Protocol shall not modify or affect the laws and
					 regulations of any contracting State or any of its international treaties,
					 conventions, agreements or proclamations, with respect to copyright, trade
					 marks or patents.</al>
				</li>
				<li><li.nr>12.</li.nr>
				  <al>Subject to the provisions of any previous conventions to
					 which they may have subscribed for the settlement of disputes, the contracting
					 States undertake to have recourse to negotiation or conciliation with a view to
					 settlement of any disputes regarding the interpretation or the application of
					 this Protocol.</al>
				</li>
				<li><li.nr>13.</li.nr>
				  <al>In case of a dispute between contracting States relating to
					 the educational, scientific or cultural character of imported materials, the
					 interested parties may, by common agreement refer it to the Director-General of
					 the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization for an
					 advisory opinion.</al>
				</li>
			 </lijst>
		  </divisie>
		  <divisie opmaak="default">
			 <kop><nr status="officieel">VIII</nr>
			 </kop>
			 <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
				<li><li.nr>14.</li.nr>
				  <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
					 <li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr>
						<al>This Protocol, of which the English and French texts are
						  equally authentic, shall bear today's date and shall be open to signature by
						  all States Parties to the Agreement, as well as by customs or economic unions,
						  provided that all member States constituting them are also Parties to the
						  Protocol.</al>
						<al>The term &#x201C;State&#x201D; or &#x201C;Country&#x201D; as used in this Protocol,
						  or in the Protocol referred to in paragraph 18, shall be taken to refer also,
						  as the context may require, to the customs or economic unions and, in all
						  matters which fall within their competence with regard to the scope of this
						  Protocol, to the whole of the territories of the member States which constitute
						  them, and not to the territory of each of those States.</al>
						<al>It is understood that, in becoming a contracting Party to
						  this Protocol, such customs or economic unions will also apply the provisions
						  of the Agreement on the same basis as is provided in the preceding paragraph
						  with respect to the Protocol.</al>
					 </li>
					 <li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr>
						<al>This Protocol shall be subject to ratification or
						  acceptance by the signatory States in accordance with their respective
						  constitutional procedures.</al>
					 </li>
					 <li><li.nr>(c)</li.nr>
						<al>The instruments of ratification or acceptance shall be
						  deposited with the Secretary-General of the United Nations.</al>
					 </li>
				  </lijst>
				</li>
				<li><li.nr>15.</li.nr>
				  <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
					 <li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr>
						<al>The States referred to in paragraph 14 (a) which are not
						  signatories of this Protocol may accede to this Protocol.</al>
					 </li>
					 <li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr>
						<al>Accession shall be effected by the deposit of a formal
						  instrument with the Secretary-General of the United Nations.</al>
					 </li>
				  </lijst>
				</li>
				<li><li.nr>16.</li.nr>
				  <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
					 <li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr>
						<al>The States referred to in paragraph 14 (a) of this
						  Protocol may, at the time of signature, ratification, acceptance or accession,
						  declare that they will not be bound by part II, part IV, annex C.1, annex F,
						  annex G and annex H, or by any of those parts or annexes. They may also declare
						  that they will be bound by annex C.1 only in respect of contracting States
						  which have themselves accepted that annex.</al>
					 </li>
					 <li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr>
						<al>Any contracting State which has made such a declaration
						  may withdraw it, in whole or in part, at any time by notification to the
						  Secretary-General of the United Nations, specifying the date on which such
						  withdrawal takes effect.</al>
					 </li>
					 <li><li.nr>(c)</li.nr>
						<al>States which have declared, in accordance with
						  subparagraph (a) of this paragraph, that they will not be bound by annex C.1
						  shall necessarily be bound by annex C.2. Those which have declared that they
						  will be bound by annex C.1 only in respect of contracting States which have
						  themselves accepted that annex shall necessarily be bound by annex C.2 in
						  respect of contracting States which have not accepted annex C.1.</al>
					 </li>
				  </lijst>
				</li>
				<li><li.nr>17.</li.nr>
				  <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
					 <li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr>
						<al>This Protocol shall come into force six months after the
						  date of deposit of the fifth instrument of ratification, acceptance or
						  accession with the Secretary-General of the United Nations.</al>
					 </li>
					 <li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr>
						<al>It shall come into force for every other State six months
						  after the date of the deposit of its instrument of ratification, acceptance or
						  accession.</al>
					 </li>
					 <li><li.nr>(c)</li.nr>
						<al>Within one month following the expiration of the periods
						  mentioned in subparagraphs (a) and (b) of this paragraph, the contracting
						  States to this Protocol shall submit a report to the United Nations
						  Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization on the measures which they
						  have taken to give full effect to the Protocol.</al>
					 </li>
					 <li><li.nr>(d)</li.nr>
						<al>The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
						  Organization shall transmit these reports to all States Parties to this
						  Protocol.</al>
					 </li>
				  </lijst>
				</li>
				<li><li.nr>18.</li.nr>
				  <al>The Protocol annexed to the Agreement, and made an integral
					 part thereof, as provided for in article XVII of the Agreement, is hereby made
					 an integral part of this Protocol and shall apply to obligations incurred under
					 this Protocol and to products covered by this Protocol.</al>
				</li>
				<li><li.nr>19.</li.nr>
				  <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
					 <li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr>
						<al>Two years after the date of the coming into force of this
						  Protocol, any contracting State may denounce this Protocol by an instrument in
						  writing deposited with the Secretary-General of the United Nations.</al>
					 </li>
					 <li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr>
						<al>The denunciation shall take effect one year after the
						  receipt of the instrument of denunciation.</al>
					 </li>
					 <li><li.nr>(c)</li.nr>
						<al>Denunciation of the Agreement pursuant to article XIV
						  thereof shall automatically imply denunciation of this Protocol.</al>
					 </li>
				  </lijst>
				</li>
				<li><li.nr>20.</li.nr>
				  <al>The Secretary-General of the United Nations shall inform the
					 States referred to in paragraph 14 (a), as well as the United Nations
					 Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization, of the deposit of all the
					 instruments of ratification, acceptance or accession referred to in paragraph
					 14 and 15; of declarations made and withdrawn under paragraph 16 of the dates
					 of entry into force of this Protocol in accordance with paragraph 17 (a) and
					 (b); and of the denunciations provided for in paragraph 19.</al>
				</li>
				<li><li.nr>21.</li.nr>
				  <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
					 <li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr>
						<al>This Protocol may be revised by the General Conference of
						  the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization. Any such
						  revision, however, shall be binding only upon States that become parties to the
						  revising Protocol.</al>
					 </li>
					 <li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr>
						<al>Should the General Conference adopt .a new protocol
						  revisingthis Protocol either totally or in part, and unless the new protocol
						  provides otherwise, the present Protocol shall cease to be open to signature,
						  ratification, acceptance or accession as from the date of the coming into force
						  of the new revising protocol.</al>
					 </li>
				  </lijst>
				</li>
				<li><li.nr>22.</li.nr>
				  <al>This Protocol shall not change or modify the Agreement.</al>
				</li>
				<li><li.nr>23.</li.nr>
				  <al>Annexes A, B, C.1, C.2, D, E, F, G and H are hereby made an
					 integral part of this Protocol.</al>
				</li>
				<li><li.nr>24.</li.nr>
				  <al>In accordance with Article 102 of the Charter of the United
					 Nations, this Protocol shall be registered by the Secretary-General of the
					 United Nations on the date of its coming into force.</al>
				</li>
			 </lijst>
		  </divisie>
		</vrije-tekst>
		<wetsluiting status="goed">
		  <slotformulering>
			 <al>IN FAITH WHEREOF the undersigned, duly authorized, have signed
				this Protocol on behalf of their respective Governments.</al>
			 <al>DONE at United Nations Headquarters, New York, this first day of
				March one thousand nine hundred and seventy-seven, in a single copy.</al>
		  </slotformulering>
		</wetsluiting>
	 </verdragtekst>
	 <verdragtekst> 
		<kop> 
		  <label>ANNEX</label><nr status="officieel">A</nr><titel status="officieel">Books, publications and
			 documents</titel> 
		</kop> 
		<vrije-tekst> 
		  <tekst status="goed"> 
			 <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"> 
				<li> 
				  <li.nr>(i)</li.nr> 
				  <al>Printed books, irrespective of the language in which they are
					 printed and whatever the amount of space given over to illustrations, including
					 the following:</al> 
				  <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"> 
					 <li> 
						<li.nr>(a)</li.nr> 
						<al>luxury editions;</al> 
					 </li> 
					 <li> 
						<li.nr>(b)</li.nr> 
						<al>books printed abroad from the manuscript of an author
						  resident in the importing country;</al> 
					 </li> 
					 <li> 
						<li.nr>(c)</li.nr> 
						<al>children's drawing and painting books;</al> 
					 </li> 
					 <li> 
						<li.nr>(d)</li.nr> 
						<al>school exercise books (workbooks) with printed texts and
						  blank spaces to be filled in by the pupils;</al> 
					 </li> 
					 <li> 
						<li.nr>(e)</li.nr> 
						<al>crossword puzzle books containing printed texts;</al> 
					 </li> 
					 <li> 
						<li.nr>(f)</li.nr> 
						<al>loose illustrations and printed pages in the form of
						  loose or bound sheets and reproduction proofs or reproduction films to be used
						  for the production of books.</al> 
					 </li> 
				  </lijst> 
				</li> 
				<li> 
				  <li.nr>(ii)</li.nr> 
				  <al>Printed documents or reports of a non-commercial
					 character.</al> 
				</li> 
				<li> 
				  <li.nr>(iii)</li.nr> 
				  <al>Microforms of the articles listed under items (i) and (ii) of
					 this annex, as well as of those listed under items (i) to (vi) of annex A to
					 the Agreement.</al> 
				</li> 
				<li> 
				  <li.nr>(iv)</li.nr> 
				  <al>Catalogues of films, recordings or other visual and auditory
					 material of an educational, scientific or cultural character.</al> 
				</li> 
				<li> 
				  <li.nr>(v)</li.nr> 
				  <al>Maps and charts of interest in scientific fields such as
					 geology, zoology, botany, mineralogy, palaeontology, archaelogy, ethnology,
					 meteorology, climatology and geophysics, and also meteorological and
					 geophysical diagrams.</al> 
				</li> 
				<li> 
				  <li.nr>(vi)</li.nr> 
				  <al>Architectural, industrial or engineering plans and designs
					 and reproductions thereof.</al> 
				</li> 
				<li> 
				  <li.nr>(vii)</li.nr> 
				  <al>Bibliographical information material for distribution free of
					 charge.</al> 
				</li> 
			 </lijst> 
		  </tekst> 
		</vrije-tekst> 
	 </verdragtekst> 
	 <verdragtekst> 
		<kop> 
		  <label>ANNEX</label><nr status="officieel">B</nr><titel status="officieel">Works of art and collectors'
			 pieces of an educational, scientific or cultural character</titel> 
		</kop> 
		<vrije-tekst> 
		  <tekst status="goed"> 
			 <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"> 
				<li> 
				  <li.nr>(i)</li.nr> 
				  <al>Paintings and drawings, whatever the nature of the materials
					 on which they have been executed entirely by hand, including copies executed by
					 hand, but excluding manufactured decorated wares.</al> 
				</li> 
				<li> 
				  <li.nr>(ii)</li.nr> 
				  <al>Ceramics and mosaics on wood, being original works of
					 art.</al> 
				</li> 
				<li> 
				  <li.nr>(iii)</li.nr> 
				  <al>Collectors' pieces and objects of art consigned to
					 galleries, museums and other institutions approved by the competent authorities
					 of the importing country for the purpose of duty-free entry of those types of
					 materials, on condition they are not resold.</al> 
				</li> 
			 </lijst> 
		  </tekst> 
		</vrije-tekst> 
	 </verdragtekst> 
	 <verdragtekst> 
		<kop> 
		  <label>ANNEX</label><nr status="officieel">C.1</nr> 
		  <titel status="officieel">Visual and auditory materials</titel>
		</kop> 
		<vrije-tekst> 
		  <tekst status="goed"> 
			 <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"> 
				<li><li.nr>(i)</li.nr>
				  <al>Films,
					 <noot id="f1e3758174" type="voet"> 
						<noot.nr>1) </noot.nr> 
						<noot.al>The duty-free entry of exposed and developed
						  cinematographic films for public commercial exhibition or sale may be limited
						  to negatives, it being understood that this limitation shall not apply to films
						  (including newsreels) when admitted duty-free under the provisions of annex C.2
						  to this Protocol.</noot.al> 
					 </noot>filmstrips, microforms and slides.</al>
				</li>
				<li> 
				  <li.nr>(ii)</li.nr> 
				  <al>Sound recordings.</al> 
				</li> 
				<li> 
				  <li.nr>(iii)</li.nr> 
				  <al>Patterns, models and wall charts of an educational,
					 scientific or cultural character, except toy models.</al> 
				</li> 
				<li> 
				  <li.nr>(iv)</li.nr> 
				  <al>Other visual and auditory materials, such as:</al> 
				  <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"> 
					 <li> 
						<li.nr>(a)</li.nr> 
						<al>video-tapes, kinescopes, video-discs, videograms and
						  other forms of visual and sound recordings;</al> 
					 </li> 
					 <li> 
						<li.nr>(b)</li.nr> 
						<al>microcards, microfiches and magnetic or other information
						  storage media required in computerized information and documentation
						  services;</al> 
					 </li> 
					 <li> 
						<li.nr>(c)</li.nr> 
						<al>materials for programmed instruction, which may be
						  presented in kit form, with the corresponding printed materials, including
						  video-cassettes and audio-cassettes;</al> 
					 </li> 
					 <li> 
						<li.nr>(d)</li.nr> 
						<al>transparencies, including those intended for direct
						  projection or for viewing through optical devices;</al> 
					 </li> 
					 <li> 
						<li.nr>(e)</li.nr> 
						<al>holograms for laser projection;</al> 
					 </li> 
					 <li> 
						<li.nr>(f)</li.nr> 
						<al>mock-ups or visualizations of abstract concepts such as
						  molecular structures or mathematical formulae;</al> 
					 </li> 
					 <li> 
						<li.nr>(g)</li.nr> 
						<al>multi-media kits;</al> 
					 </li> 
					 <li> 
						<li.nr>(h)</li.nr> 
						<al>materials for the promotion of tourism, including those
						  produced by private concerns, designed to encourage the public to travel
						  outside the country of importation.</al> 
					 </li> 
				  </lijst> 
				  <al>(The exemptions provided for in the present annex C.1 shall
					 not apply to :</al> 
				  <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
					 <li> 
						<li.nr>(a)</li.nr> 
						<al>unused microform stock and unused visual and auditory
						  recording media and their specific packaging such as cassettes, cartridges,
						  reels;</al> 
					 </li> 
					 <li> 
						<li.nr>(b)</li.nr> 
						<al>visual and auditory recordings with the exception of
						  materials for the promotion of tourism covered by paragraph (iv) (h), produced
						  by or for a private commercial enterprise, essentially for advertising
						  purposes;</al> 
					 </li> 
					 <li> 
						<li.nr>(c)</li.nr> 
						<al>visual and auditory recordings in which the advertising
						  matter is in excess of 25 per cent by time. In the case of the materials for
						  the promotion of tourism covered by paragraph (iv) (h), this percentage applies
						  only to private commercial publicity.)</al> 
					 </li>
				  </lijst>
				</li> 
			 </lijst> 
		  </tekst> 
		</vrije-tekst> 
	 </verdragtekst> 
	 <verdragtekst> 
		<kop> 
		  <label>ANNEX</label><nr status="officieel">C.2</nr><titel status="officieel">Visual and auditory materials of
			 an educational, scientific or cultural character</titel> 
		</kop> 
		<vrije-tekst> 
		  <tekst status="goed"> 
			 <tussenkop kopopmaak="cur"> <nadruk type="cur"/> </tussenkop> 
			 <al>Visual and auditory materials of an educational, scientific or
				cultural character, when imported by organizations (including, at the
				discretion of the importing country, broadcasting and television organizations)
				or by any other public or private institution or association, approved by the
				competent authorities of the importing country for the purpose of duty-free
				admission of these types of materials or when produced by the United Nations or
				any of its specialized agencies and including the following:</al> 
			 <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"> 
				<li> 
				  <li.nr>(i)</li.nr> 
				  <al>films, filmstrips, microfilms and slides;</al> 
				</li> 
				<li> 
				  <li.nr>(ii)</li.nr> 
				  <al>newsreels (with or without sound track) depicting events of
					 current news value at the time of importation, and imported in either negative
					 form, exposed and developed, or positive form, printed and developed, it being
					 understood that dutyf-ree entry may be limited to two copies of each subject
					 for copying purposes;</al> 
				</li> 
				<li> 
				  <li.nr>(iii)</li.nr> 
				  <al>archival film material (with or without sound track) intended
					 for use in connexion with newsreel films;</al> 
				</li> 
				<li> 
				  <li.nr>(iv)</li.nr> 
				  <al>recreational films particularly suited for children and
					 youth;</al> 
				</li> 
				<li> 
				  <li.nr>(v)</li.nr> 
				  <al>sound recordings;</al> 
				</li> 
				<li> 
				  <li.nr>(vi)</li.nr> 
				  <al>video-tapes, kinescopes, video-discs, videograms and other
					 forms of visual and sound recordings;</al> 
				</li> 
				<li> 
				  <li.nr>(vii)</li.nr> 
				  <al>microcards, microfiches and magnetic or other information
					 storage media required in computerized information and documentation
					 services;</al> 
				</li> 
				<li> 
				  <li.nr>(viii)</li.nr> 
				  <al>materials for programmed instruction, which may be presented
					 in kit form, with the corresponding printed materials, including
					 video-cassettes and audio-cassettes;</al> 
				</li> 
				<li> 
				  <li.nr>(ix)</li.nr> 
				  <al>transparencies, including those intended for direct
					 projection or for viewing through optical devices;</al> 
				</li> 
				<li> 
				  <li.nr>(x)</li.nr> 
				  <al>holograms for laser projection;</al> 
				</li> 
				<li> 
				  <li.nr>(xi)</li.nr> 
				  <al>mock-ups or visualizations of abstract concepts such as
					 molecular structures or mathematical formulae;</al> 
				</li>
				<li><li.nr>(xii)</li.nr>
				  <al>multi-media kits.</al>
				</li> 
			 </lijst> 
		  </tekst> 
		</vrije-tekst> 
	 </verdragtekst> 
	 <verdragtekst> 
		<kop> 
		  <label>ANNEX</label><nr status="officieel">D</nr><titel status="officieel">Scientific instruments or
			 apparatus</titel> 
		</kop> 
		<vrije-tekst> 
		  <tekst status="goed"> 
			 <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"> 
				<li> 
				  <li.nr>(i)</li.nr> 
				  <al>Scientific instruments or apparatus, provided:</al> 
				  <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"> 
					 <li> 
						<li.nr>(a)</li.nr> 
						<al>that they are consigned to public or private scientific
						  or educational institutions approved by the competent authorities of the
						  importing country for the purpose of duty-free entry of these types of
						  articles, and used for non-commercial purposes under the control and
						  responsibility of these institutions;</al> 
					 </li> 
					 <li> 
						<li.nr>(b)</li.nr> 
						<al>that instruments or apparatus of equivalent scientific
						  value are not being manufactured in the country of importation.</al> 
					 </li> 
				  </lijst> 
				</li> 
				<li> 
				  <li.nr>(ii)</li.nr> 
				  <al>Spare parts, components or accessories specifically matching
					 scientific instruments or apparatus, provided these spare parts, components or
					 accessories are imported at the same time as such instruments and apparatus, or
					 if imported subsequently, that they are identifiable as intended for
					 instruments or apparatus previously admitted duty-free or entitled to duty-free
					 entry.</al> 
				</li> 
				<li> 
				  <li.nr>(iii)</li.nr> 
				  <al>Tools to be used for the maintenance, checking, gauging or
					 repair of scientific instruments, provided these tools are imported at the same
					 time as such instruments and apparatus or, if imported subsequently, that they
					 are identifiable as intended for the specific instruments or apparatus
					 previously admitted duty-free or entitled to duty-free entry, and further
					 provided that tools of equivalent scientific value are not being manufactured
					 in the country of importation.</al> 
				</li> 
			 </lijst> 
		  </tekst> 
		</vrije-tekst> 
	 </verdragtekst> 
	 <verdragtekst> 
		<kop> 
		  <label>ANNEX</label><nr status="officieel">E</nr><titel status="officieel">Articles for the blind and other
			 handicapped persons</titel> 
		</kop> 
		<vrije-tekst> 
		  <tekst status="goed"> 
			 <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"> 
				<li> 
				  <li.nr>(i)</li.nr> 
				  <al>All articles specially designed for the educational,
					 scientific orcultural advancement of the blind which are imported directly by
					 institutions or organizations concerned with the education of, or assistance
					 to, the blind, approved by the competent authorities of the importing country
					 for the purpose of duty-free entry of these types of articles, including:</al> 
				  <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"> 
					 <li> 
						<li.nr>(a)</li.nr> 
						<al>talking books (discs, cassettes or other sound
						  reproductions) and large-print books;</al> 
					 </li> 
					 <li> 
						<li.nr>(b)</li.nr> 
						<al>phonographs and cassette players, specially designed or
						  adapted for the blind and other handicapped persons and required to play the
						  talking books;</al> 
					 </li> 
					 <li> 
						<li.nr>(c)</li.nr> 
						<al>equipment for the reading of normal print by the blind
						  and partially sighted, such as electronic reading machines,
						  television-enlargers and optical aids;</al> 
					 </li> 
					 <li> 
						<li.nr>(d)</li.nr> 
						<al>equipment for the mechanical or computerized production
						  of braille and recorded material, such as stereotyping machines, electronic
						  braille, transfer and pressing machines; braille computer terminals and
						  displays;</al> 
					 </li> 
					 <li> 
						<li.nr>(e)</li.nr> 
						<al>braille paper, magnetic tapes and cassettes for the
						  production of braille and talking books;</al> 
					 </li> 
					 <li> 
						<li.nr>(f)</li.nr> 
						<al>aids for improving the mobility of the blind, such as
						  electronic orientation and obstacle detection appliances and white canes;</al> 
					 </li> 
					 <li> 
						<li.nr>(g)</li.nr> 
						<al>technical aids for the education, rehabilitation,
						  vocational training and employment of the blind, such as braille watches,
						  braille typewriters, teaching and learning aids, games and other instruments
						  specifically adapted for the use of the blind.</al> 
					 </li> 
				  </lijst> 
				</li> 
				<li> 
				  <li.nr>(ii)</li.nr> 
				  <al>All materials specially designed for the education,
					 employment and social advancement of other physically or mentally handicapped
					 persons, directly imported by institutions or organizations concerned with the
					 education of, or assistance to, such persons, approved by the competent
					 authorities of the importing country for the purpose of duty-free entry of
					 these types of articles, provided that equivalent objects are not being
					 manufactured in the importing country.</al> 
				</li> 
			 </lijst> 
		  </tekst> 
		</vrije-tekst> 
	 </verdragtekst> 
	 <verdragtekst> 
		<kop> 
		  <label>ANNEX</label><nr status="officieel">F</nr><titel status="officieel">Sports equipment</titel> 
		</kop> 
		<vrije-tekst> 
		  <tekst status="goed"> 
			 <al>Sports equipment intended exclusively for amateur sports
				associations or groups approved by the competent authorities of the importing
				country for the purpose of duty-free entry of these types of articles, provided
				that equivalent materials are not being manufactured in the importing
				country.</al> 
		  </tekst> 
		</vrije-tekst> 
	 </verdragtekst> 
	 <verdragtekst> 
		<kop> 
		  <label>ANNEX</label><nr status="officieel">G</nr> 
		  <titel status="officieel">Musical instruments and other musical equipment</titel>
		</kop> 
		<vrije-tekst> 
		  <tekst status="goed"> 
			 <al>Musical instruments and other musical equipment intended
				solely for cultural institutions or music schools approved by the competent
				authorities of the importing country for the purpose of duty-free entry of
				these types of articles, provided that equivalent instruments and other
				equipment are not being manufactured in the importing country.</al> 
		  </tekst> 
		</vrije-tekst> 
	 </verdragtekst> 
	 <verdragtekst> 
		<kop> 
		  <label>ANNEX</label><nr status="officieel">H</nr> 
		  <titel status="officieel">Material and machines used for the production of books,
			 publications and documents</titel>
		</kop> 
		<vrije-tekst> 
		  <tekst status="goed"> 
			 <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"> 
				<li> 
				  <li.nr>(i)</li.nr> 
				  <al>Material used for the production of books, publications
					 and documents (paper pulp, recycled paper, newsprint and other types of paper
					 used for printing, printing inks, glue, etc.).</al> 
				</li> 
				<li> 
				  <li.nr>(ii)</li.nr> 
				  <al>Machines for the processing of paper pulp and paper and also
					 printing and binding machines, provided that machines of equivalent technical
					 quality are not being manufactured in the importing country.</al> 
				</li> 
			 </lijst> 
		  </tekst> 
		</vrije-tekst> 
	 </verdragtekst>
  </verdrag>
</wetgeving>
  	