<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE wetgeving SYSTEM "http://wetten.overheid.nl/dtd/bwb-plus-meta-1_61w.dtd">
<wetgeving bwb-id="BWBV0002340" dtdversie="2.0" id="10000018149" verdragnummer="000146" soort="verdrag"><intitule>Overeenkomst tussen de Regering van het Koninkrijk der Nederlanden en de Regering van Malta inzake de bevordering en wederzijdse bescherming van investeringen</intitule><verdrag tekst="authentiek" xml:lang="en"><verdragtekst>
<kop>
<titel status="officieel">Agreement between the Government of the Kingdom of the Netherlands and the Government of Malta concerning the encouragement and reciprocal protection of investments</titel>
</kop><aanhef><preambule><al>The Government of the Kingdom of the Netherlands and the Government of Malta,</al><al>Desiring to create favourable conditions for investments by nationals and companies of either State in the territory of the other State, and</al><al>Recognizing that encouragement and contractual protection of such investments are apt to stimulate private business initiative and to increase the prosperity of both nations,</al><al>Have agreed as follows:</al></preambule></aanhef><wettekst><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">I</nr>
</kop><al>For the purposes of the present Agreement:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>a)</li.nr><al>the term "investments" shall comprise every kind of asset and more particularly, though not exclusively:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>i)</li.nr><al>movable and immovable property as well as any other rights in rem;</al></li><li><li.nr>ii)</li.nr><al>shares or other kinds of interests in companies;</al></li><li><li.nr>iii)</li.nr><al>title to money or to any performance, such as goodwill, having an economic value;</al></li><li><li.nr>iv)</li.nr><al>rights in the fields of the intellectual property, technical processes and know how;</al></li><li><li.nr>v)</li.nr><al>such business concessions under public law, including concessions regarding the prospecting for or the extraction or the winning of natural resources, as give to their holders a legal position of some duration.</al></li></lijst></li><li><li.nr>b)</li.nr><al>the term "nationals" shall comprise with regard to either Contracting Party:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>i)</li.nr><al>natural persons having the nationality of that Contracting Party in accordance with its law;</al></li><li><li.nr>ii)</li.nr><al>without prejudice to the provisions of (iii) hereafter, legal persons constituted in accordance with the law of that Contracting Party;</al></li><li><li.nr>iii)</li.nr><al>legal persons controlled, directly or indirectly, by nationals of that Contracting Party but constituted in accordance with the law of the other Contracting Party.</al></li></lijst></li></lijst></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">II</nr>
</kop><al>Either Contracting Party shall, within the framework of its laws and regulations, promote economic cooperation between its nationals and nationals of the other Contracting Party, through the protection in its territory of investments of nationals of the other Contracting Party.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">III</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Each Contracting Party shall ensure fair and equitable treatment to the investments of nationals of the other Contracting Party and shall not impair by unjustified or discriminatory measures, the operation, management, maintenance, use, enjoyment or disposal thereof by those nationals.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>More particularly, each Contracting Party shall accord to such investments the same security and protection as it accords either to those of its own nationals or to those of nationals of any third State, whichever is more favourable to the investor.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>Paragraph 2 of this Article shall not apply to entry and sojourn.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">IV</nr>
</kop><al>Recognizing the principle of the freedom of transfer each Contracting Party shall authorize, in conformity with its relevant most favourable rules the transfer, without undue restriction and delay, to the country of the other Contracting Party and in the currency of that country or any other freely convertible currency of payments resulting from investment activities and in particular of the following items:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>a)</li.nr><al>net profits, interests, dividends and other current income;</al></li><li><li.nr>b)</li.nr><al>funds necessary</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>i)</li.nr><al>for the acquisition of raw or auxiliary materials, semifabricated or nished products, or</al></li><li><li.nr>ii)</li.nr><al>to replace capital assets in order to safeguard the continuity of an investment;</al></li></lijst></li><li><li.nr>c)</li.nr><al>additional funds necessary for the development of an investment;</al></li><li><li.nr>d)</li.nr><al>earnings of natural persons;</al></li><li><li.nr>e)</li.nr><al>the proceeds of liquidation of capital;</al></li><li><li.nr>f)</li.nr><al>funds in repayment of loans;</al></li><li><li.nr>g)</li.nr><al>management fees;</al></li><li><li.nr>h)</li.nr><al>royalties.</al></li></lijst></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">V</nr>
</kop><al>Neither Contracting Party shall take any measures depriving directly or indirectly, nationals of the other Contracting Party of their investments unless the following conditions are complied with:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>a)</li.nr><al>the measures are taken in the public interest and under due process of law;</al></li><li><li.nr>b)</li.nr><al>the measures are not discriminatory or contrary to any undertaking which the former Contracting Party may have given;</al></li><li><li.nr>c)</li.nr><al>the measures are accompanied by provision for the payment of just compensation. Such compensation shall represent the genuine value of the investments affected and shall, in order to be effective for the claimants, be paid and made transferable without undue delay, to the country of which those claimants are nationals and in the currency of that country or any other freely convertible currency.</al></li></lijst></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">VI</nr>
</kop><al>If a national of the one Contracting Party has transferred any rights and securities to that Party or to another national of that Party because of that Party's or the latter national's obligation, under a legal system of guaranteeing against non-commercial risks, to reimburse the former national as to damage in respect of an investment made by that national in the territory of the other Contracting Party and approved by that Party the latter Contracting Party recognizes the subrogation of the grantor into the said rights and securities of the investor.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">VII</nr>
</kop><al>The present Agreement shall apply to all investments (whether or not within the framework of a joint venture) made in the territory of the one Contracting Party by a national of the other Contracting Party.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">VIII</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>The Contracting Parties hereby establish a Mixed Commission, composed of representatives appointed by them.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>The Mixed Commission shall meet at the request of one of the Contracting Parties, to discuss any matters pertaining to the implementation of the present Agreement.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">IX</nr>
</kop><al>In respect of any matter governed by the present Agreement nothing in this Agreement shall prevent a national of the one Contracting Party from benefiting from any right more favourable to him and accorded by the other Contracting Party.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">X</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Any dispute between the Contracting Parties concerning the interpretation or application of the present Agreement which cannot be settled, within a reasonable lapse of time, by means of diplomatic negotiations, shall be submitted, at the request of any party to the dispute, to an arbitral tribunal, composed of three members. Each party shall appoint one arbitrator and the two arbitrators thus appointed shall together appoint a third arbitrator as their chairman who is not a national of either party.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>If one of the parties fails to appoint its arbitrator and has not proceeded to do so within two months after an invitation from the other party to make such appointment the latter party may invite the President of the International Court of Justice to make the necessary appointment.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>If the two arbitrators are unable to reach agreement, in the two months following their appointment on the choice of the third arbitrator, either party may invite the President of the International Court of Justice to make the necessary appointment.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr><al>If, in the cases provided for in the second and third paragraph of this Article the President of the International Court of Justice is prevented from discharging the said function or is a national of either party, the Vice-President should make the necessary appointments. If the Vice-President is prevented from discharging the said function or is a national of either party, the most senior member of the Court who is not a national of either party should make the necessary appointments.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">5</lidnr><al>The tribunal shall decide on the basis of respect for the law. Before the tribunal decides, it may at any stage of the proceedings propose to the parties that the dispute be settled amicably. The foregoing provisions shall not prejudice the power of the tribunal to decide the dispute ex aequo et bono if the parties so agree.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">6</lidnr><al>Unless the parties decide otherwise, the tribunal shall determine its own procedure.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">7</lidnr><al>The tribunal shall reach its decision by a majority of votes. Such decision shall be final and binding on the parties to the dispute.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">XI</nr>
</kop><al>As regards the Kingdom of the Netherlands, the present Agreement shall apply to the territory of the Kingdom in Europe only.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">XII</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>The present Agreement shall enter into force on the first day of the second calendar month following the date on which both Contracting Parties will have informed each other in writing that the procedures constitutionally required therefor in their respective countries have been complied with and shall remain in force for a period of 15 years.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Unless notice of termination has been given by either Contracting Party at least six months before the date of the expiry of its validity, the present Agreement shall be extended tacitly for periods of 10 years, each Contracting Party reserving the right to terminate the Agreement upon notice of at least six months before the date of expiry of the current period of validity.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>In respect of investments made before the date of the termination of the present Agreement the foregoing Articles thereof shall continue to be effective for a further period of 10 years from that date.</al></lid></artikel></wettekst><wetsluiting status="goed"><slotformulering><al>IN WITNESS WHEREOF, the undersigned representatives, duly authorized thereto, have signed the present Agreement.</al><al>DONE at The Hague, this 10th day of September 1984.</al><al><nadruk type="cur">For the Government of the</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur"> Kingdom of the Netherlands</nadruk></al><al>(sd.) H. VAN DEN BROEK</al><al><nadruk type="cur">For the Government of the</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur">Republic of Malta</nadruk></al><al>(sd.) P. FARRUGIA</al></slotformulering></wetsluiting></verdragtekst></verdrag><verdrag tekst="vertaling" xml:lang="nl"><verdragtekst>
<kop>
<titel status="officieel">Overeenkomst tussen de Regering van het Koninkrijk der Nederlanden en de Regering van Malta inzake de bevordering en wederzijdse bescherming van investeringen</titel>
</kop><aanhef><preambule><al>De Regering van het Koninkrijk der Nederlanden en de Regering van Malta,</al><al>geleid door de wens gunstige voorwaarden te scheppen voor investeringen door onderdanen en bedrijven van een van beide Staten op het grondgebied van de andere Staat, en</al><al>in het besef dat bevordering en contractuele bescherming van dergelijke investeringen zich ertoe lenen het nemen van initiatieven door het bedrijfsleven aan te moedigen en de welvaart van beide naties te vergroten,</al><al>zijn overeengekomen als volgt:</al></preambule></aanhef><wettekst><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">I</nr>
</kop><al>Voor de toepassing van deze Overeenkomst omvat de term:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>a)</li.nr><al>&#x201E;investeringen&#x201D; alle soorten vermogensbestanddelen en in het bijzonder, doch niet uitsluitend:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>i)</li.nr><al>roerende en onroerende goederen, alsmede alle andere zakelijke rechten;</al></li><li><li.nr>ii)</li.nr><al>aandelen of andere belangen in ondernemingen;</al></li><li><li.nr>iii)</li.nr><al>recht op geld of op iedere prestatie, zoals goodwill, die economische waarde heeft;</al></li><li><li.nr>iv)</li.nr><al>rechten op het gebied van de intellectuele eigendom, technische werkwijzen en know-how;</al></li><li><li.nr>v)</li.nr><al>publiekrechtelijke commerci&#xEB;le concessies, met inbegrip van concessies betreffende het opsporen, dan wel het ontginnen of winnen van natuurlijke rijkdommen, die de houders daarvan een rechtspositie van enige duur verlenen.</al></li></lijst></li><li><li.nr>b)</li.nr><al>&#x201E;onderdanen&#x201D;, met betrekking tot beide Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>i)</li.nr><al>natuurlijke personen die volgens het recht van die Overeenkomstsluitende Partij haar nationaliteit bezitten;</al></li><li><li.nr>ii)</li.nr><al>onverminderd het bepaalde in (iii) hieronder, rechtspersonen die zijn opgericht overeenkomstig het recht van die Overeenkomstsluitende Partij;</al></li><li><li.nr>iii)</li.nr><al>rechtspersonen die onder, al dan niet rechtstreeks, toezicht staan van onderdanen van die Overeenkomstsluitende Partij, maar die zijn opgericht overeenkomstig het recht van de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij.</al></li></lijst></li></lijst></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">II</nr>
</kop><al>Binnen het kader van haar wetten en voorschriften bevordert elk van beide Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen de economische samenwerking tussen haar onderdanen en de onderdanen van de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij door de bescherming op haar grondgebied van investeringen van onderdanen van de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">III</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Iedere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij waarborgt een eerlijke en rechtvaardige behandeling van de investeringen van onderdanen van de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij en belemmert niet, door ongerechtvaardigde of discriminatoire maatregelen, de werking, het beheer, de instandhouding, het gebruik en het genot hiervan of de beschikking hierover door die onderdanen.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Met name kent iedere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij aan zodanige investeringen dezelfde zekerheid en bescherming toe als zij toekent aan die van haar eigen onderdanen of die van onderdanen van een derde Staat, welke van beide het gunstigst is voor de investeerder.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>Het tweede lid van dit artikel is niet van toepassing op binnenkomst en tijdelijk verblijf.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">IV</nr>
</kop><al>In erkenning van het beginsel van de vrijheid van overmaking staat elke Overeenkomstsluitende Partij, met inachtneming van haar gunstigste regels ter zake, de overmaking toe, zonder onnodige beperking en vertraging, naar het land van de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij en in de valuta van dat land of in een andere vrij inwisselbare valuta, van betalingen die voortvloeien uit investeringsactiviteiten en in het bijzonder van de volgende bestanddelen:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>a)</li.nr><al>netto winsten, interesten, dividenden en andere lopende inkomsten;</al></li><li><li.nr>b)</li.nr><al>gelden nodig</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>i)</li.nr><al>voor het verwerven van grondstoffen of hulpmaterialen, halffabrikaten of eindprodukten, of</al></li><li><li.nr>ii)</li.nr><al>om kapitaalgoederen te vervangen ten einde de continu&#xEF;teit van een investering te waarborgen;</al></li></lijst></li><li><li.nr>c)</li.nr><al>bijkomende gelden, noodzakelijk voor de ontwikkeling van een investering;</al></li><li><li.nr>d)</li.nr><al>inkomsten uit arbeid van natuurlijke personen;</al></li><li><li.nr>e)</li.nr><al>de opbrengst van de liquidatie van kapitaal;</al></li><li><li.nr>f)</li.nr><al>gelden voor terugbetaling van leningen;</al></li><li><li.nr>g)</li.nr><al>honoraria voor verleende beheersdiensten;</al></li><li><li.nr>h)</li.nr><al>royalty's.</al></li></lijst></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">V</nr>
</kop><al>Geen van beide Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen neemt maatregelen, waardoor aan onderdanen van de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij direct of indirect hun investeringen worden ontnomen, tenzij aan de volgende voorwaarden is voldaan:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>a)</li.nr><al>de maatregelen zijn genomen in het algemeen belangen met inachtneming van een behoorlijke rechtsgang;</al></li><li><li.nr>b)</li.nr><al>de maatregelen zijn niet discriminatoir of in strijd met enige toezegging, gedaan door eerstgenoemde Overeenkomstsluitende Partij;</al></li><li><li.nr>c)</li.nr><al>de maatregelen gaan vergezeld van een regeling voor de betaling van rechtvaardige schadeloosstelling. Deze schadeloosstelling dient de echte waarde van de getroffen investeringen te vertegenwoordigen en zij moet, wil zij doeltreffend zijn voorde gerechtigden, zonder onnodige vertraging worden betaald en overgemaakt naar het land waarvan die gerechtigden onderdaan zijn, in de valuta van dat land, of in een andere vrij inwisselbare valuta.</al></li></lijst></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">VI</nr>
</kop><al>Indien een onderdaan van de ene Overeenkomstsluitende Partij enigerlei rechten en zekerheden heeft overgedragen aan die Partij of aan een andere onderdaan van die Partij wegens de verplichting van die Partij of van laatstbedoelde onderdaan, krachtens een rechtsstelsel waarbij een garantie wordt geboden tegen niet-commerci&#xEB;le risico's, ten einde de eerstbedoelde onderdaan schadeloos te stellen ten aanzien van schade verband houdend met een door die onderdaan op het grondgebied van de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij met haar toestemming gedane investering, erkent de laatstbedoelde Overeenkomstsluitende Partij de subrogatie van degene die de zekerheid heeft gesteld, in de genoemde rechten en zekerheden van de investeerder.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">VII</nr>
</kop><al>Deze Overeenkomst is van toepassing op alle investeringen (al dan niet binnen het kader van een gezamenlijke onderneming) die op het grondgebied van de ene Overeenkomstsluitende Partij zijn gedaan door een onderdaan van de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">VIII</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>De Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen stellen bij dezen een Gemengde Commissie in, bestaande uit door hen aangewezen vertegenwoordigers.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>De Gemengde Commissie komt bijeen op verzoek van een der Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen voor het bespreken van aangelegenheden betreffende de tenuitvoerlegging van deze Overeenkomst.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">IX</nr>
</kop><al>Niets in deze Overeenkomst belet een onderdaan van de ene Overeenkomstsluitende Partij met betrekking tot een bij deze Overeenkomst geregelde aangelegenheid voordeel te genieten van een voor hem gunstiger recht dat hem is verleend door de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">X</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Enig geschil tussen de Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen betreffende de uitlegging of de toepassing van deze Overeenkomst, dat niet binnen een redelijke termijn langs de diplomatieke weg kan worden geregeld, wordt op verzoek van een van de partijen bij het geschil voorgelegd aan een uit drie leden samengesteld scheidsgerecht. Iedere partij benoemt een scheidsman en de beide aldus benoemde scheidsmannen benoemen te zamen een derde scheidsman, die geen onderdaan is van een der beide partijen, tot hun voorzitter.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Indien een van de partijen nalaat haar scheidsman te benoemen en indien zij geen gevolg heeft gegeven aan het verzoek van de andere partij binnen twee maanden tot deze benoeming over te gaan, kan de laatstgenoemde partij de President van het Internationale Gerechtshof verzoeken de noodzakelijke benoeming te verrichten.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>Indien de beide scheidsmannen binnen twee maanden na hun aanwijzing niet tot overeenstemming kunnen geraken over de keuze van een derde scheidsman, kan een van beide partijen de President van het Internationale Gerechtshof verzoeken de noodzakelijke benoeming te verrichten.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr><al>Indien in de gevallen, bedoeld in het tweede en derde lid van dit artikel, de President van het Internationale Gerechtshof verhinderd is genoemde functie uit te oefenen, of onderdaan is van een van beide partijen, dienen de noodzakelijke benoemingen te geschieden door de Vice-President. Indien de Vice-President verhinderd is genoemde functie uit te oefenen, of indien hij onderdaan is van een van beide partijen, dienen de noodzakelijke benoemingen te geschieden door het lid van het Gerechtshof, dat het hoogst in anci&#xEB;nniteit is en dat geen onderdaan is van een van beide partijen.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">5</lidnr><al>Het scheidsgerecht doet uitspraak op de grondslag van de eerbiediging van het recht. Alvorens uitspraak te doen, kan het scheidsgerecht in elke stand van het geding een minnelijke schikking van het geschil aan de partijen voorstellen. De voorgaande bepalingen doen geen afbreuk aan de bevoegdheid van het scheidsgerecht in het geschil een uitspraak ex aequo et bono te doen, indien de partijen daarmee instemmen.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">6</lidnr><al>Tenzij partijen anders beslissen, stelt het scheidsgerecht zijn eigen procedureregels vast.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">7</lidnr><al>Het scheidsgerecht doet zijn uitspraak bij meerderheid van stemmen. Een zodanige uitspraak is onherroepelijk en bindend voor de partijen bij het geschil.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">XI</nr>
</kop><al>Ten aanzien van het Koninkrijk der Nederlanden is deze Overeenkomst alleen van toepassing op het Rijk in Europa.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">XII</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Deze Overeenkomst treedt in werking op de eerste dag van de tweede kalendermaand volgend op de datum waarop beide Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen elkaar schriftelijk hebben medegedeeld, dat aan de in hun onderscheiden landen hiertoe grondwettelijk vereiste procedures is voldaan, en zij blijft van kracht gedurende een tijdvak van 15 jaar.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Tenzij door een van beide Partijen ten minste zes maanden voor het vervallen van haar geldigheid kennisgeving van opzegging wordt gedaan, wordt deze Overeenkomst stilzwijgend verlengd voor telkens een volgend tijdvak van 10 jaar, waarbij iedere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij zich het recht voorbehoudt de Overeenkomst te be&#xEB;indigen, nadat zij ten minste zes maanden voor het verstrijken van de lopende termijn van geldigheid van dit voornemen kennis heeft gegeven.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>Ten aanzien van investeringen die zijn verricht voor de datum van be&#xEB;indiging van deze Overeenkomst, blijven de voorafgaande artikelen daarvan van kracht gedurende een tijdvak van nog eens 10 jaar, te rekenen vanaf die datum.</al></lid></artikel></wettekst><wetsluiting status="goed"><slotformulering><al>TEN BLIJKE WAARVAN de ondertekenende vertegenwoordigers, daartoe behoorlijk gemachtigd, deze Overeenkomst hebben ondertekend.</al><al>GEDAAN te 's-Gravenhage, op 10 september 1984.</al><al><nadruk type="cur">Voor de Regering van het</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur"> Koninkrijk der Nederlanden:</nadruk></al><al>(w.g.) H. VAN DEN BROEK</al><al><nadruk type="cur">Voor de Regering van de</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur"> Republiek Malta:</nadruk></al><al>(w.g) P. FARRUGIA</al></slotformulering></wetsluiting></verdragtekst></verdrag></wetgeving>
  	