<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE wetgeving SYSTEM "http://wetten.overheid.nl/dtd/bwb-plus-meta-1_61w.dtd">
<wetgeving bwb-id="BWBV0001793" dtdversie="2.0" id="10000012229" verdragnummer="011136" soort="verdrag">
  
  <intitule>Verdrag tussen het Koninkrijk der Nederlanden en Eurojust </intitule>
  
  <verdrag tekst="authentiek" xml:lang="en">
    <verdragtekst>
      <kop>
        <titel status="officieel">Agreement between the Kingdom of the Netherlands and Eurojust</titel>
      </kop>
      <aanhef>
        <preambule>
          <al>The Kingdom of the Netherlands and Eurojust  (hereafter, the Parties)</al>
          <al>Having regard to the Council Decision of 28 February 2002 setting up Eurojust
with a view to reinforcing the fight against serious crime;</al>
          <al>Whereas Article 1c) of the Decision taken by common agreement between
the Representatives of the Member States, meeting at Head of State or Government
level, of 13 December 2003 on the location of seats of certain offices and
agencies of the European Union, provides having regard to Article 289 of the
Treaty establishing the European Community, that Eurojust shall have its seat
in The Hague;</al>
          <al>Have agreed as follows:</al>
        </preambule>
      </aanhef>
      <wettekst>
        
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">1</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Definitions</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>For the purposes of this Agreement:</al>
          <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
            <li>
              <li.nr>a)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x2018;&#x2018;Eurojust Decision&#x2019;&#x2019;
means the Council Decision of 28 February 2002 setting up Eurojust with a
view to reinforcing the fight against serious crime;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>b)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x2018;&#x2018;Eurojust&#x2019;&#x2019; means
the unit set up by the Eurojust Decision;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>c)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x2018;&#x2018;Government&#x2019;&#x2019; means
the Government of the Kingdom of the Netherlands; </al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>d)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x2018;&#x2018;Host State authorities&#x2019;&#x2019;
means such State, municipal or other authorities of the Kingdom of the Netherlands
as may be appropriate in the context of and in accordance with the laws and
customs applicable in the Kingdom of the Netherlands;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>e)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x2018;&#x2018;Headquarters&#x2019;&#x2019;
means the area, any building, land or facilities ancillary thereto, irrespective
of ownership, used on a permanent basis, temporarily or from time to time
by Eurojust following mutual agreement between Eurojust and the Government,
to carry out its official functions;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>f)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x2018;&#x2018;national member&#x2019;&#x2019;
means a person referred to in Article 2, paragraph 1, of the Eurojust Decision;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>g)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x2018;&#x2018;College&#x2019;&#x2019; means
the College referred to in Article 10 of the Eurojust Decision;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>h)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x2018;&#x2018;President of the College&#x2019;&#x2019;
means the national member elected as President by the College, as referred
to in Article 28, paragraph 2, of the Eurojust Decision;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>i)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x2018;&#x2018;Assistant&#x2019;&#x2019; means
any assistant of a national member as referred to in Article 2, paragraph
2,  of the Eurojust Decision;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>j)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x2018;&#x2018;national correspondent&#x2019;&#x2019;
means a person referred to in Article 12 of the Eurojust Decision;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>k)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x2018;&#x2018;Joint Supervisory Body&#x2019;&#x2019;
means the body referred to in Article 23 of the Eurojust Decision;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>l)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x2018;&#x2018;Administrative Director&#x2019;&#x2019;
means the Administrative Director referred to in Article 29 of the Eurojust
Decision;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>m)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x2018;&#x2018;staff&#x2019;&#x2019; means
the Eurojust staff referred to in Article 30 of the Eurojust Decision;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>n)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x2018;&#x2018;Protocol&#x2019;&#x2019; means
the Protocol on the Privileges and Immunities of the European Communities;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>o)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x2018;&#x2018;Vienna Convention&#x2019;&#x2019;
means the Vienna Convention on Diplomatic Relations;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>p)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x2018;&#x2018;archives&#x2019;&#x2019; means
all records, correspondence, documents, manuscripts, computer and media data,
photographs, film, video and sound recordings belonging to, or held by or
on behalf of Eurojust, and any other similar material which Eurojust and the
Government may agree upon to be part of the archives of Eurojust; and</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>q)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x2018;&#x2018;Member State&#x2019;&#x2019;
means any Member State of the European  Union.</al>
            </li>
          </lijst>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">2</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Immunity from Jurisdiction and Execution and Inviolability of Archives </titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>Eurojust shall enjoy immunity from jurisdiction and execution
in the Kingdom of the Netherlands. Within one year after the entry into force
of the Treaty establishing a Constitution for the European Union, the Government
and Eurojust will decide by mutual consent whether the present provision needs
to be amended. </al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>The property, funds and assets of Eurojust, wherever located and
by whomsoever held, shall be immune from legal process and from search, seizure,
requisition, confiscation, expropriation and any other form of interference.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al>The archives of Eurojust shall be inviolable.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">3</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Inviolability of the Headquarters of Eurojust</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>The Headquarters of Eurojust shall be inviolable. Any person to
enter any place under any legal provision or on the strength of the law shall
not exercise that authority in respect of the Headquarters unless permission
to do so has been given by or on behalf of the Administrative Director acting
on behalf of the College.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>In case of fire or other emergency requiring prompt protective
action, or in the event that the competent Host State authorities have reasonable
cause to believe that such an emergency has occurred or is about to occur
in the Headquarters, the consent of the Administrative Director, on behalf
of the College, to entry into the Headquarters shall be presumed if the Administrative
Director cannot be reached in time.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al>Eurojust may expel or exclude persons from the Headquarters for
breach of its regulations.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr>
            <al>The Administrative Director, on behalf of the College, shall prevent
the Headquarters from being used to harbor persons who are avoiding arrest
under any law of the Kingdom of the Netherlands, who are wanted by the Government
for extradition to another country, or who are endeavouring to evade service
of legal process.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">4</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Protection of the Headquarters</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>The Host State shall exercise due diligence to ensure that the security
and tranquility of the Headquarters are not impaired by any person or group
of persons attempting unauthorised entry into the Headquarters, or creating
disturbances in its immediate vicinity. As may be required for this purpose,
the Host State authorities shall provide adequate police protection on the
boundaries and in the vicinity of the Headquarters.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">5</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Special Services to the Headquarters</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>The Host State authorities shall exercise, as far as it is within
their competence, and to the extent requested by the Administrative Director
on behalf of the College, the respective powers to ensure that the Headquarters
shall be supplied, on fair conditions and on equitable terms, with the necessary
services including, among others, electricity, water, sewerage, gas, post,
telephone, telegraph, local transportation, drainage, collection of refuse,
fire protection and snow removal from public streets.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>In case of any interruption or threatened interruption of any
such services, Eurojust shall be accorded the priority given to essential
agencies and organs of the Government and the Government shall take steps
accordingly to ensure that the work of Eurojust is not prejudiced.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al>The Administrative Director, on behalf of the College, shall,
upon request, make suitable arrangements to enable duly authorised representatives
of the appropriate public service bodies to inspect, repair, maintain, reconstruct
or relocate utilities, conduits, mains and sewers within the Headquarters
under conditions which shall not unreasonably disturb the carrying out of
the functions of Eurojust. Underground work may be undertaken in the Headquarters
only after consultation with the Administrative Director on behalf of the
College, and under conditions which shall not disturb the carrying out of
the functions of Eurojust.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">6</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Law and Authority in the Headquarters</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>The Headquarters shall be under the control and authority of Eurojust,
as provided in this Agreement.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>Except as otherwise provided in this Agreement, in the Eurojust
Decision or in the acts and regulations based on the Eurojust Decision, the
laws and regulations of the Host State shall apply to the Headquarters as
far as they do not interfere with Eurojust&#x2019;s functioning.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">7</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Facilities and Immunities of Eurojust in Respect of Communication</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>The Government shall permit Eurojust to communicate freely and
without a need for special permission, for all official purposes, and shall
protect the right of Eurojust to do so. Eurojust and its National Members
shall have the right to use codes and to dispatch and receive official correspondence
and other official communications by courier or in sealed bags which shall
have the same privileges and immunities as diplomatic couriers and bags.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>Eurojust shall, as far as may be compatible with the International
Telecommunication Convention of 6 November 1982, for its official communications,
enjoy treatment not less favourable than that accorded by the Kingdom of the
Netherlands to any international organisation or State, in the matter of priorities
for communication by mail, cable, telegraph, telex, radio, television, telephone,
fax, satellite, or other means.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al>Eurojust may install and use a wireless transmitter with the consent
of the Government, which consent shall not be unreasonably withheld once the
wavelength has been agreed upon.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">8</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Exemption from Taxes and Duties for Eurojust and its Property</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>Within the scope of its official activities, Eurojust, its assets,
income and other property shall be exempt from all direct taxes levied by
the Host State authorities.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>Within the scope of its official activities, Eurojust shall be
exempt from:</al>
            <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
              <li>
                <li.nr>a)</li.nr>
                <al>import taxes and duties (&#x2018;&#x2018;belastingen
bij invoer&#x2019;&#x2019;);</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>b)</li.nr>
                <al>motor vehicle tax (&#x2018;&#x2018;motorrijtuigenbelasting&#x2019;&#x2019;, &#x2018;&#x2018;MRB&#x2019;&#x2019;);</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>c)</li.nr>
                <al>tax on passenger motor vehicles and motorcycles
(&#x2018;&#x2018;belasting van personenauto&#x2019;s en motorrijwielen&#x2019;&#x2019;, &#x2018;&#x2018;BPM&#x2019;&#x2019;);</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>d)</li.nr>
                <al>value added tax (&#x2018;&#x2018;omzetbelasting&#x2019;&#x2019;, &#x2018;&#x2018;BTW&#x2019;&#x2019;)
paid on goods and services supplied on a recurring basis or involving considerable
expenditure;</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>e)</li.nr>
                <al>excise duties (&#x2018;&#x2018;accijnzen&#x2019;&#x2019;)
included in the price of alcoholic  beverages and hydrocarbons such as fuel
oils and motor fuels;</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>f)</li.nr>
                <al>real property transfer tax (&#x2018;&#x2018;overdrachtsbelasting&#x2019;&#x2019;);</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>g)</li.nr>
                <al>insurance tax (&#x2018;&#x2018;assurantiebelasting&#x2019;&#x2019;);</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>h)</li.nr>
                <al>energy tax (&#x2018;&#x2018;regulerende energiebelasting&#x2019;&#x2019;, &#x2018;&#x2018;REB&#x2019;&#x2019;);</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>i)</li.nr>
                <al>tax on water mains (&#x2018;&#x2018;belasting
op leidingwater&#x2019;&#x2019;, &#x2018;&#x2018;BOL&#x2019;&#x2019;); and</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>j)</li.nr>
                <al>any other taxes and duties of a substantially
similar character as the taxes provided for in this paragraph, imposed by
the Kingdom of the Netherlands subsequent to the date of signature of this
Agreement.</al>
              </li>
            </lijst>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al>The exemption provided for in subparagraphs 2d), e), f), g), h),
i) and j) of this Article may be granted by way of a refund.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr>
            <al>Goods acquired or imported under the terms set out in paragraph
2 shall not be sold, loaned, given away or otherwise disposed of, except in
accordance with conditions agreed upon with the Government.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">5</lidnr>
            <al>No exemption will be granted in respect of taxes and duties which
represent charges for specific services rendered.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">9</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Flag, Emblem and Markings</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>Eurojust shall be entitled to display its flag, emblem and markings in
the Headquarters, and to display its flag on vehicles used for official purposes. </al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">10</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Entry, Stay and Departure</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>The Government shall facilitate, if necessary, the entry, stay
and departure for purposes of official business of the persons listed below
and members of the family forming part of their household:</al>
            <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
              <li>
                <li.nr>a)</li.nr>
                <al>the national members and the assistants,</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>b)</li.nr>
                <al>the Administrative Director,</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>c)</li.nr>
                <al>the staff,</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>d)</li.nr>
                <al>the members of the Joint Supervisory Body,</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>e)</li.nr>
                <al>other persons, on request of the Administrative
Director.</al>
              </li>
            </lijst>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>This Article shall not prevent the requirement of reasonable evidence
to be provided by Eurojust to establish that persons claiming the treatment
provided for in this Article fall under one of the categories referred to
in paragraph 1.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al>Visas which may be required by persons referred to in this Article
shall be granted without charge and as promptly as possible.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">11</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Privileges and Immunities of a National Member Granted by the  Government</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>A national member, not being the Dutch national member, shall
be accorded:</al>
            <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
              <li>
                <li.nr>a)</li.nr>
                <al><nadruk type="cur">mutatis mutandis,</nadruk> the privileges and immunities as referred to in Article 2, paragraph 3, and
Article 7 of this Agreement; and</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>b)</li.nr>
                <al>the privileges and immunities, exemptions
and facilities accorded to heads of diplomatic missions accredited to the
Kingdom of the Netherlands in accordance with the Vienna Convention.</al>
              </li>
            </lijst>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>The members of the family forming part of the household of a national
member referred to in paragraph 1, not having the Dutch nationality or not
permanently resident, shall enjoy the privileges and immunities, exemptions
and facilities accorded to members of the family forming part of the household
of heads of diplomatic missions under the Vienna Convention.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al>The privileges granted in accordance with paragraphs 1 and 2 relating
to the exemptions from direct taxes shall only apply where a national member
and the members of the family forming part of his household are considered
by the seconding Member State as a fiscal resident in that Member State.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr>
            <al>In case a Member State, other than the Kingdom of the Netherlands,
nominates a person with the Dutch nationality or permanently resident in the
Netherlands as its national member, the Government and Eurojust shall mutually
agree upon the privileges and immunities to be granted to the national member
concerned.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">12</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Privileges and Immunities of the Dutch National Member Granted  by
the Government</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>The Dutch national member, acting in accordance with Article 7 of the
Eurojust Decision, shall enjoy:</al>
          <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
            <li>
              <li.nr>a)</li.nr>
              <al>immunity from legal process of any kind
in respect of words spoken or written and of acts performed, such immunity
to continue notwithstanding that the person concerned is no longer the Dutch
national member; and</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>b)</li.nr>
              <al>inviolability for all his official papers,
documents and other official materials and immunity from inspection and seizure
of his official luggage.</al>
            </li>
          </lijst>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">13</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Privileges and Immunities of an Assistant Granted by the Government</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>An assistant, not having the Dutch nationality or not permanently
resident in the Kingdom of the Netherlands, who is in the service of the seconding
Member State according to Article 2, paragraph 2, of the Eurojust Decision,
shall enjoy:</al>
            <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
              <li>
                <li.nr>a)</li.nr>
                <al>the privileges and immunities referred to
in Article 11, paragraph 1a); and</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>b)</li.nr>
                <al>the privileges and immunities, exemptions
and facilities accorded to diplomatic agents accredited to the Kingdom of
the Netherlands under the Vienna Convention.</al>
              </li>
            </lijst>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>An assistant, having the Dutch nationality or permanently resident
in the Kingdom of the Netherlands, shall enjoy the following privileges and
immunities:</al>
            <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
              <li>
                <li.nr>a)</li.nr>
                <al>immunity from legal process of any kind
in respect of words spoken or written, and of acts performed, in the exercise
of his official function, such immunity to continue notwithstanding that the
person concerned is no longer an assistant; and</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>b)</li.nr>
                <al>inviolability for all his official papers,
documents and other official materials and immunity from inspection and seizure
of his official luggage;</al>
              </li>
            </lijst>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al>The members of the family forming part of the household of an
assistant referred to in paragraph 1, not having the Dutch nationality or
not permanently resident, shall enjoy the privileges and immunities, exemptions
and facilities accorded to the members of the family forming part of the household
of diplomatic agents under the Vienna Convention.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr>
            <al>The privileges granted in accordance with paragraphs 1 and 3 relating
to the exemptions from direct taxes shall only apply where an assistant or
a member of the family forming part of his household is considered by the
seconding Member State as a fiscal resident in that Member State.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">14</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Administrative Director and Staff</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>In accordance with Article 30 of the Eurojust Decision, it is
hereby affirmed that Articles 12 to 16 and 18 of the Protocol are applicable
to the Administrative Director and to the staff.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>In addition to the privileges and immunities specified in paragraph
1 of this Article, for the social security scheme conducted under the authority
of Eurojust, the Administrative Director and the Staff to whom the above-mentioned
scheme applies shall be exempt from all compulsory contributions to the social
security organisations of the Kingdom of the Netherlands. Consequently, they
shall not be covered by the social security regulations of the Kingdom of
the Netherlands.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al>The provisions of paragraph 2 of this Article shall apply, mutatis
mutandis, to spouses and dependent relatives forming part of the household
of the Administrative Director and Staff, unless they are employed in the
Kingdom of the Netherlands by an employer other than Eurojust or receive social
security benefits from the Kingdom of the Netherlands.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">15</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Members of the Joint Supervisory Body</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>A member of the Joint Supervisory Body shall within and with respect to
the Kingdom of the Netherlands, while exercising his function and in the course
of his journeys to and from the place of meeting, enjoy the following privileges
and immunities:</al>
          <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
            <li>
              <li.nr>a)</li.nr>
              <al>immunity from legal process of any kind
in respect of words spoken or written, and of acts performed by him, in the
exercise of his official functions, such immunity to continue notwithstanding
that the person concerned is no longer a member of the Joint Supervisory Body;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>b)</li.nr>
              <al>inviolability for all his official papers,
documents and other official materials;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>c)</li.nr>
              <al>the same facilities regarding his personal
luggage as those accorded to the officials of foreign States on temporary
official missions; and</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>d)</li.nr>
              <al>the right, for the purpose of all communications
with Eurojust, to use codes and to dispatch or receive papers, correspondence
or other official material by courier or in sealed bags. </al>
            </li>
          </lijst>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">16</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">National Correspondents and Representatives of Third States  and Other
Entities</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>A national correspondent, a representative of an entity as referred to
in Article 26 of the Eurojust Decision, a representative of a third State
or of an entity as referred to in Article 27, paragraph 3, of the Eurojust
Decision, who has been invited by Eurojust on official business, shall enjoy
within and with respect to the Kingdom of the Netherlands the following privileges
and immunities as far as may be deemed necessary for the effective performance
of his functions and during his travel in connection with service on such
missions, committees or subsidiary bodies, and during attendance at such meetings:</al>
          <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
            <li>
              <li.nr>a)</li.nr>
              <al>immunity from legal process of any kind
in respect of words spoken or written, and of acts performed by him in the
exercise of his official functions, such immunity to continue notwithstanding
that the person concerned is no longer employed for missions, serving on committees
of, or acting as consultant for Eurojust, or is no longer present at the Headquarters
or attending meetings convened by Eurojust;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>b)</li.nr>
              <al>inviolability for all his official papers,
documents and other official materials;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>c)</li.nr>
              <al>the same immunities and facilities with
respect to his personal luggage as those accorded to members, having comparable
rank, of the staff of diplomatic missions established in the Kingdom of the
Netherlands;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>d)</li.nr>
              <al>the same privileges with respect to currency
and exchange restrictions as those accorded to representatives of foreign
States on temporary official missions;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>e)</li.nr>
              <al>the same protection and repatriation facilities
as those accorded in time of international crisis to members, having comparable
rank, of the staff of diplomatic missions established in the Kingdom of the
Netherlands;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>f)</li.nr>
              <al>the right, for the purpose of all communications
with Eurojust, to use codes and to dispatch or receive papers, correspondence
or other official material by courier or in sealed bags; and</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>g)</li.nr>
              <al>if necessary, exemption from alien restrictions
and alien registrations.</al>
            </li>
          </lijst>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">17</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Employment</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>Members of the family forming part of the household of national members,
assistants, the Administrative Director and staff shall be granted, if necessary
and in accordance with the provisions set out in the Annex, work permits in
the Kingdom of the Netherlands for the duration of the secondment of the national
member or the assistant, or for the duration of the employment of the Administrative
Director or a member of the staff with Eurojust in the Kingdom of the Netherlands.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">18</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Additional Provisions on Privileges and Immunities</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>The privileges and immunities granted under the provisions of
this Agreement are conferred in the interest of Eurojust and not for the personal
benefit of the individuals themselves. It is the duty of Eurojust and all
persons enjoying such privileges and immunities to observe in all other respects
the laws and regulations of the Kingdom of the Netherlands.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>Eurojust shall co-operate at all times with the appropriate Host
State authorities to facilitate the proper administration of justice and shall
prevent any abuse of the privileges and immunities granted under the provisions
of this Agreement.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al>Should the Government consider that an abuse of a privilege or
immunity conferred by this Agreement has occurred, the College shall, upon
request, consult with the appropriate Host State authorities to decide whether
any such abuse has occurred. If such consultations fail to achieve a satisfactory
result to both the College and the Government, the matter shall be settled
according to the procedure set out in Article 23.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr>
            <al>The immunity granted to Eurojust shall not extend to civil action
by a third party for damages, including personal injury or death, arising
from a traffic accident caused by Eurojust. The execution of any measure taken
in the implementation of this paragraph shall be subject to a waiver in accordance
with Article 19.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">5</lidnr>
            <al>The immunity granted to any person on the basis of this Agreement
shall not extend to civil action by a third party for damages, including personal
injury or death, arising from a traffic accident caused by such a person and
shall not apply to traffic offences.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">19</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Waiver of Immunities</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>The College shall be required to waive the immunity of Eurojust,
a national member, an assistant, any person referred to in Article 16 or,
where appropriate, a member of the family forming part of the household of
any person enjoying privileges and immunities on the basis of this Agreement,
where such immunity would impede the course of justice and provided such immunity
can be waived without prejudice to the interests of Eurojust. </al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>The Joint Supervisory Body shall be required to waive the immunity
of one of its members where the use of immunity would impede the course of
justice and provided such immunity can be waived without prejudice to the
interests of Eurojust or the Joint Supervisory Body.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al>When the immunity of Eurojust as mentioned in Article 2 has been
waived, searches and seizures ordered by the judicial authorities of the Kingdom
of the Netherlands shall be effected in the presence of the President of the
College or a person delegated by him, and in compliance with the rules of
confidentiality laid down in or by virtue of the Eurojust Decision.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">20</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Protection of Persons</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>Host State authorities shall, if so requested by Eurojust, take all reasonable
steps to ensure the necessary safety and protection of the persons mentioned
in this Agreement whose security is endangered due to their services to Eurojust.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">21</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Notification</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>Eurojust shall promptly notify the Government of:</al>
            <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
              <li>
                <li.nr>a)</li.nr>
                <al>the arrival and departure of national members
and assistants,</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>b)</li.nr>
                <al>the arrival and departure of the Administrative
Director and of the staff members, and</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>c)</li.nr>
                <al>the arrival and final departure of members
of the family forming part of the household of the persons referred to in
Article 11, paragraph 1, Article 13, paragraph 1, and Article 14, and, where
appropriate, domestic servants. Eurojust shall also periodically provide the
Government with a list of the persons referred to under subparagraphs a) and
b).</al>
              </li>
            </lijst>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>Eurojust shall provide the Government with a list of the members
of the Joint Supervisory Body and with a list of national correspondents,
and shall revise these lists from time to time as may be necessary.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al>The Government shall issue to the persons referred to in paragraph
1 an identification card bearing the photograph of the holder. The identification
card shall serve to identify the holder to the Host State authorities.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr>
            <al>Upon termination of the function of a person referred to in paragraph
1a) and b), his identification card and any identification card issued to
a member of his family forming part of his household shall be returned by
Eurojust within a reasonable period. </al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">22</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Interpretation of the Agreement</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>This Agreement shall be interpreted in the light of its primary
purpose, that is to enable Eurojust at its Headquarters in the Kingdom of
the Netherlands to discharge fully and efficiently its responsibilities and
fulfill its purposes.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>In case of any conflict between the Eurojust Decision and this
Agreement, the Eurojust Decision shall prevail.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">23</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Settlement of Disputes</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>Any dispute between Eurojust and the Government concerning the
interpretation or application of this Agreement, and any question affecting
the Headquarters or the relationship between Eurojust and the Government,
which is not settled amicably, shall at the request of either Party to the
dispute be referred to a tribunal of three arbitrators for final decision.
Each Party shall appoint one arbitrator. The third arbitrator, who shall be
chairman of the tribunal, is to be chosen by the first two arbitrators.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>If one of the parties fails to appoint an arbitrator within two
months following a request from the other Party to make such an appointment,
the other Party may request the President of the Court of Justice of the European
Communities or, in his absence, the Vice-President, to make such an appointment.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al>Should the first two arbitrators fail to agree upon the third
arbitrator within two months following their appointment, either Party may
request the President of the Court of Justice of the European Communities
or, in his absence, the Vice-President, to make such an appointment.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr>
            <al>Unless the parties agree otherwise, the tribunal shall determine
its own procedure.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">5</lidnr>
            <al>The tribunal shall reach its decision by a majority of votes.
The chairman shall have a casting vote. The decision shall be final and binding
on the parties to the dispute.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">24</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Termination of the Agreement</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>This Agreement shall cease to be in force following mutual consent
of Eurojust and the Government. </al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>In the event of the Headquarters of Eurojust being removed from
the territory of the Kingdom of the Netherlands, this Agreement shall expire
after a certain period to be determined by mutual consent considering thereby
the time necessary for such transfer and for the disposal of the property
of Eurojust in the Kingdom of the Netherlands.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al>Notwithstanding the previous paragraphs, this Agreement shall
remain in force with regard to any event that has occurred before its date
of expiry.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">25</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Amendments</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>The Parties shall at the request of either of them enter into consultations
regarding the amendment of this Agreement.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">26</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Entry into Force</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al>This Agreement shall enter into force on the first day of the
first month following the date of signature by both Parties.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al>With respect to the Kingdom of the Netherlands, this Agreement
shall apply to the part of the Kingdom in Europe only.</al>
          </lid>
          
          
          
          
          
        </artikel>
        
      </wettekst>
      <wetsluiting status="goed">
        <slotformulering>
          <al>DONE at The Hague on 15 March 2006, in two copies in the English language.</al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">For the Kingdom of the Netherlands</nadruk>
          </al>
          <al>ATZO NICOLA&#xCF;</al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">For Eurojust</nadruk>
          </al>
          <al>M. KENNEDY</al>
        </slotformulering>
      </wetsluiting>
    </verdragtekst>
    <verdragtekst>
      <kop>
        
      <titel status="officieel">Annex as referred to in Article 17 of the Agreement between the Kingdom of the
Netherlands and Eurojust</titel></kop>
      <vrije-tekst>
        <tekst status="goed">
          
          <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
            <li>
              <li.nr>1.</li.nr>
              <al>Members of the family forming part of the household of national
members, assistants, the Administrative Director and staff shall be authorised
to engage in gainful employment in the Netherlands for the duration of the
term of office of a national member, an assistant, the Administrative Director
and a member of the staff concerned. </al>
            </li><li>
              <li.nr>2.</li.nr>
              <al>The following persons are members of the family forming part of
the household in the sense of paragraph 1:</al>
            <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>a)</li.nr><al>the spouse or the registered partner of
a national member, an assistant, the Administrative Director or a member of
the staff;</al></li><li><li.nr>b)</li.nr><al>children of a national member, an assistant,
the Administrative Director or a member of the staff who are under the age
of 24;</al></li><li><li.nr>c)</li.nr><al>children of a national member, an assistant,
the Administrative Director or a member of the staff who are aged 24 or over,
but not older than 27, provided that they formed part of the household of
national members, assistants, the Administrative Director and staff concerned
prior to their first entry into the Netherlands and still form part of this
household, and that they are unmarried, financially dependent on the national
member, the assistant, the Administrative Director or the member of the staff
concerned and are attending education in the Netherlands.</al></li></lijst></li>
            
          <li>
              <li.nr>3.</li.nr>
              <al>Persons mentioned in paragraph 2 who obtain gainful employment
shall enjoy no immunity from criminal, civil or administrative jurisdiction
with respect to matters arising in the course of or in connection with such
employment. However, any measures of execution shall be taken without infringing
the inviolability of their person or of their residence, if they are entitled
to such inviolability.</al>
            </li><li>
              <li.nr>4.</li.nr>
              <al>In case of the insolvency of a person aged under 24 with respect
to a claim arising out of gainful employment of that person, the immunity
of the national member, the assistant, the Administrative Director or the
member of the staff of whose family the person concerned is a member shall
be waived for the purpose of settlement of the claim, in accordance with the
provisions of Article 19 of the Seat Agreement.</al>
            </li><li>
              <li.nr>5.</li.nr>
              <al>The employment referred to in paragraph 1 shall be in accordance
with Netherlands legislation, including fiscal and social security legislation,
unless any other international legal instrument provides otherwise.</al>
            </li></lijst>
          
          
        </tekst>
      </vrije-tekst>
    </verdragtekst>
  </verdrag>
  
</wetgeving>
  	