<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE wetgeving SYSTEM "http://wetten.overheid.nl/dtd/bwb-plus-meta-1_61w.dtd">
<wetgeving bwb-id="BWBV0005805" dtdversie="2.0" id="10000052799" verdragnummer="007912" xml:lang="en" soort="verdrag">
  
  
  
  <intitule>Briefwisseling tussen de Nederlandse en de Amerikaanse Regering houdende uitvoering van artikel III van de Overeenkomst tot economische samenwerking tussen de Regeringen van het Koninkrijk der Nederlanden en de Verenigde Staten van Amerika</intitule>
  
  <verdrag status="goed" tekst="authentiek" xml:lang="en"><verdragtekst><kop><label>No</label><nr status="officieel">I</nr></kop><vrije-tekst><tekst status="goed"><al>DEPARTMENT OF STATE</al><al>Washington</al><al>September 24, 1952</al><al>Sir:</al><al>I have the honor to refer to the conversations which have recently
taken place between representatives of our two Governments relating to Article III of the Economic Cooperation Agreement between the
United States of America and the Kingdom of the Netherlands, signed
at The Hague, on July 2, 1948, as heretofore amended or supplemented.
As a consequence of those conversations, the Government of
the United States of America proposes the following agreement to
the Government of the Kingdom of the Netherlands:</al><al>The Governments of the Kingdom of the Netherlands and of the
United States of America will, upon the request of either of them,
consult respecting projects in the Kingdom of the Netherlands proposed
by nationals of the United States of America with regard to
which guaranties under Section 111 (b) (3) of the Economic Cooperation
Act of 1948, as heretofore amended, have been made or are
under consideration. With respect to such guaranties extending to
projects which are approved by the Government of the Kingdom of
the Netherlands in accordance with the provisions of the aforesaid
Section, the Government of the Kingdom of the Netherlands agrees:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>a.</li.nr><al>That if the Government of the United States of America makes
payment in United States dollars to any person under any such
guaranty, the Government of the Kingdom of the Netherlands will
recognize the transfer to the United States of America of any right,
title or interest of such person in assets, currency, credits, or other
property on account of which such payment was made and the
subrogation of the United States of America to any claim or cause
of action of such person arising in connection therewith. The Government
of the Kingdom of the Netherlands shall also recognize any
transfer to the Government of the United States of America pursuant
to such guaranty of any compensation for loss covered by such
guaranties received from any source other than the Government of
the United States of America;</al></li><li><li.nr>b.</li.nr><al>That any claim against the Government of the Kingdom of
the Netherlands to which the Government of the United States of
America may be subrogated as the result of any payment under a
guaranty shall be deemed to be an espoused claim subject to the
procedures provided in Article X of the aforesaid Economic Cooperation
Agreement, whether or not the condition stated in paragraph 3
of said Article X has been satisfied; provided, however, that such
payment is made only after the recipient of the payment has taken
reasonable measures to pursue any judicial or administrative remedies
which may be available in connection with its claim for a period of
at least one year from the initiation of the action on account of which
the payment is made;</al></li><li><li.nr>c.</li.nr><al>That any guilders acquired by the Government of the United
States of America pursuant to the terms of any such guaranty shall
be accorded treatment with respect to convertibility which is not less
favorable than the treatment which would have been accorded to the
holder of the guaranty and that the Government of the United States of America shall be permitted freely to use guilders thus acquired
for its administrative expenditures.</al></li></lijst><al>If this proposal is acceptable to the Government of the Kingdom
of the Netherlands, it is suggested that you reply by note. This note,
together with such reply, will constitute an agreement between our
two Governments on this subject, the agreement to enter into force
on the date of receipt of your reply note.</al><al>Accept, Excellency, the renewed assurances of my highest consideration.</al><al>For the Secretary of State:</al><al>(Sd.) JAMES C. H. BONBRIGHT</al><al><nadruk type="cur">His Excellency</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur">Dr. J. Herman van Roijen,</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur">Ambassador of the Netherlands.</nadruk></al></tekst></vrije-tekst></verdragtekst><verdragtekst xml:lang="en"><kop><label>No.</label><nr status="officieel">II</nr></kop><vrije-tekst><tekst status="goed"><al>EMBASSY OF THE NETHERLANDS</al><al>Washington, October 7, 1952</al><al>Sir:</al><al>I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of your note of
September 24th, 1952, reading as follows:</al><al><redactie type="extra">(zoals in No. I)</redactie></al><al>I have the honor to state that the Government of the Kingdom
of the Netherlands accepts the proposed agreement as outlined in
your above-mentioned note and considers that your note and this
reply constitute an agreement between the two Governments on this
subject, the agreement to enter into force on the date of receipt of
this reply note.</al><al>Accept, Sir, the renewed assurances of my highest consideration.</al><al>(Sd.) J. H. VAN ROIJEN</al><al><nadruk type="cur">The Honorable Dean Acheson,</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur">Secretary of State,</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur">Washington, D.C.</nadruk></al></tekst></vrije-tekst></verdragtekst></verdrag></wetgeving>
  	