<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE wetgeving SYSTEM "http://wetten.overheid.nl/dtd/bwb-plus-meta-1_61w.dtd">
<wetgeving bwb-id="BWBV0001163" id="10000002619" verdragnummer="006022" soort="verdrag">
  <intitule>Notawisseling tussen de Nederlandse en de Italiaanse Regering
    houdende een verdrag inzake voorrechten en immuniteiten te verlenen aan
    verbindingsambtenaren en andere personeelsleden die vanwege de Italiaanse
    Regering bij de Europol Drugs Eenheid te 's-Gravenhage worden tewerkgesteld</intitule>
  
  <verdrag tekst="authentiek" xml:lang="en">
    <verdragtekst>
      
      <kop>
        <label>Nr.</label><nr>1</nr>
      </kop>
      <vrije-tekst>
        <tekst status="goed"><al><redactie type="extra">(Op 1 december 1994 aan het Italiaanse Ministerie van Buitenlandse
            Zaken gezonden)</redactie></al>
          <tussenkop>ROM/PA-103581</tussenkop>
          <tussenkop>Note verbale</tussenkop>
          <al>The Royal Netherlands Embassy presents its compliments to the
            Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Italy and with
            reference to the Ministerial Agreement establishing the Europol
            Drugs Unit, adopted by the TREVI Ministers during their meeting in
            Copenhagen on 1 and 2 June 1993, and to the decision of the European
            Council of 29 October 1993 that Europol should have its seat in The
            Hague, and pending the establishment of Europol by treaty, has the
            honour to propose the following on behalf of the Government of the
            Kingdom of the Netherlands.</al></tekst><artikel status="goed"><kop><nr>1</nr></kop><al>Liaison officers and other members of staff who are employed at
            the Europol Drugs Unit in The Hague on behalf of the Government of
            Italy under the afore-mentioned Ministerial Agreement and who settle
            in the Netherlands for that reason, and members of their family who
            form part of their household and who do not possess Dutch
            nationality, shall enjoy the privileges and immunities in and
            vis-&#xE0;-vis the Kingdom of the Netherlands that accrue to members of
            the administrative and technical staff of diplomatic missions
            established in the Netherlands under the Vienna Convention on
            Diplomatic Relations of 18 April 1961, except that the immunities
            shall not extend to damage caused by a vehicle or other means of
            transport belonging to or driven by them, nor to traffic offences
            and that the immunity from criminal jurisdiction shall not extend to
            acts performed outside the course of their duties.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><nr>2</nr></kop><al>The obligations of Sending States and their personnel that
            apply under the Vienna Convention to members of the administrative
            and technical staff of diplomatic missions established in the
            Netherlands shall apply to the persons referred to at <intref status="actief" doc="1.0:v:BWBV0001163&amp;artikel=1">1</intref>.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><nr>3</nr></kop><al>The Government of the Kingdom of the Netherlands shall, upon
            request, supply the persons referred to at <intref status="actief" doc="1.0:v:BWBV0001163&amp;artikel=1">1.</intref> with an identity card
            showing their status.</al></artikel><tekst status="goed"><al>The Embassy proposes that this note and the affirmative note of
            the Ministry of Foreign Affairs together shall constitute an
            agreement between the Government of the Kingdom of the Netherlands
            and the Government of Italy, which shall enter into force on the
            fifteenth day after the date of receipt of the affirmative note of
            the Ministry of Foreign Affairs and which shall remain in force for
            one year while, in case at the end of this term a treaty concerning
            the establishment of Europol is not in force, a further exchange of
            notes to prolong the agreement may be concluded.</al>
          <al>The Royal Netherlands Embassy avails itself of this opportunity to
            renew to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Italy
            the assurances of its highest consideration.</al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">Ministry of Foreign Affairs </nadruk>
          </al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">of the Republic of Italy </nadruk>
          </al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">Rome</nadruk>
          </al></tekst>
      </vrije-tekst>
    </verdragtekst>
  <verdragtekst><kop><label>Nr.</label><nr>II</nr></kop><vrije-tekst><tekst status="goed">
          
          
          
          
          
          
          <tussenkop>MINISTERO DEGLI AFFARI ESTERI</tussenkop>
          
          <tussenkop>Note Verbale</tussenkop>
          <al>The Ministry of Foreign Affairs of Italy presents its compliments
            to the Embassy of the Kingdom of the Netherlands and has the honour
            to confirm receipt of <intref status="actief" doc="1.0:v:BWBV0001163&amp;verdragtekst=1">Embassy's note of 1 December 1994</intref> which
            read as follows:</al>
          <al><redactie type="extra">(zoals in Nr. I)</redactie></al>
          <al>The Ministry has the honour to inform the Embassy that the above
            proposals are acceptable to the Government of Italy and that the
            <intref status="actief" doc="1.0:v:BWBV0001163&amp;verdragtekst=1">note of the Embassy</intref> and this affirmative note constitute an
            Agreement between the Government of the Kingdom of the Netherlands
            and the Government of Italy which shall enter into force on the
            fiftheenth day after the date of receipt by the Embassy of this note
            and which shall remain in force for one year while, in case at the
            end of this term a treaty concerning the establishment of Europol is
            not in force, a further exchange of notes to prolong the Agreement
            may be concluded.</al>
          <al>The Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of Italy avails
            itself of this opportunity to renew to the Royal Netherlands Embassy
            the assurances of its highest consideration.</al>
          <al>Rome, 24 gen. 1995 </al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">Royal Netherlands Embassy  </nadruk>
          </al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">Rome</nadruk>
          </al>
        </tekst></vrije-tekst></verdragtekst></verdrag>
</wetgeving>
  	