<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE wetgeving SYSTEM "http://wetten.overheid.nl/dtd/bwb-plus-meta-1_61w.dtd">
<wetgeving bwb-id="BWBV0001897" dtdversie="2.0" id="10000013679" verdragnummer="010222" soort="verdrag">
  
  <intitule>Verdrag inzake luchtvervoer tussen de lidstaten en geassocieerde leden
van de Associatie van Cara&#xEF;bische Staten</intitule>
  
  
  
  <verdrag tekst="authentiek" xml:lang="en">
    <verdragtekst>
      <kop>
        <titel status="officieel">Air Transport agreement among the Member States and Associate
Members of the Association of Caribbean States</titel>
      </kop>
      <aanhef><preambule><al>Preamble</al><al>The States, Countries and territories referred to in Article IV of the
Convention Establishing the Association of Caribbean States (ACS), done at
Cartagena de Indias, Republic of Colombia on July 24, 1994 considering the
Plans of Action adopted by the Heads of State and/or Government of the States,
Countries and Territories of the Association of Caribbean States at the 2nd Summit in Santo Domingo, Dominican Republic;      </al><al>Bearing in mind the decision to promote the Programme adopted by the ACS
and entitled ``Uniting the Caribbean by Air and Sea";</al><al>Expressing the willingness to create the legal framework necessary for
the establishment of the Sustainable Tourism Zone in the Caribbean region;</al><al>Conscious of the need for airlines of the Member States and Associate
Members to offer the traveling and shipping public a variety of air service
options;</al><al>Determined to ensure the highest degree of operational safety and security
in international civil aviation;</al><al>Recognizing the need for a general aviation policy for the Association
of Caribbean States by which Member States and Associate Member States may
be guided in their aviation arrangements;</al><al>Recognizing the importance of the Convention on International Civil Aviation
opened for signature in Chicago on December 7, 1944, as the principal regulatory
instrument for the conduct of international civil aviation;</al><al>Have agreed as follows:</al></preambule></aanhef><wettekst>
        
        
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">1</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Definitions</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid><lidnr status="officieel">A</lidnr><al>For the purposes of this Agreement, unless otherwise stated, the term: </al>
          <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
            <li>
              <li.nr>1.</li.nr>
              <al> ``Parties" means the Member States and Associate Members of the Association
of Caribbean States or States that may conclude treaties on behalf of the
Associate Members, which have signed and have deposited their instruments
of ratification or accession with the Depository in accordance with Article
24 of this Agreement;</al>
            </li>
          <li>
              <li.nr>2.</li.nr>
              <al> ``Agreement" means this Agreement, its annexes, and any amendments
thereto which have entered into force for the Parties, in accordance of the
relevant provisions with this Agreement;</al>
            </li><li>
              <li.nr>3.</li.nr>
              <al> ``Convention" means Convention on the International Civil Aviation,
opened for signature in Chicago on December 7, 1944, and includes:</al>
            <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
            <li>
              <li.nr>a)</li.nr>
              <al>Any amendment that has entered into force
under Article 94a) of the Convention, which is in force among the Parties;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>b)</li.nr>
              <al>Any annex or any amendment thereto adopted
under Article 90 of the Convention, insofar as such annex or amendment is
at any given time effective for the Parties;</al>
            </li>
          </lijst></li><li>
              <li.nr>4.</li.nr>
              <al> ``Territory" means the land areas, archipelagic waters and adjacent
territorial waters under the sovereignty and jurisdiction of a Party in the
ACS Region, according to the International Laws;</al>
            </li><li>
              <li.nr>5.</li.nr>
              <al> ``Aeronautical Authorities" means the Civil Aviation Authorities of
the Parties, or any other person or entity authorized to perform the functions
of these Authorities;</al>
            </li><li>
              <li.nr>6.</li.nr>
              <al> ``Designated airline(s)" means an airline authorized by the Aeronautical
Authorities of one of the Parties, in accordance with Article 3 of this Agreement;</al>
            </li><li>
              <li.nr>7.</li.nr>
              <al> ``International air transport" means air transport which passes through
the airspace over the territory of more than one State;</al>
            </li><li>
              <li.nr>8.</li.nr>
              <al> ``Air transport" means the public carriage by aircraft of passengers,
baggage, cargo, and mail, separately or in combination, for remuneration or
hire;</al>
            </li><li>
              <li.nr>9.</li.nr>
              <al> ``Tariff" means any price charged for the carriage of passengers and
their baggage and/or cargo excluding mail in air transport by airlines, including
their agents, and the conditions governing the availability of such price;</al>
            </li><li>
              <li.nr>10.</li.nr>
              <al> ``Full cost" means the cost of providing service and may include a
reasonable return on assets after depreciation;</al>
            </li><li>
              <li.nr>11.</li.nr>
              <al> ``Stop over" means a predetermined interruption in a journey, which
is continued with the same airline and document;</al>
            </li><li>
              <li.nr>12.</li.nr>
              <al> ``Stop for non-traffic purposes" means a landing for any purpose other
than taking on or disembarking of passengers, cargo or mail; </al>
            </li><li>
              <li.nr>13.</li.nr>
              <al> ``User fees" means any rate, tariff or tax charged for the use of
airport, air navigation or security facilities or services including related
services and installations.</al>
            </li></lijst></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">B</lidnr><al> Other terms should have the meaning assigned to them by the Convention.</al></lid>
          
          
          
          
          
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">2</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Granting of Rights</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al> Each Party grants to the other Parties the following rights for the
conduct of international air transport by the designated airlines of the other
Parties:</al>
            <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
              <li>
                <li.nr>a)</li.nr>
                <al>The right to fly across its territory without
landing;</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>b)</li.nr>
                <al>The right to make stops for non-traffic
purposes in its territory;</al>
              </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>c)</li.nr>
              <al>The right to operate third and fourth freedom
traffic rights separately or in combination, on regular flights of passengers,
cargo and mail;</al>
            </li><li>
              <li.nr>d)</li.nr>
              <al>In respect of the exercise of fifth freedom
traffic rights to scheduled flights for passengers, cargo and mail, separately
or in combination, within the ACS region, each Party shall select one of the
following options:</al>
            <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
            <li>
              <li.nr>(i)</li.nr>
              <al>The exercise of such rights among the Parties
concerned;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>(ii)</li.nr>
              <al>The exercise of such rights on the reciprocal
and liberal exchange of rights among the Parties concerned.</al>
            </li>
          </lijst></li></lijst>
          </lid>
          
          
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al> Following consultations in accordance with Article 15, a Party shall
have the right to temporally suspend fifth freedom operations when considered
detrimental to its national interest. Such suspension shall come into effect
ninety (90) days after the other Party has been notified in writing.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al> At the time of signing, ratification or accession to the Agreement
a Party shall indicate whether it elects to be bound by sub-paragraph 1.d.i
or subparagraph 1.d.ii of this Article. This election is without prejudice
to a Party that elects to be bound by sub-paragraph 1.d.ii subsequently indicating
to the depositary its wish to be bound by sub-paragraph 1.d.i of this Article.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr>
            <al> The Parties shall favourably consider requests by designated airlines
to operate non-scheduled passenger and/or cargo flights whenever these do
not affect nor constitute unfair competition for scheduled flights.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">5</lidnr>
            <al> For the purpose of promoting multi destination tourism the Parties
grant stop over rights and direct transit traffic between their territories
to the designated airlines. </al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">6</lidnr>
            <al> Nothing in this Article shall be understood to mean that a Party grants
to an airline of another Party the right of cabotage.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">3</nr>
            
          </kop>
          <tussenkop>A. Designation and Authorization</tussenkop><lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al> Each Party shall have the right to designate up to two airlines to
conduct the services agreed to in this Agreement and to withdraw or alter
such designation. The designation shall be transmitted to the other Party
in writing indicating whether the airline is authorized to conduct scheduled
or non-scheduled air transport services, or both.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al> Upon receipt of such designation and application from the designated
airline, in the form and manner prescribed for operating authorizations, the
Aeronautical Authorities of the other Party shall grant appropriate authorization
with minimum procedural delay, provided that:</al>
            <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
              <li>
                <li.nr>a)</li.nr>
                <al>Substantial ownership and effective control
of that airline are vested in one or more Parties, its or their nationals
or both; and</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>b)</li.nr>
                <al>The headquarters of the designated airline
are located in the territory of the Party designating the airline; and</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>c)</li.nr>
                <al>The designated airline is qualified to meet
the conditions prescribed under the laws and regulations normally applied
to the operation of international air transport by the Party considering the
application or applications; and</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>d)</li.nr>
                <al>The Party that designates the airline is
maintaining and administering the standards set forth in Article 6 and Article
7 of the Agreement.</al>
              </li>
            </lijst>
          </lid>
        <tussenkop>B. Community of Interest</tussenkop><al>The right of each Party to designate an airline or airlines shall include
designation in accordance with the Principle of Community of Interest as established
by the Intemational Civil Aviation Organization (ICAO). On receipt of such
designation and application from the designated airline in the form and manner
prescribed for operating authorization the Aeronautical Authorities shall,
without undue delay, grant the appropriate authorization provided the designated
airline complies with the provisions of paragraph 2 c of the present Article.</al><al>Once the designation is received, the responsibility for compliance with
Articles 6 and 7 of the Agreement remains with the Party issuing the air operator's
certificate to the designated airline.</al></artikel>
        
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">4</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Revocation, Suspension and Limitation of Authorization</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al> A Party may revoke, suspend or limit the operating authorizations or
technical permits of a designated airline where: </al>
            <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
              <li>
                <li.nr>a)</li.nr>
                <al>The airline no longer complies with the
requirements set forth in Article 3 Paragraph 2. a, b and c;</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>b)</li.nr>
                <al>The airline has failed to comply with the
laws and regulations referred to in Article 5 of the Agreement;</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>c)</li.nr>
                <al>The other Party is not maintaining and administering
the standards as set forth in Article 6 of the Agreement.</al>
              </li>
            </lijst>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al> Unless immediate action, is essential to prevent further non-compliance
with paragraph 1 b or c of this Article, the rights established by this Article
shall be exercised only after consultation with the Party concerned.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al> This Article does not limit the rights of a Party to withhold, revoke,
limit or impose conditions for the operating authorizations of an airline
or airlines of another Party in accordance with the provisions of Article
7 of the Agreement.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">5</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Enforcement of Laws</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al> While entering, remaining in or leaving the territory of a Party, its
laws and regulations relating to the operation and navigation of aircraft
shall be complied with by the designated airlines.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al> While entering, remaining in or leaving the territory of a Party, its
laws and regulations relating to the admission to or departure from its territory
of passengers, crew or cargo on aircraft (including regulations relating to
entry, clearance, aviation security, immigration, passports, customs and quarantine
or, in the case of mail, postal regulations) shall be complied with by, or
on behalf of such passengers, crew or cargo of the designated airlines, or
their representatives.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">6</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Safety</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al> The Parties shall adhere to the ICAO universal operational safety oversight
programme, and will therefore promote reciprocal cooperation and assistance
among Member States and Associate Members, particularly with regard to developing
the plan of action adopted in each case after periodic evaluation carried
out by ICAO.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al> If, upon publication of the ICAO report on the safety standards of
any Party, that Party does not, (within a reasonable time frame, agreed upon
between the Party and ICAO), apply corrective measures to guarantee that safety
standards are met, (and the deadlines provided for in the plan of action expires),
any Party can request consultation to urge that Party to observe the respective
standards.</al>
          <al>If after consultation no corrective measures are taken (and there has
been at least one month's prior notice in writing), either Party can suspend,
revoke or limit authorization granted to an airline or airlines designated
by the Party which has not taken appropriate corrective measures within a
reasonable period of time agreed upon by the Parties.</al></lid>
          
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al> A Party which for economic or technical reasons, finds difficulty in
complying with the provisions of paragraph 1 and 2, may request assistance
from any other Party, in meeting its safety obligations under this Article.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">7</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Security</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al> In accordance with their rights and obligations under international
law, the Parties reaffirm their obligation to each other to protect the security
of civil aviation against acts of unlawful interference. Without prejudice
to their rights and obligations under international law, the Parties shall
act particularly in accordance with the terms of the Convention on Offences
and Certain Other Acts Committed on Board Aircraft signed in Tokyo on 14 September
1963, the Convention for the Suppression of Unlawful Seizure of Aircraft,
signed at The Hague on 16 December 1970, the Convention for the Suppression
of Unlawful Acts against the Safety of Civil Aviation, signed at Montreal
on 23 September 1971, and the Protocol for the Suppression of Unlawful Acts
of Violence at Airports Serving International Civil Aviation signed at Montreal
on 24 February 1988, supplementary to the Montreal Convention of 1971.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al> The Parties shall provide upon request all necessary assistance to
each other to prevent acts of unlawful seizure of civil aircraft and other
unlawful acts against the safety of such aircraft, of their passengers and
crew, and of airports and air navigation facilities, and to address any other
threat to aviation security.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al> The Parties shall, in their mutual relations, act in conformity with
the aviation security provisions established by the International Civil Aviation
Organization and designated as Annexes to the Convention provided these security
provisions are applicable to the Parties; they shall require that operators
of aircraft of their registry, operators of aircraft who have their principal
place of business or permanent residence in their territory, and the operators
of airports in their territory act in conformity with such aviation security
provisions.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr>
            <al> Each Party agrees that these operators of aircraft can be requested
by the other Party to observe the security provisions mentioned in paragraph
3 of this Article for entry into, for departure from, and while within the
territory of the other Party and to take adequate measures to protect aircraft
and to inspect passengers, crew, and their baggage and carry-on items, as
well as cargo and aircraft stores, prior to and during boarding or loading.
A Party shall also give positive consideration to any request from another
Party for special security measures to meet a particular security threat.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">5</lidnr>
            <al> When an incident or threat of an incident of unlawful seizure of aircraft
or other unlawful acts against the security of passengers, crew, aircraft,
airports or air navigation facilities occurs, the Parties shall assist each
other by facilitating communications and other appropriate measures intended
to terminate rapidly and safely such incident or threat.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">6</lidnr>
            <al> When a Party has reasonable grounds to believe that another Party has
departed from the civil aviation security provisions of this Article, the
Aeronautical Authorities of that Party may request immediate actions by the
Aeronautical Authorities of the other Party. Failure to reach a satisfactory
agreement within 14 days from the date of such request and if required by
an emergency a Party may withhold, revoke, limit or impose conditions on the
operating authorization and technical permits of an airline or airlines of
that Party.</al>
          <al>The specific security concerns shall be subsequently subjected to the
procedures of Article 15 of the Agreement.</al></lid>
          
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">8</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Commercial Opportunities</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al> The designated airlines of a Party shall have the right to establish
offices in the territory of another Party for the promotion and sale of air
transport.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al> The designated airlines of a Party shall be entitled, in accordance
with the laws and regulations of other Parties relating to entry, residence,
and employment, to maintain in the territory of the other Parties managerial,
sales, technical, operational, and other specialist staff required for the
provision of air transport.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al> Air carriers can choose freely from among the different ground handling
services available, and any charge must be reasonable, based on costs and
on fair, uniform and non-discriminatory treatment.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr>
            <al> A designated airline shall have the right to convert and transfer on
demand net revenues obtained from the sale of the air transport services.</al>
          <al>Conversion and transference shall be permitted promptly without restrictions
or taxation in respect thereof at the rate of exchange applicable to current
transactions on the date the carrier makes the initial application for remittance,
according to the legislation in force in each country.</al></lid>
          
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">9</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Code Sharing</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>In operating international air services authorized under this Agreement,
any designated airline of a Party may, with prior approval by the Aeronautical
Authorities concerned, enter into cooperative marketing arrangements such
as blocked-space, code-sharing or leasing agreements, with an airline of another
Party.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">10</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Computerized Reservation Systems</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al> The Parties agree that:</al>
            <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
              <li>
                <li.nr>a)</li.nr>
                <al>The interests of the users of the air transport
services will be protected from any misuse of information;</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>b)</li.nr>
                <al>A designated airline and its agents will
have unrestricted and nondiscriminatory access to and use of Computer Reservation
Systems (CRS) in the territory of the Parties.</al>
              </li>
            </lijst>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al> The regulations and operation of CRS shall be governed by the Code
of Conduct established by ICAO.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">11</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Customs Duties and Charges</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al> Aircraft on a flight to, from, or across the territory of a Party shall
be admitted temporarily free of duty, subject to the customs regulations of
that Party. Fuel, lubricating oils, spare parts, standard equipment and aircraft
stores on board such aircraft, on arrival in the territory of another Party
and retained on board on departure shall be exempted from customs duty, inspection
fees or similar national or local duties and charges. This exemption will
not be applicable to quantities of items unloaded, except where the contrary
is provided for in accordance with the customs regulations of the relevant
Party which can demand that said quantities of items remain under customs
supervision.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al> Spare parts and equipment imported into the territory of a Party for
incorporation in or use on an aircraft of another Party engaged in international
air navigation shall be admitted free of customs duty, subject to compliance
with the regulations of the Party concerned, which may provide that the articles
shall be kept under customs supervision and control.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">12</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">User Fees</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al> User fees shall be fair, reasonable, non-discriminatory and equitably
distributed among the categories of users.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al> User fees must reflect the full cost of providing and administrating
services, installations and facilities at airports, air navigation services
and security. Installations and services provided must be efficiently and
economically operated.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al> Each Party shall promote the exchange of information necessary for
a reasonable revision of the fees, in accordance with paragraphs 1 and 2 of
this Article. Each Party shall urge the competent authorities to inform users
of any proposed change in fees, so as to allow them to express their views
before such fees become effective.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">13</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Fair Competition</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al> Each Party shall allow a fair and equal opportunity to the designated
airlines of all Parties to compete in providing the international air transport
governed by this Agreement.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al> Each Party shall take all appropriate actions within their respective
jurisdictions to avoid and eliminate all forms of unfair competitive practices.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al> Each Party shall allow a designated airline to determine the frequency
and capacity of the international air transport it offers based upon commercial
considerations in the marketplace. Consistent with this right, no Party shall
unilaterally limit the volume of traffic, frequency or regularity of service,
or the aircraft type or types operated by the designated airlines of another
Party, except for reasons of airport constraints, safety or security.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr>
            <al> The airlines shall submit their flight-schedules they consider convenient
according to the needs of the market, to the respective Aeronautical Authorities
for approval.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">14</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Tariffs</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al> The tariffs applicable by the designated airlines of each of the Parties
shall be established at reasonable levels, taking into account all relevant
factors including the cost of providing service, a reasonable profit and the
technical and economic characteristics of the different routes.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al> Without prejudice to the provisions of national legislation, the tariffs
to be applied by the designated airline or airlines of any Party for services
covered by this Agreement shall be subject to the principle of Country of
Origin tariff approval.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">15</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Consultations</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>A Party may, at any time, request consultations relating to this Agreement
with one or more Parties concerned. Such consultations shall begin at the
earliest possible date, but within 45 days from the date the other Party (or
Parties) concerned receives the request, unless otherwise agreed.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">16</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Disputes Settlement</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>Any dispute between the Parties concerning the interpretation and/or application
of this Agreement shall be referred to an arbitral tribunal for consideration
and decision where it has not been resolved by other dispute resolution mechanism,
among others negotiation, consultation or mediation. The process of dispute
settlement shall take account of the relevant ICAO policy guidance. The arbitral
tribunal shall be governed by the procedure provided in Article 85 of the
Convention and the decisions of the arbitral tribunal shall be binding upon
the Parties.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">17</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Existing Agreements</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>Bearing in mind the provisions in Article 2, this Agreement shall not
affect any memorandum of understanding, bilateral or multilateral agreement
showing similar authorizations that are already in force among the Parties
or among the Parties and a non-Party nor the renewal thereof.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">18</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Duration and Withdrawal</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>This Agreement shall have an indefinite duration. Any Party may at any
time denounce this Agreement. The consequent withdrawal shall take effect
one year after the date of the receipt by the Depositary of the formal notification
of denunciation. The denunciation shall be without prejudice to any obligation
incurred by the denouncing Party under this Agreement prior to such denunciation.
This Agreement shall continue to be in force thereafter with respect to the
other Parties.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">19</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Signature</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>This Agreement shall be open for signature by any State, Country and Territory
referred to in Article IV of the Convention Establishing the Association of
the Caribbean States that has ratified or adhered to said Convention.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">20</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Ratification</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>This Agreement shall be subject to ratification, acceptance or approval
by the States, Countries and Territories mentioned in Article IV of the Convention
Establishing the Association of Caribbean States, in accordance with the respective
Constitutional procedures.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">21</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Accession</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>After its entry into force, this Agreement shall remain open to accession
by the States, Countries and Territories mentioned in Article IV of the Convention
Establishing the Association of Caribbean States, in accordance wit the respective
constitutional procedures.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">22</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Amendments</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>This Agreement may be amended by consensus among the Parties.</al>
          <al>Amendments shall enter into force when one third of the Parties have deposited
their instruments of ratification, acceptance or approval and shall have effect
only as among Parties which have ratified, accepted or approved such amendments.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">23</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Reservations</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>A Party may enter reservations at the time of signing, ratifying, accepting,
approving or acceding to this Agreement, which will be notified to the Depository,
in accordance with the legislation of each Party. </al>
          <al>Such reservations shall not modify the provisions of the Agreement with
respect to the other Parties.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">24</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Depository</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>Instruments of Ratification, acceptance or approval or accession shall
be deposited with the Government of the Republic of Colombia in its capacity
as the Depository, which shall transmit certified copies to the Member States
and Associate Members.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">25</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Registration with ICAO</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>The Government of the Republic of Colombia shall register this Agreement
and all amendments thereto with the International Civil Aviation Organization.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">26</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Entry into Force</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>This Agreement shall enter into force on the 60th day after
the deposit of the instrument of ratification, acceptance, approval or accession,
when one third (nine) of the States, Countries and Territories mentioned in
Article IV of the Convention Establishing the Association of Caribbean States
have deposited their instruments of ratification, acceptance, approval or
accession.</al>
          
          
        </artikel>
      </wettekst>
      <wetsluiting status="goed">
        <slotformulering>
          <al>DONE in Panama City, Panama on the 14th day of the month of
February 2004, in a single copy in the English, French and Spanish languages,
each text being equally authentic. The original text and any amendments shall
be deposited with the Government of the Republic of Colombia in its capacity
as the Depository.</al>
          <al>IN WITNESS WHEREOF the undersigned plenipotentiaries, being duly authorized
by their respective Governments, have signed this Agreement.</al>
        </slotformulering>
      </wetsluiting>
    </verdragtekst>
  </verdrag>
  
</wetgeving>
  	