<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE wetgeving SYSTEM "http://wetten.overheid.nl/dtd/bwb-plus-meta-1_61w.dtd">
<wetgeving bwb-id="BWBV0004242" dtdversie="2.0" id="10000037169" sleutel="V3378" verdragnummer="002963" soort="verdrag"> 
  
  <alias-titels><alias-titel>Agreement on economic and technical co-operation between the Government of the Kingdom of the Netherlands and the Government of the Democratic Republic of the Sudan</alias-titel></alias-titels>
  <intitule>Overeenkomst inzake economische en technische samenwerking tussen de Regering van het Koninkrijk der Nederlanden en de Regering van de Democratische Republiek Soedan</intitule> 
   
  <verdrag tekst="authentiek" xml:lang="en"><verdragtekst>
<kop>
<titel status="officieel">Agreement on economic and technical co-operation between the Government of the Kingdom of the Netherlands and the Government of the Democratic Republic of the Sudan</titel>
</kop><aanhef><preambule><al>The Government of the Kingdom of the Netherlands and the Government of the Democratic Republic of the Sudan, being desirous to strengthen their traditional ties of friendship, to promote and intensify their economic and technical relations and to encourage investments on the basis of equality and mutual benefit,</al></preambule><afkondiging><al>Have agreed as follows:</al></afkondiging></aanhef><wettekst><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">I</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>The two Contracting Parties undertake to promote their cooperation in the economic and technical fields.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>The two Contracting Parties shall co-operate to facilitate the participation of their nationals in the establishment of productive and commercial activities and the provision of services in both countries.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>Any future technical co-operation between the two countries shall be defined in special agreements or administrative arrangements.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">II</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>To secure the achievement of the aims of the present Agreement, each Contracting Party undertakes within the framework of its laws, rules and regulations to authorize its nationals at their request to deliver capital goods and carry out public works for governmental and private enterprises in the territory of the other Contracting Party against payment agreed upon.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Each Contracting Party shall guarantee, within the framework of its laws, rules and regulations, the transfer from its territory, when due, of the sums owing to creditors, who are nationals of the other Contracting Party.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">III</nr>
</kop><al>The two Contracting Parties shall facilitate the intensification of commercial relations between their respective countries to the highest possible extent. For that purpose they shall, within the framework of their laws, rules and regulations, further the co-operation between all companies, associations, foundations and other organizations or subsidiary bodies thereof, which are connected with the economic life in both countries including all individuals engaged in economic activities.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">IV</nr>
</kop><al>When deciding on requests for the establishment of regular civil air services the Contracting Parties shall take into consideration the importance of the greatest possible freedom in air traffic.</al><al>Accordingly, the Contracting Parties acknowledge that the best means of achieving the aim set forth in the first paragraph of this Article lies in observing the provisions of the Air Transport Agreement in force between them.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">V</nr>
</kop><al>The Contracting Parties agree to promote the development of international shipping services. In doing so they shall maintain free and normal competitive conditions. Either Contracting Party shall refrain from taking any discriminatory measures against, and from restricting the free participation in international traffic of, vessels operated by enterprises of which the place of effective management is situated in the territory and flying the flag of the other Contracting Party.</al><al>From this arrangement shall be excepted fishery and coastal shipping in the non-European parts of the Kingdom of the Netherlands, to which only the internal regulations of these parts of the Kingdom shall apply, and fishery and coastal shipping in the Sudan.</al><al>Either Contracting Party shall accord in its ports to the vessels flying the flag of the other Contracting Party the same treatment as it accords to its own vessels. This provision applies to custom formalities, the collection of taxes, port fees and port charges, the free entry into ports, the assignment of berths, facilities for loading and unloading, and to all other facilities accorded to shipping and to economic activities in connection with vessels, their crews, their passengers and the cargoes they carry.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">VI</nr>
</kop><al>With respect to the payment of taxes, fees or charges and to the enjoyment of fiscal deductions and exemptions, each Contracting Party shall accord in its territory to nationals of the other Contracting Party engaged in any economic activity the same treatment as it accords to its own nationals.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">VII</nr>
</kop><al>Subject to the rights provided by international conventions, the nationals of either Contracting Party shall, as regards the protection of industrial property, enjoy in the territory of the other Contracting Party a protection not less favourable than that enjoyed by the nationals of the latter. Industrial property includes patents of inventions, industrial and commercial trade-marks, trade-names, industrial designs or models and the repression of unfair competition.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">VIII</nr>
</kop><al>Either Contracting Party undertakes to facilitate, within the framework of its laws, rules, and regulations:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>the holding in its territory by the other Contracting Party of economic and commercial exhibitions and displays;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>the importation into its territory by the other Contracting Party of professional equipment and of material and equipment intended for technical work on behalf of governmental bodies or private enterprises and the re-exportation thereof.</al></li></lijst></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">IX</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Each Contracting Party shall ensure fair and equitable treatment to the investments of nationals of the other Contracting Party and shall not by means of unjustified or discriminatory measures impair the management, maintenance, use, enjoyment or disposal thereof by those nationals.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>More particularly, each Contracting Party shall accord to such investments, the same security and protection as it accords to those of its own nationals.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">X</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Either Contracting Party shall guarantee to nationals of the other Contracting Party the transfer to their country of:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>the net profits, interests, and royalties, accruing from any economic activity to those nationals.</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>an appropriate portion of their earnings while they are authorized to work in its territory.</al></li><li><li.nr>(c)</li.nr><al>funds in repayment of loans which the Contracting Parties have recognized as investments.</al></li><li><li.nr>(d)</li.nr><al>in the event of liquidation, the proceeds from such liquidation.</al></li></lijst></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Subject to the laws, rules and regulations in force in each country any such transfer shall be carried out without undue restrictions or delay.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">XI</nr>
</kop><al>The investments of nationals of either Contracting Party in the territory of the other Contracting Party shall not be expropriated except for the public benefit and against compensation. Such compensation shall represent the equivalent to the depreciated value of the investment affected, it shall be actually realizable, freely transferable, and shall be paid without undue delay.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">XII</nr>
</kop><al>Either Contracting Party, approving in its territory the making of an investment on which the other Contracting Party or a national thereof has granted any financial security against non-commercial risks, shall recognize the subrogation of the grantor of that security into the rights of the investor as to damages to the extent of any payment made.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">XIII</nr>
</kop><al>The present Agreement shall apply to all investments made in the territory of the one Contracting Party by a national of the other Contracting Party irrespective of whether they were made before or after the date of the coming into force of the present Agreement.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">XIV</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>The Contracting Parties agree to establish a Mixed Commission, composed of representatives appointed by them.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>The Mixed Commission shall meet at the request of one of the Contracting Parties, to discuss any matters pertaining to the implementation of the present Agreement and to consider means of promoting their economic co-operation.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>The Mixed Commission shall keep under review the development of the economic relations between the two countries, both in bilateral and multilateral contexts. It shall moreover make recommendations to the respective Governments in cases where the objectives of this Agreement might be furthered and a fuller measure of economic co-operation might be obtained.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">XV</nr>
</kop><al>For the purposes of the present Agreement:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>1.</li.nr><al>the term &#x201C;nationals&#x201D; includes legal persons recognized by the laws of each Contracting Party in its territory.</al></li><li><li.nr>2.</li.nr><al>the term &#x201C;legal person&#x201D; includes a legal person established according to the law of one Contracting Party, in the territory of that Contracting Party in respect of which, because of its being controlled by a national of the other Contracting Party, it has been agreed upon by contract that it should be treated, for the purposes of the present Agreement, as a national of the latter Contracting Party.</al></li><li><li.nr>3.</li.nr><al>the term &#x201C;investment&#x201D; shall comprise every kind of asset and more particularly, though not exclusively:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>movable and immovable property as well as any other rights in rem, such as mortgage, lien, pledge, usufruct and similar rights;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>share or other kinds of interest in companies;</al></li><li><li.nr>(c)</li.nr><al>title to money or to any performance having an economic value;</al></li><li><li.nr>(d)</li.nr><al>copyright, industrial property rights, technical processes, trade names, and goodwill and</al></li><li><li.nr>(e)</li.nr><al>such business concession under public law, including concession regarding the prospecting for, or the extraction or the winning of natural resources, as give to their holder a legal position of some duration.</al></li></lijst><al>Any alteration in the form in which assets are invested shall not affect their classification as investment.</al></li></lijst></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">XVI</nr>
</kop><al>Where any matter is governed by both the present Agreement and other international Agreement binding on both Contracting Parties, nothing in this Agreement shall prevent a national of the one Contracting Party from benefiting by the provisions most favourable to him.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">XVII</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Disputes concerning the interpretation or application of the present Agreement should, if possible, be settled by the two Contracting Parties. If a dispute cannot thus be settled it shall be submitted, at the request of either party to the dispute, to an arbitral tribunal composed of three members. Each party shall appoint one arbitrator and the two arbitrators thus appointed shall together appoint an umpire who must not be a national of either party.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>If one of the parties fails to appoint its arbitrator and has not proceeded to do so within two months after an invitation from the other party to make such appointment, the arbitrator shall be appointed, at the request of the latter party, by the President of the International Court of Justice.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>If the two arbitrators are unable to reach agreement, in the two months following their appointment, on the choice of an umpire, the latter shall be appointed, at the request of either party, by the President of the International Court of Justice.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr><al>If, in the cases provided for in the second and third paragraph of this Article, the President of the International Court of Justice is prevented from discharging the said function or is a national of either party, the Vice-President shall make the necessary appointments. If the Vice-President is prevented from discharging the said function or is a national of either party, the Member of the Court next in seniority who is not a national of either party shall make the necessary appointments.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">5</lidnr><al>The tribunal shall base its decision on the provisions of the present Agreement in conformity with the principles of law. Before giving its decision, the tribunal may at any stage of the proceedings propose to the parties that the dispute be settled amicably. The foregoing provisions shall not prejudice the power of the arbitral tribunal to decide the dispute <nadruk type="cur">ex aequo et bono</nadruk> if the parties so agree.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">6</lidnr><al>Unless the parties decide otherwise, the tribunal shall determine its own procedure.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">7</lidnr><al>The tribunal shall reach its decision by a majority of votes. Such decision shall be final and binding on the parties to the dispute. Each Contracting Party shall bear the costs of its own arbitrator and of its counsel in the arbitral proceedings; the cost of the umpire and the remaining costs shall be borne in equal parts by both Contracting Parties.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">XVIII</nr>
</kop><al>As regards the Kingdom of the Netherlands, the present Agreement shall apply to the territory of the Kingdom in Europe, to Surinam and to the Netherlands Antilles, unless the instrument of ratification of the Kingdom of the Netherlands provides otherwise.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">XIX</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>The present Agreement shall be ratified and the instruments of ratification shall be exchanged as soon as possible at Khartoum.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>The present Agreement shall enter into force on the date of the exchange of the instruments of ratification and shall remain in force for a period of five years. Unless notice of termination has been given by either Contracting Party at least six months before the date of the expiry of its validity, the present Agreement shall be extended tacitly for another period of five years, and so on, each Contracting Party reserving the right to terminate the Agreement upon notice of at least six months before the date of expiry of the current period of validity.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>Subject to the periods mentioned in paragraph 2 of this Article, the Government of the Kingdom of the Netherlands shall be entitled to terminate the application of the present Agreement separately in respect of Surinam or the Netherlands Antilles.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr><al>Termination of the present Agreement shall not affect the validity of contracts concluded, or the validity of financial securities given, within the framework of the present Agreement prior to the date of termination.</al></lid></artikel></wettekst><wetsluiting status="goed"><slotformulering><al>IN WITNESS WHEREOF, the undersigned representatives, duly authorized thereto, have signed the present Agreement.</al><al>DONE at Khartoum on this day the 22nd. of August 1970, in duplicate, in the English language.</al><al><nadruk type="cur">For the Government of the Kingdom of the Netherlands,</nadruk></al><al>(sd.) G. WEHRY</al><al><nadruk type="cur"> For the Government of the Democratic Republic of the Sudan,</nadruk></al><al> (sd.) G. M. HAMID</al></slotformulering></wetsluiting></verdragtekst></verdrag> 
<verdrag tekst="vertaling" xml:lang="nl"><verdragtekst>
<kop>
<titel status="officieel">Overeenkomst inzake economische en technische samenwerking tussen de Regering van het Koninkrijk der Nederlanden en de Regering van de Democratische Republiek Soedan</titel>
</kop><aanhef><preambule><al>De Regering van het Koninkrijk der Nederlanden en de Regering van de Democratische Republiek Soedan, verlangende hun traditionele vriendschapsbanden aan te halen, hun economische en technische betrekkingen te ontwikkelen en te versterken en investeringen op basis van gelijkheid en tot wederzijds voordeel te bevorderen,</al></preambule><afkondiging><al>Zijn als volgt overeengekomen:</al></afkondiging></aanhef><wettekst><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">I</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>De beide Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen verbinden zich hun samenwerking op economisch en technisch gebied te bevorderen.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>De beide Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen zullen samenwerken ter vergemakkelijking van de deelneming door hun onderdanen in de ontplooiing van produktieve en commerci&#xEB;le activiteiten en de verlening van diensten in beide landen.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>Elke vorm van toekomstige technische samenwerking tussen de beide landen wordt omschreven in bijzondere overeenkomsten of administratieve akkoorden.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">II</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Teneinde de doelstellingen dezer Overeenkomst te verwezenlijken verbindt elke Overeenkomstsluitende Partij zich om, binnen de grenzen harer wetten, regelingen en voorschriften, haar onderdanen, op daartoe gedaan verzoek, te machtigen tot het leveren van kapitaalgoederen aan, en het uitvoeren van openbare werken ten behoeve van, Overheids- en particuliere ondernemingen op het grondgebied van de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij, tegen overeengekomen betalingen.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Elke Overeenkomstsluitende Partij waarborgt binnen de grenzen harer wetten, regelingen en voorschriften het telkens op de vervaldag overmaken uit haar grondgebied van de bedragen verschuldigd aan crediteuren die onderdanen zijn van de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">III</nr>
</kop><al>De beide Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen bevorderen de grootst mogelijke uitbreiding van de handelsbetrekkingen tussen hun onderscheiden landen. Hiertoe bevorderen zij, in het kader van hun wetten, regelingen en voorschriften, de samenwerking tussen alle maatschappijen, verenigingen, stichtingen en andere organisaties of dochterondernemingen daarvan, die verband houden met de nationale economie in beide landen, met inbegrip van alle personen die economische activiteiten verrichten.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">IV</nr>
</kop><al>Bij beslissingen op verzoeken inzake de instelling van geregelde burgerluchtvaartdiensten houden de Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen rekening met het belang van de grootst mogelijke vrijheid in het luchtverkeer.</al><al>Derhalve erkennen de Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen dat de beste wijze om het doel vervat in het eerste lid van dit artikel te verwezenlijken ligt in de naleving van de bepalingen van de tussen hen van kracht zijnde luchtvaartovereenkomst.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">V</nr>
</kop><al>De Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen komen overeen de ontwikkeling van internationale scheepvaartdiensten te bevorderen. Hierbij handhaven zij de vrije en normale mededingingsvoorwaarden. Elke Overeenkomstsluitende Partij onthoudt zich van het nemen van enigerlei discriminerende maatregelen tegen, en van het beperken van de vrije deelneming aan het internationale verkeer door schepen die worden ge&#xEB;xploiteerd door ondernemingen waarvan de plaats van daadwerkelijke leiding is gelegen binnen het grondgebied en die de vlag voeren van de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij.</al><al>Van deze regeling zijn uitgezonderd de visserij en de kustvaart in de niet-Europese delen van het Koninkrijk der Nederlanden, waarop alleen de interne regelingen van deze delen van het Koninkrijk van toepassing zijn, alsmede de visserij en de kustvaart in Soedan.</al><al>In haar havens kent elke Overeenkomstsluitende Partij aan schepen die de vlag van de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij voeren, dezelfde behandeling toe als die welke zij aan haar eigen schepen toekent. Deze bepaling is van toepassing op de douaneformaliteiten, het innen van belastingen en havengelden en -rechten, de vrije toegang tot de havens, het aanwijzen van aanlegsteigers, faciliteiten voor laden en lossen, alsmede op iedere andere faciliteit verleend aan de scheepvaart en aan economische activiteiten die betrekking hebben op de schepen, hun bemanningen, hun passagiers en hun lading.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">VI</nr>
</kop><al>Wat de betaling van belastingen, rechten of heffingen betreft, alsmede de toekenning van fiscale aftrekken en vrijstellingen, kent elke Overeenkomstsluitende Partij op haar grondgebied aan onderdanen van de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij, die economische activiteiten verrichten, dezelfde behandeling toe als die welke zij toekent aan haar eigen onderdanen.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">VII</nr>
</kop><al>Met inachtneming van de rechten waarin in internationale overeenkomsten is voorzien, genieten de onderdanen van elke Overeenkomstsluitende Partij, wat betreft de bescherming van de industri&#xEB;le eigendom, op het grondgebied van de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij een niet minder gunstige bescherming dan die welke de onderdanen van de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij genieten. De industri&#xEB;le eigendom omvat onder meer octrooien op uitvindingen, fabrieks- en handelsmerken, handelsnamen, industri&#xEB;le tekeningen of modellen en de bestrijding van oneerlijke mededinging.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">VIII</nr>
</kop><al>Elke Overeenkomstsluitende Partij verbindt zich binnen de grenzen harer wetten, regelingen en voorschriften te vergemakkelijken:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>het organiseren op haar grondgebied door de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij van economische en commerci&#xEB;le tentoonstellingen en soortgelijke manifestaties;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>de invoer in haar grondgebied door de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij van beroepsuitrusting en van materialen en uitrusting voor gebruik bij technische werkzaamheden ten behoeve van overheidsinstellingen of particuliere ondernemingen, en de wederuitvoer daarvan.</al></li></lijst></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">IX</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Elke Overeenkomstsluitende Partij waarborgt de eerlijke en billijke behandeling van de investeringen van onderdanen van de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij en belemmert niet, door ongerechtvaardigde of discriminatoire maatregelen, het beheer, de instandhouding, het gebruik en het genot daarvan of de beschikking daarover door die onderdanen.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Met name verleent elke Overeenkomstsluitende Partij aan zodanige investeringen dezelfde veiligheid en bescherming die zij verleent aan haar eigen onderdanen.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">X</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Elke Overeenkomstsluitende Partij waarborgt de onderdanen van de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij de overmaking naar hun land van:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>de netto-winsten, renten en royalties, verkregen uit enige economische activiteit aan die onderdanen;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>een passend deel van hun inkomsten wanneer zij toestemming hebben hun werkzaamheden op haar grondgebied uit te oefenen;</al></li><li><li.nr>(c)</li.nr><al>gelden voor de terugbetaling van leningen die de Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen als investeringen hebben erkend;</al></li><li><li.nr>(d)</li.nr><al>in geval van liquidatie, de opbrengst daarvan.</al></li></lijst></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Met inachtneming van de wetten, regelingen en voorschriften die in elk land van kracht zijn, worden zodanige overmakingen verricht zonder onnodige beperkingen of vertraging.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">XI</nr>
</kop><al>De investeringen van onderdanen van een der Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen op het grondgebied van de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij mogen niet worden onteigend, behalve in het openbaar belang en tegen vergoeding. Een zodanige vergoeding vertegenwoordigt de tegenwaarde van de getroffen investering; zij dient inderdaad verwezenlijkt te kunnen worden, vrijelijk te kunnen worden overgemaakt en zonder nodeloze vertraging te worden betaald.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">XII</nr>
</kop><al>Elke Overeenkomstsluitende Partij die goedkeurt dat op haar grondgebied een investering wordt verricht, ten aanzien waarvan de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij of een onderdaan daarvan enige financi&#xEB;le zekerheid tegen niet-commerci&#xEB;le risico's heeft gesteld, erkent de subrogatie van degene die deze zekerheid heeft gesteld in de rechten van de investeerder met betrekking tot schadevergoeding ten bedrage van iedere verrichte betaling.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">XIII</nr>
</kop><al>Deze Overeenkomst is van toepassing op alle investeringen verricht op het grondgebied van een der Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen door een onderdaan van de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij, ongeacht of deze zijn gedaan voor of na de datum waarop deze Overeenkomst in werking treedt.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">XIV</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>De Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen komen overeen een Gemengde Commissie in te stellen, bestaande uit door hen benoemde vertegenwoordigers.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>De Gemengde Commissie komt op verzoek van een der Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen bijeen ter bespreking van aangelegenheden betreffende de tenuitvoerlegging van deze Overeenkomst en ter bestudering van middelen voor de bevordering van hun economische samenwerking.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>De Gemengde Commissie stelt zich voortdurend op de hoogte van de ontwikkeling van de economische betrekkingen tussen de twee landen, zowel in bilateraal als in multilateraal verband. Bovendien doet zij aanbevelingen aan de onderscheiden Regeringen wanneer de doelstellingen van deze Overeenkomst zouden kunnen worden bevorderd en een grotere mate van economische samenwerking tot stand zou kunnen worden gebracht.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">XV</nr>
</kop><al>Voor de toepassing van deze Overeenkomst:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>1.</li.nr><al>wordt onder de term &#x201E;onderdanen&#x201D; mede verstaan rechtspersonen opgericht overeenkomstig het recht van elke Overeenkomstsluitende Partij op haar grondgebied;</al></li><li><li.nr>2.</li.nr><al>wordt onder de term &#x201E;rechtspersoon&#x201D; mede verstaan een rechtspersoon opgericht overeenkomstig het recht van een der Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen op het grondgebied van die Overeenkomstsluitende Partij, ten aanzien van welke rechtspersoon bij contract is overeengekomen dat hij ter fine van deze Overeenkomst als een onderdaan van de andere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij moet worden beschouwd omdat een onderdaan van laatstgenoemde Partij overwegend belang bij die rechtspersoon heeft;</al></li><li><li.nr>3.</li.nr><al>wordt onder de term &#x201E;investering&#x201D; verstaan alle activa en in het bijzonder, doch niet uitsluitend:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>roerende en onroerende goederen, zomede alle andere rechten ter zake zoals hypotheek, retentierecht, pandrecht, vruchtgebruik en soortgelijke rechten;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>aandelen of andere soorten belangen in maatschappijen;</al></li><li><li.nr>(c)</li.nr><al>recht op geld of op iedere verrichting die economische waarde heeft;</al></li><li><li.nr>(d)</li.nr><al>auteursrecht, rechten van industri&#xEB;le eigendom, technische werkwijzen, handelsnaam en goodwill en</al></li><li><li.nr>(e)</li.nr><al>zodanige publiekrechtelijke zakelijke concessies, waaronder concessies betreffende het zoeken naar of de extractie of winning van natuurlijke rijkdommen, die de houder daarvan gedurende enige tijd een rechtspositie verlenen.</al></li></lijst><al>Een wijziging in de vorm waarin activa zijn ge&#xEF;nvesteerd is niet van invloed op hun status als investering.</al></li></lijst></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">XVI</nr>
</kop><al>Wanneer een aangelegenheid bij zowel deze Overeenkomst als bij een andere internationale overeenkomst die verbindend is voor de Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen is geregeld, belet niets in deze Overeenkomst een onderdaan van een Overeenkomstsluitende Partij, zich te beroepen op de bepalingen die voor hem het gunstigst zijn.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">XVII</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Geschillen betreffende de uitlegging of de toepassing van deze Overeenkomst zullen, zo mogelijk, door de Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen worden geregeld. Indien een geschil niet op deze wijze kan worden geregeld, wordt het op verzoek van een der Partijen bij het geschil voorgelegd aan een uit drie leden bestaand scheidsgerecht. Iedere partij benoemt een scheidsman en de beide aldus benoemde scheidsmannen benoemen samen een derde scheidsman die geen onderdaan van een der partijen is.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Indien een der partijen geen scheidsman heeft benoemd en indien zij daartoe niet is overgegaan binnen twee maanden na een daartoe strekkend verzoek van de andere partij wordt de scheidsman op verzoek van laatstbedoelde partij benoemd door de President van het Internationale Gerechtshof.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>Indien de twee scheidsmannen binnen twee maanden na hun benoeming niet tot overeenstemming kunnen geraken over de keuze van een scheidsrechter, wordt deze op verzoek van een der partijen benoemd door de President van het Internationale Gerechtshof.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr><al>Indien in de gevallen bedoeld in het tweede en het derde lid van dit artikel, de President van het Internationale Gerechtshof verhinderd is genoemde functie uit te oefenen of indien hij onderdaan is van een der partijen, geschieden de noodzakelijke benoemingen door de Vice-President. Indien deze verhinderd is genoemde functie uit te oefenen of indien hij onderdaan is van een der partijen, geschieden de noodzakelijke benoemingen door het in jaren oudste lid van het Hof dat geen onderdaan is van een der partijen.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">5</lidnr><al>Het scheidsgerecht doet uitspraak op de grondslag van de bepalingen van deze Overeenkomst overeenkomstig de beginselen van het recht. Alvorens uitspraak te doen kan het scheidsgerecht, in ieder stadium van de procedure, aan de partijen voorstellen dat terzake van het geschil een minnelijke schikking wordt getroffen. De bovenstaande bepalingen doen geen afbreuk aan de bevoegdheid van het scheidsgerecht om een uitspraak <nadruk type="cur">ex aequo et bono</nadruk> te doen wanneer de partijen aldus overeenkomen.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">6</lidnr><al>Tenzij partijen anders beslissen, stelt het scheidsgerecht zijn procedureregels zelf vast.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">7</lidnr><al>Het scheidsgerecht beslist bij meerderheid van stemmen. Een zodanige beslissing is onherroepelijk en bindend voor de partijen bij het geschil. Elke Overeenkomstsluitende Partij draagt de kosten van haar eigen scheidsman en van haar advocaat in de scheidsrechterlijke procedure; de kosten van de scheidsrechter en de overige kosten worden gelijkelijk door de beide Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen gedragen.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">XVIII</nr>
</kop><al>Wat het Koninkrijk der Nederlanden betreft, is deze Overeenkomst van toepassing op het in Europa gelegen grondgebied van het Koninkrijk, op Suriname en op de Nederlandse Antillen, tenzij in de akte van bekrachtiging van het Koninkrijk der Nederlanden anders wordt bepaald.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">XIX</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Deze Overeenkomst dient te worden bekrachtigd en de akten van bekrachtiging worden zo spoedig mogelijk te Khartoem uitgewisseld.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Deze Overeenkomst treedt in werking op de dag van de uitwisseling van de akten van bekrachtiging en blijft van kracht voor een periode van vijf jaar. Tenzij een der Overeenkomstsluitende Partijen ten minste zes maanden voor het verstrijken van de geldigheidsperiode mededeling van be&#xEB;indiging van de Overeenkomst heeft gedaan, wordt de geldigheid van deze Overeenkomst stilzwijgend voor een nieuwe periode van vijf jaar verlengd, en zo vervolgens, waarbij iedere Overeenkomstsluitende Partij zich het recht voorbehoudt, de Overeenkomst te be&#xEB;indigen door daarvan ten minste zes maanden voor de datum van het verstrijken van de lopende periode kennis te geven.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>Met inachtneming van de termijnen genoemd in het tweede lid van dit artikel heeft de Regering van het Koninkrijk der Nederlanden het recht de toepassing van deze Overeenkomst voor Suriname of de Nederlandse Antillen afzonderlijk te be&#xEB;indigen.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr><al>De be&#xEB;indiging van deze Overeenkomst laat onverlet de geldigheid van contracten gesloten, of de geldigheid van enige financi&#xEB;le zekerheid gesteld in het kader van deze Overeenkomst en v&#xF3;&#xF3;r de datum harer be&#xEB;indiging.</al></lid></artikel></wettekst><wetsluiting status="goed"><slotformulering><al>TEN BLIJKE WAARVAN de ondergetekende vertegenwoordigers, daartoe behoorlijk gemachtigd, deze Overeenkomst hebben ondertekend.</al><al>GEDAAN te Khartoem, de 22ste augustus 1970, in tweevoud in de Engelse taal.</al><al><nadruk type="cur">Voor de Regering van het Koninkrijk der Nederlanden,</nadruk></al><al>(w.g.) G. WEHRY</al><al><nadruk type="cur"> Voor de Regering van de Democratische Republiek Soedan,</nadruk></al><al> (w.g.) G. M. HAMID</al></slotformulering></wetsluiting></verdragtekst></verdrag></wetgeving>
  	