<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE wetgeving SYSTEM "http://wetten.overheid.nl/dtd/bwb-plus-meta-1_61w.dtd">
<wetgeving bwb-id="BWBV0004843" dtdversie="2.0" id="10000043179" verdragnummer="012514" soort="verdrag">
  
  <intitule>Notawisseling houdende een verdrag tussen het Koninkrijk der Nederlanden en het Sierra Leone Tribunaal inzake het transport en de opslag van de archieven van het Tribunaal</intitule>
  
  <verdrag status="goed" tekst="authentiek" xml:lang="en">
    <verdragtekst xml:lang="en">
      <kop>
        <label>Nr.</label>
        <nr status="officieel">I</nr>
      </kop>
      <vrije-tekst><tekst status="goed"><al>SPECIAL
COURT FOR SIERRA
LEONE</al><al>Freetown, 26 November
2010</al><al><nadruk type="vet">Agreement between the Kingdom of the Netherlands
and the Special Court for Sierra Leone in connection with the
transportation and storage of the archives of the Special
Court</nadruk></al>

          <al>The
Special Court for Sierra Leone (hereinafter referred to as
&#x201C;Special Court&#x201D;) presents its compliments to the Ministry
of Foreign Affairs of the Kingdom of the Netherlands and has the honour
to refer to the consultations between the Ministry and the National
Archives of the Netherlands (the <nadruk type="cur">Nationaal
Archief</nadruk>, an Agency of the Ministry of Education, Culture and
Science) on the one hand, and the Special Court, on the other hand, on
the transportation of the archives of the Special Court to, and the
storage of these archives at, the premises of the National Archives of
the Netherlands (hereinafter &#x201C;Transportation and
Storage&#x201D;).</al><al>As a result of these consultations held in
connection with the Transportation and Storage of the Special
Court&#x2019;s archives, the Special Court has the honour to propose
the following:</al></tekst><artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">1</nr>
            </kop>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
              <al>The
Transportation and Storage of the Special Court&#x2019;s archives shall
be at the expense of the Special
Court.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
              <al>The
Kingdom of the Netherlands shall only bear liability for damages and
losses occurred to the archives of the SCSL in case these damages and
losses are the result of gross negligence and intentional acts of its
officers in connection with the Transportation of the archives by the
Royal Netherlands Air
Force.</al>
            </lid>
          </artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">2</nr>
            </kop>
            <al>During
the Transportation and Storage of the Special Court&#x2019;s archives,
the Special Court (and upon its succession, the Residual Special Court)
shall at all times retain exclusive ownership of the archives and
remain exclusively responsible for the &#x201C;Chain of Custody&#x201D;
of the
archives.</al>
          </artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">3</nr>
            </kop>

            <al>In
accordance with Article 2 of the Headquarters Agreement between the
Kingdom of the Netherlands and the Special Court for Sierra Leone, of
19 June 2006, the provisions of the Agreement between the Kingdom of
the Netherlands and the United Nations concerning the Headquarters of
the International Tribunal for the Prosecution of Persons Responsible
for Serious Violations of International Humanitarian Law Committed in
the Territory of the Former Yugoslavia since 1991, concluded at New
York on 29 July 1994, as amended (hereinafter referred to as
&#x201C;the Agreement&#x201D;), shall apply, <nadruk type="cur">mutatis
mutandis</nadruk>, in connection with the Transportation and Storage,
in
particular:</al>
            <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
              <li>
                <li.nr>a)</li.nr>
                <al>The
archives of the Special Court, and in general all documents and
materials made available, belonging to or used by the Special Court,
shall be inviolable, as mentioned in Article IX of the
Agreement;</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>b)</li.nr>
                <al>The assets, income and
other property of the Special Court, shall be exempt from all direct
taxes, as mentioned in Article X of the Agreement;</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>c)</li.nr>
                <al>All persons referred to in Article XIV, XV, XVII,
XVIII and XIX of the Agreement shall have the right of unimpeded entry
into, exit from and movement within the Kingdom of the Netherlands, and
they shall be granted facilities for speedy travel as mentioned in
Article XXIII of the
Agreement.</al>
              </li>
            </lijst>
          </artikel>
          <artikel status="goed">
            <kop>
              <label>Article</label>
              <nr status="officieel">4</nr>
            </kop>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
              <al>Operational
arrangements shall be made in connection with the Transportation and
Storage.</al>
            </lid>
            <lid>
              <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
              <al>The
conditions of storage and access to the Special Court&#x2019;s archives
shall be regulated by a Memorandum of Understanding between the Special
Court and the Kingdom of the
Netherlands.</al>
            </lid>
          </artikel></vrije-tekst><wetsluiting status="goed"><slotformulering><al>If the
abovementioned proposal is acceptable to the Ministry, the Special
Court has the honour to propose that this Note, together with the
affirmative Note in reply from the Ministry, shall constitute an
Agreement between the Special Court for Sierra Leone and the Kingdom of
the Netherlands in connection with the Transportation and Storage of
the archives of the Special Court. This Agreement shall apply to the
territory of the Kingdom of the Netherlands in Europe, and shall enter
into force on the date of the affirmative Note in reply from the
Ministry, with retroactive effect as per 10 December 2010.</al>
          <al>The
Special Court for Sierra Leone avails itself of this opportunity to
renew to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Kingdom of the
Netherlands the assurances of its highest
consideration.</al>
          <al>BINTA MANSARAY</al>
          <al>Registrar</al>
          <al>Special Court for Sierra Leone</al>
          <al><nadruk type="cur">Ministry of Foreign Affairs</nadruk></al>
          <al><nadruk type="cur">The
Hague</nadruk></al></slotformulering></wetsluiting>
    </verdragtekst>
    <verdragtekst xml:lang="en">
      <kop>
        <label>Nr.</label>
        <nr status="officieel">II</nr>
      </kop>
      <vrije-tekst>
        <tekst status="goed">
          
          <al>The Hague,  14 December
2010</al>
          <al>The Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Kingdom of the Netherlands
presents its compliments to the Special Court for Sierra Leone and has
the honour to refer to the special Courts&#x2019; Note of 26 November
2010, which reads as follows:</al>
          <al>
            <redactie type="extra">(Zoals in
Nr. I)</redactie>
          </al>
          <al>The Ministry has the honour to inform the
Special Court that the proposals set forth in the Special
Court&#x2019;s Note are acceptable to the Ministry and to confirm that
the Special Court&#x2019;s Note and this Note shall constitute an
Agreement between the Kingdom of the Netherlands and the Special Court
for Sierra Leone in connection with the Transportation and Storage of
the archives of the Special Court. This Agreement shall apply to the
territory of the Kingdom of the Netherlands in Europe, and shall enter
into force on the date of this affirmative Note in reply, with
retroactive effect as per 10 December
2010.</al>
          <al>The Ministry
of Foreign Affairs of the Kingdom of the Netherlands avails itself of
this opportunity to renew to the Special Court for Sierra Leone the
assurances of its highest
consideration.</al>
          <al><nadruk type="cur">Special Court for Sierra Leone</nadruk></al>
          <al><nadruk type="cur">Jomo Kenyatta
Road</nadruk></al>
          <al><nadruk type="cur">Freetown</nadruk></al>
          <al><nadruk type="cur">Sierra
Leone</nadruk></al>
        </tekst>
      </vrije-tekst>
    </verdragtekst>
  </verdrag>
  
</wetgeving>
  	