<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE wetgeving SYSTEM "http://wetten.overheid.nl/dtd/bwb-plus-meta-1_61w.dtd">
<wetgeving bwb-id="BWBV0005168" dtdversie="2.0" id="10000046429" verdragnummer="007872" soort="verdrag">
  
  
  
  <intitule>Notawisseling tussen de Nederlandse en de Deense Regering, houdende een overeenkomst betreffende vergoeding van tengevolge van de tweede wereldoorlog geleden oorlogsschade</intitule>
  
  <verdrag status="goed" tekst="authentiek" xml:lang="en"><verdragtekst><kop><nr status="officieel">I</nr></kop><vrije-tekst><tekst status="goed"><tussenkop kopopmaak="cur">L&#xC9;GATION DES PAYS-BAS</tussenkop><al>Copenhagen, April 24th, 1952.</al><al> Monsieur le Ministre,</al><al>With reference to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs' note of the 24th of May 1949 and subsequent conversations regarding equal treatment of physical and legal persons of Danish and Netherlands nationality with regard to the possibility of according compensation for war damage sustained in the Netherlands and in Denmark respectively, I have the honour to inform Your Excellency that the Netherlands Government have with interest taken note of the fact that the Danish Government, subject to reciprocity, are prepared to conclude an agreement with the Netherlands Government on this subject.</al><al>The Netherlands Government share the opinion of the Danish Government that the agreement should be confined to compensation for war damage on property and accordingly propose that the agreement should read as follows:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr> &#x201E;1.</li.nr><al>The Netherlands Government shall treat Danish subjects on a footing of equality with Netherlands nationals with respect to compensation for war damage sustained as a result of the second world war on property in the Netherlands.</al></li><li><li.nr>2.</li.nr><al>The Danish Government shall treat Netherlands subjects on a footing of equality with Danish nationals with respect to compensation for war damage sustained as a result of the second world war on property in Denmark.</al></li><li><li.nr>3.</li.nr><al>Legal persons in which Danish or Netherlands interests, or Danish and Netherlands interests in addition to each other, are represented for at least fifty per cent, whether according to the capital invested or according to the control exercised, shall receive for war damage on their property, sustained as a result of the second world war in Denmark and in the Netherlands, a compensation in accordance with the compensation accorded to legal persons by Danish and Netherlands Law respectively.</al></li><li><li.nr>4.</li.nr><al>Any claim for compensation resulting from this agreement must be lodged with the competent Government within six months after the date of this agreement in order to be taken into consideration.&#x201D;</al></li></lijst><al>If the Danish Government agree with the proposals contained in the foregoing paragraphs, I have the honour to suggest that the present note and Your Excellency's reply to that effect should be considered as placing on record the agreement of the two Governments in this matter.</al><al>I have the honour to be, Monsieur le Ministre,</al><al>Your obedient Servant,</al><al>(s.) G. P. LUDEN</al><al><nadruk type="cur">His Excellency</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur"> Monsieur Erik Eriksen,</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur"> Prime Minister,</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur">Minister of Foreign Affairs a.i.,</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur"> Copenhagen.</nadruk></al></tekst></vrije-tekst></verdragtekst><verdragtekst><kop><nr status="officieel">II</nr></kop><vrije-tekst><tekst status="goed">

<tussenkop kopopmaak="cur">MINISTRY FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS</tussenkop>
<al>Copenhagen, May 8th, 1952.</al><al>P. J. IV. Index no. 6. D. 57.</al><al> Monsieur le Ministre,</al><al>I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your note of April 24th, 1952, concerning equal treatment of physical and legal persons of Danish and Netherlands nationality with regard to the possibility of according compensation for war damage sustained in Denmark and in the Netherlands respectively as a result of the second world war. I have the honour to inform Your Excellency that the Danish Government have with interest taken note of the fact that the Netherlands Government, subject to reciprocity, are prepared to conclude an agreement with the Danish Government on this subject.</al><al>The Danish Government share the opinion of the Netherlands Government that the agreement should be confined to compensation for war damage on property. The proposed agreement reads as follows:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>&#x201E;1.</li.nr><al>The Netherlands Government shall treat Danish subjects on a footing of equality with Netherlands nationals with respect to compensation for war damage sustained as a result of the second world war on property in the Netherlands.</al></li><li><li.nr>2.</li.nr><al>The Danish Government shall treat Netherlands subjects on a footing of equality with Danish nationals with respect to compensation for war damage sustained as a result of the second world war on property in Denmark.</al></li><li><li.nr>3.</li.nr><al>Legal persons in which Danish or Netherlands interests, or Danish and Netherlands interests in addition to each other, are represented for at least fifty per cent, whether according to the capital invested or according to the control exercised, shall receive for war damage on their property, sustained as a result of the second world war in Denmark and in the Netherlands, a compensation in accordance with the compensation accorded to legal persons by Danish and Netherlands Law respectively.</al></li><li><li.nr>4.</li.nr><al>Any claim for compensation resulting from this agreement must be lodged with the competent Government within six months after the date of this agreement in order to be taken into consideration.&#x201D;</al></li></lijst><al>I have the honour to confirm that the Danish Government agree with the proposals contained in the foregoing paragraphs and that Your Excellency's note and the present note should be considered as placing on record the agreement of the two Governments in this matter.</al><al>I have the honour to be, Monsieur le Ministre,</al><al>Your obedient Servant,</al><al>(s.) OLE BJ&#xD8;RN KRAFT</al><al><nadruk type="cur">His Excellency</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur">Monsieur G. P. Luden,</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur">Envoy extraordinary and Minister plenipotentiary</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur">of Her Majesty the Queen of the Netherlands,</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur">Copenhagen.</nadruk></al></tekst></vrije-tekst></verdragtekst></verdrag></wetgeving>
  	