<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE wetgeving SYSTEM "http://wetten.overheid.nl/dtd/bwb-plus-meta-1_61w.dtd">
<wetgeving bwb-id="BWBV0004147" dtdversie="2.0" id="10000036219" verdragnummer="012371" xml:lang="nl" soort="verdrag"><alias-titels><alias-titel>International Convention on Civil Liability for Oil Pollution Damage, 1992 (1992 Liability Convention)</alias-titel></alias-titels><intitule>Internationaal Verdrag inzake de wettelijke aansprakelijkheid voor schade door verontreiniging door olie, 1992 (Aansprakelijkheidsverdrag 1992)</intitule><verdrag tekst="authentiek" xml:lang="en"><verdragtekst>
<kop>
<titel status="officieel">International Convention on Civil Liability for Oil Pollution Damage,
1992 (1992 Liability Convention)</titel>
</kop><aanhef><preambule><al>The States Parties to the present Convention,</al><al>Conscious of the dangers of pollution posed by the worldwide maritime carriage of oil in bulk,</al><al>Convinced of the need to ensure that adequate compensation is available to persons who suffer damage caused by pollution resulting from the escape or discharge of oil from ships,</al><al>Desiring to adopt uniform international rules and procedures for determining questions of liability and providing adequate compensation in such cases,</al></preambule><afkondiging><al>Have agreed als follows:</al></afkondiging></aanhef><wettekst><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">I</nr>
</kop><al>For the purposes of this Convention:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>1.</li.nr><al>&#x201C;Ship&#x201D; means any sea-going vessel and seaborne craft of any type whatsoever constructed or adapted for the carriage of oil in bulk as cargo, provided that a ship capable of carrying oil and other cargoes shall be regarded as a ship only when it is actually carrying oil in bulk as cargo and during any voyage following such carriage unless it is proved that it has no residues of such carriage of oil in bulk aboard.</al></li><li><li.nr>2.</li.nr><al>&#x201C;Person&#x201D; means any individual or partnership or any public or private body, whether corporate or not, including a State or any of its constituent subdivisions.</al></li><li><li.nr>3.</li.nr><al>&#x201C;Owner&#x201D; means the person or persons registered as the owner of the ship or, in the absence of registration, the person or persons owning the ship. However in the case of a ship owned by a State and operated by a company which in that State is registered as the ship's operator, &#x201C;owner&#x201D; shall mean such company.</al></li><li><li.nr>4.</li.nr><al>&#x201C;State of the ship's registry&#x201D; means in relation to registered ships the State of registration of the ship, and in relation to unregistered ships the State whose flag the ship is flying.</al></li><li><li.nr>5.</li.nr><al>&#x201C;Oil&#x201D; means any persistent hydrocarbon mineral oil such as crude oil, fuel oil, heavy diesel oil and lubricating oil, whether carried on board a ship as cargo or in the bunkers of such a ship.</al></li><li><li.nr>6.</li.nr><al>&#x201C;Pollution damage&#x201D; means:</al>
									<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." type="expliciet">
										<li>
											<li.nr>(a)</li.nr>
											<al>loss or damage caused outside the ship by contamination resulting from the escape or discharge of oil from the ship, wherever such escape or discharge may occur, provided that compensation  for impairment of the environment other than loss of profit from such impairment shall be limited to costs of reasonable measures of reinstatement actually undertaken or to be undertaken;</al>
										</li>
										<li>
											<li.nr>(b)</li.nr>
											<al>the costs of preventive measures and further loss or damage caused by preventive measures.</al>
										</li>
									</lijst></li><li><li.nr>7.</li.nr><al>&#x201C;Preventive measures&#x201D; means any reasonable measures taken by any person after an incident has occurred to prevent or minimize pollution damage.</al></li><li><li.nr>8.</li.nr><al>&#x201C;Incident&#x201D; means any occurrence, or series of occurrences having the same origin, which causes pollution damage or creates a grave and imminent threat of causing such damage.</al></li><li><li.nr>9.</li.nr><al>&#x201C;Organization&#x201D; means the International Maritime Organization.</al></li><li>
											<li.nr>10.</li.nr>
											<al>&#x201C;1969 Liability Convention&#x201D; means the International Convention on Civil Liability for Oil Pollution Damage, 1969. For States Parties to the Protocol of 1976 to that Convention, the term shall be deemed to include the 1969 Liability Convention as amended by that Protocol.</al>
										</li></lijst></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">II</nr>
</kop><al>This Convention shall apply exclusively:</al>
							<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." type="expliciet">
								<li>
									<li.nr>(a)</li.nr>
									<al>to pollution damage caused:</al>
									<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." type="expliciet">
										<li>
											<li.nr>(i)</li.nr>
											<al>in the territory, including the territorial sea, of a Contracting State, and</al>
										</li>
										<li>
											<li.nr>(ii)</li.nr>
											<al>in the exclusive economic zone of a Contracting State, established in accordance with international law, or, if a Contracting State has not established such a zone, in an area beyond and adjacent to the territorial sea of that State determined by that State in accordance with international law and extending not more than 200 nautical miles from the baselines from which the breadth of its territorial sea is measured;</al>
										</li>
									</lijst>
								</li>
								<li>
									<li.nr>(b)</li.nr>
									<al>to preventive measures, wherever taken, to prevent or minimize such damage.</al>
									
									
									
								</li>
								
								
							</lijst></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">III</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Except as provided in paragraphs 2 and 3 of this Article, the owner of a ship at the time of an incident, or, where the incident consists of a series of occurrences, at the time of the first such occurrence, shall be liable for any pollution damage caused by the ship as a result of the incident.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>No liability for pollution damage shall attach to the owner if he proves that the damage:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>resulted from an act of war, hostilities, civil war, insurrection or a natural phenomenon of an exceptional, inevitable and irresistible character, or</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>was wholly caused by an act or omission done with intent to cause damage by a third party, or</al></li><li><li.nr>(c)</li.nr><al>was wholly caused by the negligence or other wrongful act of any Government or other authority responsible for the maintenance of lights or other navigational aids in the exercise of that function.</al></li></lijst></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>If the owner proves that the pollution damage resulted wholly or partially either from an act or omission done with intent to cause damage by the person who suffered the damage or from the negligence of that person, the owner may be exonerated wholly or partially from his liability to such person.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr><al>No claim for compensation for pollution damage may be made against the owner otherwise than in accordance with this Convention. Subject to paragraph 5 of this Article, no claim for compensation for pollution damage under this Convention or otherwise may be made against:</al><lijst><li>
									<li.nr>(a)</li.nr>
									<al>the servants or agents of the owner of the members of the crew;</al>
								</li>
								<li>
									<li.nr>(b)</li.nr>
									<al>the pilot or any other person who, without being a member of the crew, performs services for the ship;</al>
								</li>
								<li>
									<li.nr>(c)</li.nr>
									<al>any charterer (howsoever described, including a bareboat charterer), manager of operator of the ship;</al>
								</li><li>
									<li.nr>(d)</li.nr>
									<al>any person performing salvage operations with the consent of the owner or on the instructions of a competent public authority;</al>
								</li>
								<li>
									<li.nr>(e)</li.nr>
									<al>any person taking preventive measures;</al>
								</li>
								<li>
									<li.nr>(f)</li.nr>
									<al> all servants or agents of persons mentioned in subparagraphs (c), (d) and (e);</al>
									
								</li></lijst><al>unless the damage resulted from their personal act or omission, committed with the intent to cause such damage, or recklessly and with knowledge that such damage would probably result.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">5</lidnr><al>Nothing in this Convention shall prejudice any right of recourse of the owner against third parties.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">IV</nr>
</kop><al>When an incident involving two or more ships occurs and pollution damage results therefrom, the owners of all the ships concerned, unless exonerated under Article III, shall be jointly and severally liable for all such damage which is not reasonably separable.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">V</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>The owner of a ship shall be entitled to limit his liability under this Convention in respect of any one incident to an aggregate amount calculated as follows:</al>
									<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
										<li>
											<li.nr>(a)</li.nr>
											<al>4,510,000 units of account for a ship not exceeding 5,000 units of tonnage;</al>
										</li>
										<li>
											<li.nr>(b)</li.nr>
											<al>for a ship with a tonnage in excess thereof, for each additional unit of tonnage, 631 units of account in addition to the amount mentioned in subparagraph (a);</al>
											
										</li>
									</lijst><al>provided, however, that this aggregate amount shall not in any event exceed 89,770,000 units of account.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>The owner shall not be entitled to limit his liability under this Convention if it is proved that the pollution damage resulted from his personal act or omission, committed with the intent to cause such damage, or recklessly and with knowledge that such damage would probably result.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>For the purpose of availing himself of the benefit of limitation provided for in paragraph 1 of this Article the owner shall constitute a fund for the total sum representing the limit of his liability with the Court or other competent authority of any one of the Contracting States in which action is brought under Article IX or, if no action is brought, with any Court or other competent authority in any one of the Contracting States in which an action can be brought under Article IX. The fund can be constituted either by depositing the sum or by producing a bank guarantee or other guarantee, acceptable under the legislation of the Contracting Statewhere the fund is constituted, and considered to be adequate by the Court or other competent authority.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr><al>The fund shall be distributed among the claimants in proportion to the amounts of their established claims.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">5</lidnr><al>If before the fund is distributed the owner or any of his servants or agents or any person providing him insurance or other financial security has as a result of the incident in question, paid compensation for pollution damage, such person shall, up to the amount he has paid, acquire by subrogation the rights which the person so compensated would have enjoyed under this Convention.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">6</lidnr><al>The right of subrogation provided for in paragraph 5 of this Article may also be exercised by a person other than those mentioned therein in respect of any amount of compensation for pollution damage which he may have paid but only to the extent that such subrogation is permitted under the applicable national law.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">7</lidnr><al>Where the owner or any other person establishes that he may be compelled to pay at a later date in whole or in part any such amount of compensation, with regard to which such person would have enjoyed a right of subrogation under paragraphs 5 or 6 of this Article, had the compensation been paid before the fund was distributed, the Count or other competent authority of the State where the fund has been constituted may order that a sufficient sum shall be provisionally set aside to enable such person at such later date to enforce his claim against the fund.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">8</lidnr><al>Claims in respect of expenses reasonably incurred or sacrifices reasonably made by the owner voluntarily to prevent or minimize pollution damage shall rank equally with other claims against the fund.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">9</lidnr><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
										<li>
											<li.nr>(a).</li.nr>
											<al>The &#x201C;unit of account&#x201D;referred to in paragraph 1 of this Article is the Special Drawing Right as defined by the International Monetary Fund. The amounts mentioned in paragraph 1 shall be converted into national currency on the basis of the value of that currency by reference to the Special Drawing Right on the date of the constitution of the fund referred to in paragraph 3. The value of the national currency, in terms of the Special Drawing Right, of  a Contracting State which is a member of the International Monetary Fund shall be calculated in accordance with the method of valuation applied by the International Monetary Fund in effect on the date in question for its operations and transactions. The value of the national currency, in terms of the Special Drawing Right, of a Contracting State which is not a member of the International Monetary Fund shall be calculated in a manner determined by that State.</al>
										</li>
										<li>
											<li.nr>(b).</li.nr>
											<al>Nevertheless, a Contracting State which is not a member of the International Monetary Fund and whose law does not permit the application of the provisions of paragraph 9(a) may, at the time of ratification, acceptance, approval of or accession to this Convention or at any time thereafter, declare that the unit of account referred to in paragraph 9(a) shall be equal to 15 gold francs. The gold franc referred to in this paragraph corresponds to sixty-five and a half milligrammes of gold of millesimal fineness nine hundred. The conversion of the gold franc into the national currency shall be made according to the law of the State concerned.</al>
										</li>
										<li>
											<li.nr>(c).</li.nr>
											<al>The calculation mentioned in the last sentence of paragraph 9(a) and the conversion mentioned in paragraph 9(b) shall be made in such manner as to express in the national currency of the Contracting State as far as possible the same real value for the amounts in paragraph 1 as would result from the application of the first three sentences of paragraph 9(a). Contracting States shall communicate to the depositary the manner of calculation pursuant to paragraph 9(a), or the result of the conversion in paragraph 9(b) as the case may be, when depositing an instrument of ratification, acceptance, approval of or accession to this Convention and whenever there is a change in either.</al>
										</li>
									</lijst></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">10</lidnr><al>For the purpose of this Article the ship's tonnage shall be the gross tonnage calculated in accordance with the tonnage measurement regulations contained in Annex I of the International Convention on Tonnage Measurement of Ships, 1969.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">11</lidnr><al>The insurer or other person providing financial security shall be entitled to constitute a fund in accordance with this Article on the same conditions and having the same effect as if it were constituted by the owner. Such a fund may be constituted even if, under the provisions of paragraph 2, the owner is not entitled to limit his liability, but its constitution shall in that case not prejudice the rights of any claimant against the owner.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">VI</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Where the owner, after an incident, has constituted a fund in accordance with Article V, and is entitled to limit his liability,</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>no person having a claim for pollution damage arising out of that incident shall be entitled to exercise any right against any other assets of the owner in respect of such claim;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>the Court or other competent authority of any Contracting State shall order the release of any ship or other property belonging to the owner which has been arrested in respect of a claim for pollution damage arising out of that incident, and shall similarly release any bail or other security furnished to avoid such arrest.</al></li></lijst></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>The foregoing shall, however, only apply if the claimant has access to the Court administering the fund and the fund is actually available in respect of his claim.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">VII</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>The owner of a ship registered in a Contracting State and carrying more than 2,000 tons of oil in bulk as cargo shall be required to maintain insurance or other financial security, such as the guarantee of a bank or a certificate delivered by an international compensation fund, in the sums fixed by applying the limits of liability prescribed in Article V, paragraph 1 to cover his liability for pollution damage under this Convention.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>A certificate attesting that insurance or other financial security is in force in accordance with the provisions of this Convention shall be issued to each ship after the appropriate authority of a Contracting State has determined that the requirements of paragraph 1 have been complied with. With respect to a ship registered in a Contracting State such certificate shall be issued or certified by the appropriate authority of the State of the ship's registry; with respect to a ship not registered in a Contracting State it may be issued or certified by the appropriate authority of any Contracting State. This certificate shall be in the form of the annexed model and shall contain the following particulars:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>name of ship and port of registration;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>name and principal place of business of owner;</al></li><li><li.nr>(c)</li.nr><al>type of security;</al></li><li><li.nr>(d)</li.nr><al>name and principal place of business of insurer or other person giving security and, where appropriate, place of business where the insurance or security is established;</al></li><li><li.nr>(e)</li.nr><al>period of validity of certificate which shall not be longer than the period of validity of the insurance or other security.</al></li></lijst></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>The certificate shall be in the official language or languages of the issuing State. If the language used is neither English nor French, the text shall include a translation into one of these languages.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr><al>The certificate shall be carried on board the ship and a copy shall be deposited with the authorities who keep the record of the ship's registry or, if the ship is not registered in a Contracting State, with the authorities of the State issuing or certifying the certificate.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">5</lidnr><al>An insurance or other financial security shall not satisfy the requirements of this Article if it can cease, for reasons other than the expiry of the period of validity of the insurance or security specified in the certificate under paragraph 2 of this Article, before three months have elapsed from the date on which notice of its termination is given to the authorities referred to in paragraph 4 of this Article, unless the certificate has been surrendered to these authorities or a new certificate has been issued within the said period. The foregoing provisions shall similarly apply to any modification which results in the insurance or security no longer satisfying the requirements of this Article.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">6</lidnr><al>The State of registry shall, subject to the provisions of this Article, determine the conditions of issue and validity of the certificate.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">7</lidnr><al>Certificates issued or certified under the authority of a Contracting State in accordance with paragraph 2 shall be accepted by other Contracting States for the purposes of this Convention and shall be regarded by other Contracting States as having the same force as certificates issued or certified by them even if issued or certified in respect of a ship not registered in a Contracting State. A Contracting State may at any time request consultation with the issuing or certifying State should it believe that the insurer or guarantor named in the certificate is not financially capable of meeting the obligations imposed by this Convention.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">8</lidnr><al>Any claim for compensation for pollution damage may be brought directly against the insurer or other person providing financial security for the owner's liability for pollution damage. In such case the defendant may, even if the owner is not entitled to limit his liability according to Article V, paragraph 2, avail himself of the limits of liability prescribed in Article V, paragraph 1. He may further avail himself of the defences (other than the bankruptcy or winding up of the owner) which the owner himself would have been entitled to invoke. Furthermore, the defendant may avail himself of the defence that the pollution damage resulted from the wilful misconduct of the owner himself, but the defendant shall not avail himself of any other defence which he might have been entitled to invoke in proceedings brought by the owner against him. The defendant shall in any event have the right to require the owner to be joined in the proceedings.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">9</lidnr><al>Any sums provided by insurance or by other financial security maintained in accordance with paragraph 1 of this Article shall be available exclusively for the satisfaction of claims under this Convention.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">10</lidnr><al>A Contracting State shall not permit a ship under its flag to which this Article applies to trade unless a certificate has been issued under paragraph 2 or 12 of this Article.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">11</lidnr><al>Subject to the provisions of this Article, each Contracting State shall ensure, under its national legislation, that insurance or other security to the extent specified in paragraph 1 of this Article is in force in respect of any ship, wherever registered, entering or leaving a port in its territory, or arriving at or leaving an offshore terminal in its territorial sea, if the ship actually carries more than 2,000 tons of oil in bulk as cargo.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">12</lidnr><al>If insurance or other financial security is not maintained in respect of a ship owned by a Contracting State, the provisions of this Article relating thereto shall not be applicable to such ship, but the ship shall carry a certificate issued by the appropriate authorities of the State of the ship's registry stating that the ship is owned by that State and that the ship's liability is covered within the limits prescribed by Article V, paragraph 1. Such a certificate shall follow as closely as practicable the model prescribed by paragraph 2 of this Article.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">VIII</nr>
</kop><al>Rights of compensation under this Convention shall be extinguished unless an action is brought thereunder within three years from the date when the damage occurred. However, in no case shall an action be brought after six years from the date of the incident which caused the damage. Where this incident consists of a series of occurrences, the six years' period shall run from the date of the first such occurrence.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">IX</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Where an incident has caused pollution damage in the territory, including the territorial sea or an area referred to in Article II, of one or more Contracting States or preventive measures have been taken to prevent or minimize pollution damage in such territory including the territorial sea or area, actions for compensation may only be brought in the Courts of any such Contracting State or States. Reasonable notice of any such action shall be given to the defendant.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Each Contracting State shall ensure that its Courts possess the necessary jurisdiction to entertain such actions for compensation.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>After the fund has been constituted in accordance with Article V the Courts of the State in which the fund is constituted shall be exclusively competent to determine all matters relating to the apportionment and distribution of the fund.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">X</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Any judgment given by a Court with jurisdiction in accordance with Article IX which is enforceable in the State of origin where it is no longer subject to ordinary forms of review, shall be recognized in any Contracting State, except:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>where the judgment was obtained by fraud; or</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>where the defendant was not given reasonable notice and a fair opportunity to present his case.</al></li></lijst></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>A judgment recognized under paragraph 1 of this Article shall be enforceable in each Contracting State as soon as the formalities required in that State have been complied with. The formalities shall not permit the merits of the case to be re-opened.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">XI</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>The provisions of this Convention shall not apply to warships or other ships owned or operated by a State and used, for the time being, only on Government non-commercial service.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>With respect to ships owned by a Contracting State and used for commercial purposes, each State shall be subject to suit in the jurisdictions set forth in Article IX and shall waive all defences based on its status as a sovereign State.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">XII</nr>
</kop><al>This Convention shall supersede any International Conventions in force or open for signature, ratification or accession at the date on which the Convention is opened for signature, but only to the extent that such Conventions would be in conflict with it; however, nothing in this Article shall affect the obligations of Contracting States to non-Contracting States arising under such International Conventions.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								
								
							<label>Article</label><nr status="officieel">XII bis</nr><titel status="officieel">Transitional provisions</titel></kop>
							
							<al>The following transitional provisions shall apply in the case of a State which at the time of an incident is a Party both to this Convention and to the 1969 Liability Convention:</al>
							<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
								<li>
									<li.nr>(a)</li.nr>
									<al>Where an incident has caused pollution damage within the scope of this Convention, liability under this Convention shall be deemed to be discharged if, and to the extent that, it also arises under the 1969 Liability Convention;</al>
								</li>
								<li>
									<li.nr>(b)</li.nr>
									<al>where an incident has caused pollution damage within the scope of this Convention, and the State is a Party both to this Convention and to the International Convention on the Establishment of an International Fund for Compensation for Oil Pollution Damage, 1971, liability remaining to be discharged after the application of subparagraph (a) of this Article shall arise under this Convention only to the extent that pollution damage remains uncompensated after application of the said 1971 Convention;</al>
								</li>
								<li>
									<li.nr>(c)</li.nr>
									<al>in the application of Article III, paragraph 4, of this Convention the expression &#x201C;this Convention&#x201D; shall be interpreted as referring to this Convention or the 1969 Liability Convention, as appropriate;</al>
								</li>
								<li>
									<li.nr>(d)</li.nr>
									<al>in the application of Article V, paragraph 3, of this Convention the total sum of the fund to be constituted shall be reduced by the amount by which liability has been deemed to be discharged in accordance with subparagraph (a) of this Article.</al>
									
								</li>
							</lijst>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Article</label><nr>XII ter</nr><titel>Final clauses</titel></kop><al>The final clauses of this Convention shall be Articles 12 to 18 of the Protocol of 1992 to amend the 1969 Liability Convention. References in this Convention to Contracting States shall be taken to mean references to the Contracting States of that Protocol.</al></artikel><hoofdstuk><kop><titel>FINAL CLAUSES</titel></kop><artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Article</label><nr>12</nr><titel>Signature, ratification, acceptance, approval and accession</titel></kop><lid>
								<lidnr>1</lidnr>
								<al>This Protocol shall be open for signature at London from 15 January 1993 to 14 January 1994 by all States.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr>2</lidnr>
								<al>Subject to paragraph 4, any State may become a Party to this Protocol by:</al>
								<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." type="expliciet">
									<li>
										<li.nr>(a)</li.nr>
										<al>signature subject to ratification, acceptance or approval followed by ratification, acceptance or approval; or</al>
									</li>
									<li>
										<li.nr>b)</li.nr>
										<al>accession.</al>
									</li>
								</lijst>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr>3</lidnr>
								<al>Ratification, acceptance, approval or accession shall be effected by the deposit of a formal instrument to that effect with the Secretary General of the Organization.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr>4</lidnr>
								<al>Any Contracting State to the International Convention on the Establishment of an International Fund for Compensation for Oil Pollution Damage, 1971, hereinafter referred to as the 1971 Fund Convention, may ratify, accept, approve or accede to this Protocol only if it ratifies, accepts, approves or accedes to the Protocol of 1992 to amend that Convention at the same time, unless it denounces the 1971 Fund Convention to take effect on the date when this Protocol enters into force for that State.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr>5</lidnr>
								<al>A State which is a Party to this Protocol but not a Party to the 1969 Liability Convention shall be bound by the provisions of the 1969 Liability Convention as amended by this Protocol in relation to other States Parties hereto, but shall not be bound by the provisions of the 1969 Liability Convention in relation to States Parties thereto.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr>6</lidnr>
								<al>Any instrument of ratification, acceptance, approval or accession deposited after the entry into force of an amendment to the 1969 Liability Convention as amended by this Protocol shall be deemed to apply to the Convention so amended, as modified by such amendment.</al>
							</lid>
						</artikel><artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Article</label>
								<nr status="officieel">13</nr>
								<titel status="officieel">Entry into force</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
								<al>This Protocol shall enter into force twelve months following the date on which ten States including four States each with not less than one million units of gross tanker tonnage have deposited instruments of ratification, acceptance, approval or accession with the Secretary-General of the Organization.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
								<al>However, any Contracting State to the 1971 Fund Convention may, at the time of the deposit of its instrument of ratification, acceptance, approval or accession in respect of this Protocol, declare that such instrument shall be deemed not to be effective for the purposes of this Article until the end of the six-month period in Article 31 of the Protocol of 1992 to amend the 1971 Fund Convention. A State which is not a Contracting State to the 1971 Fund Convention but which deposits an instrument of ratification, acceptance, approval or accession in respect of the Protocol of 1992 to amend the 1971 Fund Convention may also make a declaration in accordance with this paragraph at the same time.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
								<al>Any State which has made a declaration in accordance with the preceding paragraph may withdraw it at any time by means of a notification addressed to the Secretary-General of the Organization. Any such withdrawal shall take effect on the date the notification is received, provided that such State shall be deemed to have deposited its instrument of ratification, acceptance, approval or accession in respect of this Protocol on that date.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr>
								<al>For any State which ratifies, accepts, approves or accedes to it after the conditions in paragraph 1 for entry into force have been met, this Protocol shall enter into force twelve months following the date of deposit by such State of the appropriate instrument.</al>
							</lid>
						</artikel><artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Article</label>
								<nr>14</nr>
								<titel>Revision and amendment</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr>1</lidnr>
								<al>A Conference for the purpose of revising or amending the 1992 Liability Convention may be convened by the Organization.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr>2</lidnr>
								<al>The Organization shall convene a Conference of Contracting States for the purpose of revising or amending the 1992 Liability Convention at the request of not less than one third of the Contracting States.</al>
								
							</lid>
							</artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Article</label><nr status="officieel">15</nr><titel status="officieel">Amendments of limitation amounts</titel></kop><lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
								<al>Upon the request of at least one quarter of the Contracting States any proposal to amend the limits of liability laid down in Article V, paragraph 1, of the 1969 Liability Convention as amended by this Protocol shall be circulated by the Secretary-General to all Members of the Organization and to all Contracting States.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
								<al>Any amendment proposed and circulated as above shall be submitted to the Legal Committee of the Organization for consideration at a date at least six months after the date of its circulation.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
								<al>All Contracting States to the 1969 Liability Convention as amended by this Protocol, whether or not Members of the Organization, shall be entitled to participate in the proceedings of the Legal Committee for the consideration and adoption of amendments.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr>
								<al>Amendments shall be adopted by a two-thirds majority of the Contracting States present and voting in the Legal Committee, expanded as provided for in paragraph 3, on condition that at least one half of the Contracting States shall be present at the time of voting.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">5</lidnr>
								
								
								
								
							<al>When acting on a proposal to amend the limits, the Legal Committee shall take into account the experience of incidents and in particular the amount of damage resulting therefrom, changes in the monetary values and the effect of the proposed amendment on the cost of insurance. It shall also take into account the relationship between the limits in Article V, paragraph 1, of the 1969 Liability Convention as amended by this Protocol and those in Article 4, paragraph 4, of the International Convention on the Establishment of an International Fund for Compensation for Oil Pollution Damage, 1992.
								</al></lid>
							<lid><lidnr status="officieel">6</lidnr><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
									<li>
										<li.nr>(a)</li.nr>
										
									<al>No amendment of the limits of liability under this Article may be considered before 15 January 1998 nor less than five years from the date of entry into force of a previous amendment under this Article. No mendment under this Article shall be considered before this Protocol s entered into force.</al></li>
									<li>
										<li.nr>(b)</li.nr>
										<al>No limit may be increased so as to exceed an amount which corresponds to the limit laid down in the 1969 Liability Convention as amended by this Protocol increased by 6 per cent per year calculated on a compound basis from 15 January 1993.</al>
									</li>
									<li>
										<li.nr>(c)</li.nr>
										<al>No limit may be increased so as to exceed an amount which corresponds to the limit laid down in the 1969 Liability Convention as amended by this Protocol multiplied by 3.</al>
									</li>
								</lijst></lid><lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">7</lidnr>
								<al>Any amendment adopted in accordance with paragraph 4 shall be notified by the Organization to all Contracting States. The amendment shall be deemed to have been accepted at the end of a period of eighteen months after the date of notification, unless within that period not less than one quarter of the States that were Contracting States at the time of the adoption of the amendment by the Legal Committee have communicated to the Organization that they do not accept the amendment in which case the amendment is rejected and shall have no effect.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">8</lidnr>
								<al>An amendment deemed to have been accepted in accordance with paragraph 7 shall enter into force eighteen months after its acceptance.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">9</lidnr>
								<al>All Contracting States shall be bound by the amendment, unless they denounce this Protocol in accordance with Article 16, paragraphs 1 and 2, at least six months before the amendment enters into force. Such denunciation shall take effect when the amendment enters into force.</al>
								
							</lid>
						<lid><lidnr status="officieel">10</lidnr><al>When an amendment has been adopted by the Legal Committee but the eighteen-month period for its acceptance has not yet expired, a State which becomes a Contracting State during that period shall bebound by the amendment if it enters into force. A State which becomes a Contracting State after that period shall be bound by an amendment which has been accepted in accordance with paragraph 7. In the cases referred to in this paragraph, a State becomes bound by an amendment when that amendment enters into force, or when this Protocol enters into force for that State, if later.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Article</label>
								<nr>16</nr>
								<titel>Denunciation</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr>1</lidnr>
								<al>This Protocol may be denounced by any Party at any time after the date on which it enters into force for that Party.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr>2</lidnr>
								<al>Denunciation shall be effected by the deposit of an instrument with the Secretary-General of the Organization.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr>3</lidnr>
								<al>A denunciation shall take effect twelve months, or such longer period as may be specified in the instrument of denunciation, after its deposit with the Secretary-General of the Organization.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr>4</lidnr>
								<al>As between the Parties to this Protocol, denunciation by any of them of the 1969 Liability Convention in accordance with Article XVI thereof shall not be construed in any way as a denunciation of the 1969 Liability Convention as amended by this Protocol.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr>5</lidnr>
								<al>Denunciation of the Protocol of 1992 to amend the 1971 Fund Convention by a State which remains a Party to the 1971 Fund Convention shall be deemed to be a denunciation of this Protocol. Such denunciation shall take effect on the date on which denunciation of the Protocol of 1992 to amend the 1971 Fund Convention takes effect according to Article 34 of that Protocol.</al>
							</lid>
						</artikel><artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Article</label>
								<nr>17</nr>
								<titel>Depositary</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr>1</lidnr>
								<al>This Protocol and any amendments accepted under Article 15 shall be deposited with the Secretary-General of the Organization.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr>2</lidnr>
								<al>The Secretary-General of the Organization shall:</al>
								<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." type="expliciet">
									<li>
										<li.nr>(a)</li.nr>
										<al>inform all States which have signed or acceded to this Protocol of:</al>
										<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." type="expliciet">
											<li>
												<li.nr>(i)</li.nr>
												<al>each new signature or deposit of an instrument together with the date thereof;</al>
											</li>
											<li>
												<li.nr>(ii)</li.nr>
												<al>each declaration and notification under Article 13 and each declaration and communication under Article V, paragraph 9, of the 1992 Liability Convention;</al>
											</li>
											<li>
												<li.nr>(iii)</li.nr>
												<al>the date of entry into force of this Protocol;</al>
											</li>
											<li>
												<li.nr>(iv)</li.nr>
												<al>any proposal to amend limits of liability which has been made in accordance with Article 15, paragraph 1;</al>
											</li>
											<li>
												<li.nr>(v)</li.nr>
												<al>any amendment which has been adopted in accordance with Article 15, paragraph 4;</al>
											</li>
											<li>
												<li.nr>(vi)</li.nr>
												<al>any amendment deemed to have been accepted under Article 15, paragraph 7, together with the date on which that amendment shall enter into force in accordance with paragraphs 8 and 9 of that Article;</al>
											</li>
											<li>
												<li.nr>(vii)</li.nr>
												<al>the deposit of any instrument of denunciation of this Protocol together with the date of the deposit and the date on which it takes effect;</al></li><li><li.nr>(viii)</li.nr><al>any denunciation deemed to have been made under Article 16, paragraph 5;</al>
											</li>
											<li>
												<li.nr>(ix)</li.nr>
												<al>any communication called for by any Article of this Protocol;</al>
											</li>
										</lijst>
									</li>
									<li>
										<li.nr>(b)</li.nr>
										<al>transmit certified true copies of this Protocol to all Signatory States and to all States which accede to this Protocol.</al>
									</li>
								</lijst>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr>3</lidnr>
								<al> As soon as this Protocol enters into force, the text shall be transmitted by the Secretary-General of the Organization to the Secretariat of the United Nations for registration and publication in accordance with Article 102 of the Charter of the United Nations.</al>
							</lid>
						</artikel><artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Article</label>
								<nr>18</nr>
								<titel>Languages</titel>
							</kop>
							<al>This Protocol is established in a single original in the Arabic, Chinese, English, French, Russian and Spanish languages, each text being equally authentic.</al>
						</artikel></hoofdstuk><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">XIII</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>The present Convention shall remain open for signature until 31 December 1970 and shall thereafter remain open for accession.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>States Members of the United Nations or any of the Specialized Agencies or of the International Atomic Energy Agency or Parties to the Statute of the International Court of Justice may become Parties to this Convention by:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>signature without reservation as to ratification, acceptance or approval;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>signature subject to ratification, acceptance or approval followed by ratification, acceptance or approval; or</al></li><li><li.nr>(c)</li.nr><al>accession.</al></li></lijst></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">XIV</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Ratification, acceptance, approval or accession shall be effected by the deposit of a formal instrument to that effect with the Secretary-General of the Organization.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Any instrument of ratification, acceptance, approval or accession deposited after the entry into force of an amendment to the present Convention with respect to all existing Contracting States, or after the completion of all measures required for the entry into force of the amendment with respect to those Contracting States shall be deemed to apply to the Convention as modified by the amendment.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">XV</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>The present Convention shall enter into force on the ninetieth day following the date on which Governments of eight States including five States each with not less than 1,000,000 gross tons of tanker tonnage have either signed it without reservation as to ratification, acceptance or approval or have deposited instruments of ratification, acceptance, approval or accession with the Secretary-General of the Organization.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>For each State which subsequently ratifies, accepts, approves or accedes to it the present Convention shall come into force on the ninetieth day after deposit by such State of the appropriate instrument.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">XVI</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>The present Convention may be denounced by any Contracting State at any time after the date on which the Convention comes into force for that State.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Denunciation shall be effected by the deposit of an instrument with the Secretary-General of the Organization.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>A denunciation shall take effect one year, or such longer period as may be specified in the instrument of denunciation, after its deposit with the Secretary-General of the Organization.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">XVII</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>The United Nations, where it is the administering authority for a territory, or any Contracting State responsible for the international relations of a territory, shall as soon as possible consult with the appropriate authorities of such territory or take such other measures as may be appropriate, in order to extend the present Convention to that territory and may at any time by notification in writing to the Secretary-General of the Organization declare that the present Convention shall extend to such territory.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>The present Convention shall, from the date of receipt of the notification or from such other date as may be specified in the notification, extend to the territory named therein.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>The United Nations, or any Contracting State which has made a declaration under paragraph 1 of this Article may at any time after the date on which the Convention has been so extended to any territory declare by notification in writing to the Secretary-General of the Organization that the present Convention shall cease to extend to any such territory named in the notification.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr><al>The present Convention shall cease to extend to any territory mentioned in such notification one year, or such longer period as may be specified therein, after the date of receipt of the notification by the Secretary-General of the Organization.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">XVIII</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>A Conference for the purpose of revising or amending the present Convention may be convened by the Organization.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>The Organization shall convene a Conference of the Contracting States for revising or amending the present Convention at the request of not less than one-third of the Contracting States.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">XIX</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>The present Convention shall be deposited with the Secretary-General of the Organization.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>The Secretary-General of the Organization shall:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>inform all States which have signed or acceded to the Convention of</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(i)</li.nr><al>each new signature or deposit of instrument together with the date thereof;</al></li><li><li.nr>(ii)</li.nr><al>the deposit of any instrument of denunciation of this Convention together with the date of the deposit;</al></li><li><li.nr>(iii)</li.nr><al>the extension of the present Convention to any territory under paragraph 1 of Article XVII and of the termination of any such extension under the provisions of paragraph 4 of that Article stating in each case the date on which the present Convention has been or will cease to be so extended;</al></li></lijst></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>transmit certified true copies of the present Convention to all Signatory States and to all States which accede to the present Convention.</al></li></lijst></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">XX</nr>
</kop><al>As soon as the present Convention comes into force, the text shall be transmitted by the Secretary-General of the Organization to the Secretariat of the United Nations for registration and publication in accordance with Article 102 of the Charter of the United Nations.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">XXI</nr>
</kop><al>The present Convention is established in a single copy in the English and French languages, both texts being equally authentic. Official translations in the Russian and Spanish languages shall be prepared and deposited with the signed original.</al></artikel></wettekst><wetsluiting status="goed"><slotformulering><al>DONE AT LONDON, this twenty-seventh day of November one thousand nine hundred and ninety-two.</al>
							<al>IN WITNESS WHEREOF the undersigned, being duly authorized by their respective Governments for that purpose, have signed this Protocol.</al></slotformulering></wetsluiting></verdragtekst><verdragtekst><kop><label>Annex</label><titel>Certificate of insurance or other financial security in respect of
civil liability for oil pollution damage</titel></kop><vrije-tekst><tekst status="goed"><al>Issued in accordance with the provisions of Article VII of the International
Convention on Civil Liability for Oil Pollution Damage, 1992.</al><table><tgroup cols="4"><colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="*"/><colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="*"/><colspec colname="col3" colnum="3" colwidth="*"/><colspec colname="col4" colnum="4" colwidth="*"/><tbody><row><entry colname="col1"><al>Name of ship</al></entry><entry colname="col2"><al>Distinctive number or letters</al></entry><entry colname="col3"><al>Port of registry</al></entry><entry colname="col4"><al>Name and address of owner</al></entry></row><row><entry colname="col1"/><entry colname="col2"/><entry colname="col3"/><entry colname="col4"/></row></tbody></tgroup></table><al>This is to certify that there is in force in respect of the above-named ship a policy of insurance or other financial security satisfying the requirements of Article VII of the International Convention on Civil Liability for Oil Pollution Damage, 1992.</al><al>Type of Security............................................................................................................</al><al>Duration of Security.......................................................................................................</al><al>Name and Address of the Insurer(s) and/or Guarantor(s)</al><al>Name............................................................................................................................</al><al>Address...................................................................................................................................................</al><al>This certificate is valid until..............................................</al><al>Issued or certified by the Government of......................................................................................................................................</al><al>(Full designation of the State)</al><table><tgroup cols="2"><colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="*"/><colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="*"/><tbody><row><entry colname="col1"><al>At............................</al></entry><entry colname="col2"><al>On............................</al></entry></row><row><entry colname="col1"><al>(Place)</al></entry><entry colname="col2"><al>(Date)</al></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table><al>Signature and Title of issuing or certifying official</al><tussenkop>Explanatory Notes:</tussenkop><lijst><li><li.nr>1.</li.nr><al>If desired, the designation of the State may include a reference to the competent public authority of the country where the certificate is issued.</al></li><li><li.nr>2.</li.nr><al>If the total amount of security has been furnished by more than one source, the amount of each of them should be indicated.</al></li><li><li.nr>3.</li.nr><al>If security is furnished in several forms, these should be enumerated.</al></li><li><li.nr>4.</li.nr><al>The entry &#x201C;Duration of Security&#x201D; must stipulate the date on which such security takes effect.</al></li></lijst></tekst></vrije-tekst></verdragtekst></verdrag><verdrag tekst="vertaling" xml:lang="nl"><verdragtekst>
<kop>
<titel status="officieel">Internationaal Verdrag inzake de wettelijke aansprakelijkheid voor schade door verontreiniging door olie, 1992 (Aansprakelijkheidsverdrag 1992)</titel>
</kop><aanhef><preambule><al>De Staten, Partijen bij dit Verdrag,</al><al>zich bewust van de gevaren van verontreiniging, verbonden aan het vervoer van olie in bulk over de wereldzee&#xEB;n,</al><al>overtuigd van de noodzaak waarborgen te scheppen voor een passende vergoeding aan personen die schade lijden door verontreiniging veroorzaakt door het ontsnappen of doen wegvloeien van olie uit schepen,</al><al>de wens koesterende eenvormige internationale regels en procedures te aanvaarden voor het nemen van beslissingen in kwesties van aansprakelijkheid en het verschaffen van een passende vergoeding in zodanige gevallen,</al></preambule><afkondiging><al>zijn overeengekomen als volgt:</al></afkondiging></aanhef><wettekst><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">I</nr>
</kop><al>Voor de toepassing van dit Verdrag:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>1.</li.nr><al>wordt onder &#x201E;schip&#x201D; verstaan: alle zeeschepen en andere zeegaande vaartuigen, van welk type ook, gebouwd of aangepast voor het vervoer van olie in bulk als lading, met dien verstande dat een schip dat olie en andere soorten lading kan vervoeren alleen als een schip wordt beschouwd, wanneer het daadwerkelijk olie in bulk als lading vervoert en tijdens iedere reis na een zodanig vervoer, tenzij wordt aangetoond dat het geen residuen van zulk vervoer van olie in bulk aan boord heeft.</al></li><li><li.nr>2.</li.nr><al>wordt onder &#x201E;persoon&#x201D; verstaan iedere natuurlijke persoon of maatschap, alsmede ieder publiekrechtelijk of privaatrechtelijk lichaam, al of niet rechtspersoonlijkheid bezittend, hieronder begrepen een Staat of zijn staatsrechtelijke onderdelen;</al></li><li><li.nr>3.</li.nr><al>wordt onder &#x201E;eigenaar&#x201D; verstaan: de persoon of personen die als eigenaar van het schip zijn teboekgesteld of, indien er geen teboekstelling heeft plaatsgehad, de persoon of personen, die het schip in eigendom hebben.</al><al>Indien evenwel een schip eigendom is van een Staat en ge&#xEB;xploiteerd wordt door een maatschappij die in die Staat teboekstaat als de exploitant van het schip, betekent &#x201E;eigenaar&#x201D; een zodanige maatschappij;</al></li><li><li.nr>4.</li.nr><al>wordt onder &#x201E;Staat waarin het schip is teboekgesteld&#x201D; verstaan ten aanzien van teboekgestelde schepen: de Staat waarin het schip is teboekgesteld, en ten aanzien van niet teboekgestelde schepen: de Staat onder wiens vlag het schip vaart;</al></li><li><li.nr>5.</li.nr><al>wordt onder &#x201E;olie&#x201D; verstaan: alle persistente uit koolwaterstoffen bestaande minerale oli&#xEB;n, zoals ruwe olie, stookolie, zware dieselolie en smeerolie, vervoerd aan boord van een schip als lading of in de bunkers van het schip.</al></li><li><li.nr>6.</li.nr><al>wordt onder &#x201E;schade door verontreiniging&#x201D; verstaan:</al>
									<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." type="expliciet">
										<li>
											<li.nr>a.</li.nr>
											<al>verlies of schade buiten het schip veroorzaakt door bevuiling ten gevolge van het ontsnappen of doen wegvloeien van olie uit het schip, waar zulk ontsnappen of doen wegvloeien ook mag plaatsvinden, met dien verstande dat vergoeding voor andere schade aan het milieu dan winstderving ten gevolge van deze schade wordt beperkt tot de kosten van redelijke maatregelen tot herstel die daadwerkelijk worden ondernomen of zullen worden ondernomen.</al>
										</li>
										<li>
											<li.nr>b.</li.nr>
											<al>de kosten van preventieve maatregelen alsmede verlies of schade veroorzaakt door die maatregelen;</al>
										</li>
									</lijst></li><li><li.nr>7.</li.nr><al>wordt onder &#x201E;preventieve maatregelen&#x201D; verstaan: alle na het voorval door een persoon genomen redelijke maatregelen ter voorkoming of beperking van de schade door verontreiniging;</al></li><li><li.nr>8.</li.nr><al>wordt onder &#x201E;voorval&#x201D; verstaan: elk feit of elke opeenvolging van feiten met dezelfde oorzaak, waardoor schade door verontreiniging wordt veroorzaakt, of waardoor een ernstige en onmiddellijke dreiging ontstaat dat zulk een schade zal worden veroorzaakt.</al></li><li><li.nr>9.</li.nr><al>wordt onder &#x201E;Organisatie&#x201D; verstaan: de Internationale Maritieme Organisatie.</al></li><li>
											<li.nr>10.</li.nr>
											<al>wordt onder het &#x201E;Aansprakelijkheidsverdrag, 1969&#x201D; verstaan: het Internationaal Verdrag inzake de wettelijke aansprakelijkheid voor schade door verontreiniging door olie, 1969. Voor Partijen bij het Protocol van 1976 bij dit Verdrag, wordt met deze term bedoeld het Aansprakelijkheidsverdrag, 1969, zoals gewijzigd bij dat Protocol.</al>
										</li></lijst></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">II</nr>
</kop><al>Dit Verdrag is uitsluitend van toepassing op:</al>
							<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." type="expliciet">
								<li>
									<li.nr>a.</li.nr>
									<al>schade door verontreiniging veroorzaakt:</al>
									<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." type="expliciet">
										<li>
											<li.nr>i.</li.nr>
											<al>op het grondgebied, de territoriale zee daaronder begrepen, van een Verdragsluitende Staat, en</al>
											
											
										</li>
									<li>
													<li.nr>ii.</li.nr>
													<al>binnen de exclusieve economische zone van een Verdragsluitende Staat, vastgesteld overeenkomstig het internationale recht, of, indien een Verdragsluitende Staat een zodanige zone niet heeft vastgesteld, binnen een gebied buiten en grenzend aan de territoriale zee van die Staat, door die Staat vastgesteld overeenkomstig het internationale recht en dat zich niet verder uitstrekt dan 200 zeemijl van de basislijnen waarvan de breedte van zijn territoriale zee wordt gemeten;</al>
												</li></lijst>
								</li>
								<li>
									<li.nr>b.</li.nr>
									<al>preventieve maatregelen, waar ook genomen, ter voorkoming of ter beperking van zodanige schade.</al>
								</li>
							</lijst></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">III</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>De eigenaar van het schip op het tijdstip van het voorval, of, zo het voorval bestaat uit een opeenvolging van feiten, op het tijdstip van het eerste feit, is, behoudens het bepaalde in het tweede en het derde lid van dit artikel, aansprakelijk voor schade door verontreiniging, veroorzaakt door het schip als gevolg van het voorval.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>De eigenaar is niet aansprakelijk voor schade door verontreiniging, indien hij bewijst dat de schade:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>a)</li.nr><al>het gevolg is van een oorlogshandeling, vijandelijkheden, burgeroorlog, opstand of een natuurverschijnsel van een uitzonderlijke, onvermijdelijke en onweerstaanbare aard, of</al></li><li><li.nr>b)</li.nr><al>geheel en al werd veroorzaakt door een handelen of nalaten van derden, met het opzet schade te veroorzaken, of</al></li><li><li.nr>c)</li.nr><al>geheel en al werd veroorzaakt door onzorgvuldigheid of een andere onrechtmatige handeling van een Regering of andere autoriteit, verantwoordelijk voor het onderhoud van lichten of andere hulpmiddelen bij de navigatie, in de uitoefening van die functie.</al></li></lijst></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>Indien de eigenaar bewijst dat de schade door verontreiniging geheel of gedeeltelijk het gevolg is van een handelen of nalaten van de persoon, die de schade heeft geleden, met het opzet de schade te veroorzaken, of van de schuld van die persoon, kan de eigenaar geheel of gedeeltelijk worden ontheven van zijn aansprakelijkheid tegenover die persoon.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr><al>Geen vordering tot vergoeding van schade door verontreiniging kan tegen de eigenaar worden ingesteld anders dan in overeenstemming met dit Verdrag. Onverminderd het bepaalde in het vijfde lid van dit artikel kan noch op grond van dit Verdrag, noch op enige andere grond, een vordering tot vergoeding van schade door verontreiniging worden ingesteld tegen:</al>
									<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." type="expliciet">
										<li>
											<li.nr>a.</li.nr>
											<al>de ondergeschikten of lasthebbers van de eigenaar of de leden van de bemanning;</al>
										</li>
										<li>
											<li.nr>b.</li.nr>
											<al>de loods of enige andere persoon die, zonder lid van de bemanning te zijn, diensten voor het schip verricht;</al>
										</li>
										<li>
											<li.nr>c.</li.nr>
											<al>een bevrachter (hoe ook omschreven, met inbegrip van een rompbevrachter), beheerder of degene in wiens handen de exploitatie van het schip is gelegd;</al>
										</li>
										<li>
											<li.nr>d.</li.nr>
											<al>personen die met instemming van de eigenaar of in opdracht van een bevoegde overheidsinstantie hulpverleningswerkzaamheden verrichten;</al>
										</li>
										<li>
											<li.nr>e.</li.nr>
											<al>personen die preventieve maatregelen nemen;</al>
										</li>
										<li>
											<li.nr>f.</li.nr>
											<al>alle ondergeschikten of lasthebbers van personen genoemd onder c, d en e;</al>
											
										</li>
									</lijst>
								<al>tenzij de schade het gevolg is van hun persoonlijk handelen of nalaten, begaan hetzij met het opzet zodanige schade te veroorzaken hetzij roekeloos en in de wetenschap dat zodanige schade er waarschijnlijk uit zou voortvloeien.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">5</lidnr><al>Geen bepaling in dit Verdrag maakt inbreuk op enig recht van verhaal van de eigenaar tegenover derden.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">IV</nr>
</kop><al>Wanneer zich een voorval voordoet waarbij twee of meer schepen zijn betrokken en er ten gevolge daarvan schade door verontreiniging is ontstaan, zijn de eigenaren van alle betrokken schepen, tenzij zij ingevolge artikel III van aansprakelijkheid zijn ontheven, hoofdelijk aansprakelijk voor alle schade die redelijkerwijs niet te scheiden is.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">V</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>De eigenaar van een schip kan zijn aansprakelijkheid uit hoofde van dit Verdrag per voorval beperken tot een totaal bedrag dat als volgt wordt berekend:</al>
									<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
										<li>
											<li.nr>a.</li.nr>
											<al>4.510.000 rekeneenheden voor een schip met een brutotonnage van niet meer dan 5000;</al>
										</li>
										<li>
											<li.nr>b.</li.nr>
											<al>voor een schip met een grotere brutotonnage, voor elke toename van de brutotonnage met &#xE9;&#xE9;n, 631 rekeneenheden boven het onder a genoemde bedrag;</al>
											
										</li>
									</lijst><al>met dien verstande evenwel dat dit bedrag in geen geval in totaal 89.770.000 rekeneenheden te boven kan gaan.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>De eigenaar is niet gerechtigd zijn aansprakelijkheid ingevolge dit Verdrag te beperken indien wordt bewezen dat de schade door verontreiniging het gevolg is van zijn persoonlijk handelen of nalaten, begaan hetzij met het opzet zodanige schade te veroorzaken, hetzij roekeloos en in de wetenschap dat zodanige schade er waarschijnlijk uit zou voortvloeien.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>Ten einde zich te kunnen beroepen op de in het eerste lid van dit artikel bedoelde beperking, moet de eigenaar een fonds vormen tot een bedrag gelijk aan het maximum van zijn aansprakelijkheid bij de rechterlijke of andere bevoegde autoriteit van een Verdragsluitende Staat binnen wiens grondgebied een vordering op grond van artikel IX wordt ingesteld, of, indien geen vordering wordt ingesteld, bij een rechterlijke of andere bevoegde autoriteit van een Verdragsluitende Staat binnen wiens grondgebied een vordering op grond van artikel IX kan worden ingesteld. Het fonds kan worden gevormd door het storten van de geldsom of door het stellen van een bankgarantie of iedere andere garantie welke aanvaardbaar is volgens de wetgeving van de Verdragsluitende Staat waar het fonds wordt gevormd en welke door de rechterlijke of andere bevoegde autoriteit genoegzaam wordt geacht.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr><al>Het fonds wordt verdeeld onder de schuldeisers in evenredigheid met de bedragen van hun erkende vorderingen.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">5</lidnr><al>Indien v&#xF3;&#xF3;r de verdeling van het fonds de eigenaar of een van zijn ondergeschikten of lasthebbers, of een persoon die hem een verzekering of andere zekerheid heeft verschaft, in verband met het voorval een vergoeding terzake van schade door verontreiniging hebben betaald, treden deze personen bij wege van subrogatie, tot het bedrag dat zij hebben betaald, in de rechten die de door hen schadeloos gestelde persoon op grond van dit Verdrag zou hebben gehad.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">6</lidnr><al>Het recht van subrogatie, bedoeld in het vijfde lid van dit artikel kan ook worden uitgeoefend door andere dan de daarin genoemde personen met betrekking tot enige vergoeding voor schade door verontreiniging die zij mochten hebben betaald, maar alleen voor zover een zodanige subrogatie is geoorloofd volgens de toepasselijke nationale wetgeving.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">7</lidnr><al>Wanneer de eigenaar of enige andere persoon aantoont dat hij gedwongen zou kunnen worden op een later tijdstip geheel of ten dele een zodanige schadevergoeding te betalen terzake waarvan hij, indien de vergoeding zou zijn betaald v&#xF3;&#xF3;r de verdeling van het fonds, ingevolge het vijfde of het zesde lid van dit artikel bij wege van subrogatie rechten zou hebben verkregen, dan kan de rechterlijke of andere bevoegde autoriteit bevelen dat voorlopig een bedrag wordt terzijde gesteld dat voldoende is om het deze persoon mogelijk te maken op een later tijdstip zijn rechten tegen het fonds geldend te maken.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">8</lidnr><al>Vorderingen die betrekking hebben op door de eigenaar vrijwillig en binnen de grenzen der redelijkheid gedane uitgaven en gebrachte offers ter voorkoming of beperking van schade door verontreiniging staan in rang gelijk met andere vorderingen op het fonds.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">9</lidnr><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
												<li><li.nr>a.</li.nr><al>De &#x201E;rekeneenheid&#x201D; bedoeld in het eerste lid van dit artikel is het bijzondere trekkingsrecht zoals dit is omschreven door het Internationale Monetaire Fonds. De in het eerste lid genoemde bedragen worden omgerekend in een nationale munteenheid volgens de waarde van die munteenheid ten opzichte van het bijzondere trekkingsrecht op de datum van de vorming van het in het derde lid bedoelde fonds. De waarde van de nationale munteenheid, uitgedrukt in bijzondere trekkingsrechten, van een Verdragsluitende Staat die Lid is van het Internationale Monetaire Fonds, wordt berekend overeenkomstig de waarderingsmethode die door het Internationale Monetaire Fonds op de desbetreffende datum wordt toegepast voor zijn eigen verrichtingen en transacties. De waarde van de nationale munteenheid, uitgedrukt in bijzondere trekkingsrechten, van een Verdragsluitende Staat die geen lid is van het Internationale Monetaire Fonds, wordt berekend op een door die Staat vastgestelde wijze.</al></li><li>
													<li.nr>b.</li.nr>
													<al>Niettemin kan een Verdragsluitende Staat die geen Lid is van het Internationale Monetaire Fonds en wiens wet de toepassing van de bepalingen van het negende lid, onder a, niet toelaat, op het tijdstip van bekrachtiging, aanvaarding, goedkeuring van dan wel toetreding tot dit Verdrag of op enig tijdstip nadien, verklaren dat de in het negende lid, onder a, bedoelde rekeneenheid gelijk zal zijn aan 15 goudfranken. De in dit lid bedoelde goudfrank komt overeen met vijfenzestig en een half milligram goud van een gehalte van negenhonderdduizendste fijn. De omrekening van de goudfrank in de nationale munteenheid geschiedt volgens de wet van de betrokken Staat.</al>
													
												</li>
											<li>
															<li.nr>c.</li.nr>
															<al>De in de laatste zin van het negende lid, onder a, genoemde berekening en de in het negende lid, onder b, genoemde omrekening geschieden op zodanige wijze dat in de nationale munteenheid van de Verdragsluitende Staat zoveel mogelijk dezelfde werkelijke waarde tot uitdrukking komt voor de bedragen genoemd in het eerste lid als zou voortvloeien uit de toepassing van de eerste drie zinnen van het negende lid, onder a. Bij nederlegging van een akte van bekrachtiging, aanvaarding, goedkeuring van of toetreding tot dit Verdrag en telkens wanneer een verandering optreedt in hun wijze van berekening ingevolge het negende lid, onder a, of in het resultaat van de omrekening ingevolge het negende lid, onder b, delen de Verdragsluitende Staten de depositaris hun wijze van berekening dan wel het resultaat van de omrekening mede.</al>
														</li></lijst></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">10</lidnr><al>Voor de toepassing van dit artikel is de brutotonnage van het schip de brutotonnage berekend overeenkomstig de voorschriften voor de meting vervat in Bijlage I van het Internationaal Verdrag betreffende de meting van schepen, 1969.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">11</lidnr><al>De verzekeraar of persoon die financi&#xEB;le zekerheid stelt heeft het recht tot het vormen van een fonds in overeenstemming met dit artikel op dezelfde voorwaarden en met dezelfde rechtsgevolgen als ware het door de eigenaar gevormd. Een zodanig fonds kan zelfs worden gevormd indien, ingevolge het bepaalde in het tweede lid, de eigenaar niet gerechtigd is zijn aansprakelijkheid te beperken, maar de vorming daarvan laat dan de rechten van de schuldeisers tegenover de eigenaar onverlet.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">VI</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Indien na een voorval de eigenaar overeenkomstig artikel V een fonds heeft gevormd en gerechtigd is zijn aansprakelijkheid te beperken,</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>zal een persoon die uit dat voorval een vordering wegens schade door verontreiniging heeft, ter zake van die vordering geen rechten kunnen doen gelden op andere goederen van die eigenaar;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>zal de rechterlijke of andere bevoegde autoriteit van een Verdragsluitende Staat de opheffing bevelen van beslag, gelegd op schepen of andere eigendommen van de eigenaar terzake van een vordering tot vergoeding van schade door verontreiniging voortvloeiende uit dat voorval en op overeenkomstige wijze handelen ten aanzien van borgtocht of andere ter voorkoming van een zodanig beslag gestelde zekerheid.</al></li></lijst></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Het voorgaande is evenwel alleen van toepassing indien de schuldeiser toegang heeft tot de rechtbank die het fonds beheert en het fonds daadwerkelijk beschikbaar is tot voldoening van zijn vordering.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">VII</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>De eigenaar van een in een Verdragsluitende Staat teboekgesteld schip dat meer dan 2000 ton olie in bulk als lading vervoert, is gehouden een verzekering of andere financi&#xEB;le zekerheid, zoals een bankgarantie of een door een internationaal schadefonds afgegeven certificaat in stand te houden tot dekking van zijn aansprakelijkheid voor schade door verontreiniging volgens dit Verdrag, tot een bedrag gelijk aan het maximum van zijn aansprakelijkheid ingevolge het eerste lid van artikel V.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Een certificaat houdende verklaring dat een overeenkomst van verzekering of een andere financi&#xEB;le zekerheid in overeenstemming met de bepalingen van dit Verdrag van kracht is, wordt aan elk schip afgegeven, nadat de bevoegde autoriteit van een Verdragsluitende Staat heeft vastgesteld dat aan de eisen van het eerste lid is voldaan. Met betrekking tot een schip teboekgesteld in een Verdragsluitende Staat wordt zulk een certificaat afgegeven of gewaarmerkt door de bevoegde autoriteit van de Staat waar het schip is teboekgesteld; met betrekking tot een schip dat niet in een Verdragsluitende Staat is teboekgesteld, kan het worden afgegeven of gewaarmerkt door de bevoegde autoriteit van een Verdragsluitende Staat. Dit certificaat heeft de vorm van het aangehechte model en bevat de navolgende gegevens:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>naam van het schip en van de plaats van teboekstelling;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>naam en adres van de eigenaar en van diens hoofdkantoor;</al></li><li><li.nr>(c)</li.nr><al>soort der zekerheid;</al></li><li><li.nr>(d)</li.nr><al>naam en adres van het hoofdkantoor van de verzekeraar of de persoon die de zekerheid stelt en, waar dienstig, het adres van het kantoor waar de verzekering is gesloten of de zekerheid is gesteld;</al></li><li><li.nr>(e)</li.nr><al>geldigheidsduur van het certificaat, die niet langer kan zijn dan de geldigheidsduur van de verzekering of andere zekerheid.</al></li></lijst></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>Het certificaat wordt gesteld in de offici&#xEB;le taal of de offici&#xEB;le talen van de Staat waar het wordt afgegeven. Indien de gebruikte taal noch de Franse, noch de Engelse is, moet de tekst een vertaling in een van deze talen bevatten.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr><al>Het certificaat moet zich aan boord van het schip bevinden en een afschrift moet worden nedergelegd bij de autoriteiten die het register houden waarin het schip staat teboekgesteld of, indien het schip niet in een Verdragsluitende Staat is teboekgesteld, bij de autoriteiten van de Staat die het certificaat afgeeft of waarmerkt.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">5</lidnr><al>Een verzekering of een andere financi&#xEB;le zekerheid voldoet niet aan de bepalingen van dit artikel, indien zij, om andere redenen dan het verstrijken van haar geldigheidsduur zoals vermeld in het certificaat ingevolge het tweede lid van dit artikel, kan vervallen alvorens drie maanden zijn verlopen sedert de datum waarop aan de autoriteiten bedoeld in het vierde lid van dit artikel mededeling is gedaan van haar be&#xEB;indiging, tenzij het certificaat bij deze autoriteiten is ingeleverd, dan wel binnen bedoelde termijn een nieuw certificaat is afgegeven. Het vorenstaande is eveneens van toepassing op alle wijzigingen die ten gevolge hebben dat de verzekering of zekerheid niet langer voldoet aan de bepalingen van dit artikel.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">6</lidnr><al>Onverminderd het in dit artikel bepaalde stelt de Staat waar het schip is teboekgesteld de voorwaarden vast betreffende de afgifte en geldigheid van het certificaat.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">7</lidnr><al>Certificaten, afgegeven of gewaarmerkt onder het gezag van een Verdragsluitende Staat overeenkomstig het tweede lid, worden voor de toepassing van dit Verdrag erkend door andere Verdragsluitende Staten, als bezittende dezelfde geldigheid als door deze afgegeven of gewaarmerkte certificaten, zelfs indien zij zijn afgegeven of gewaarmerkt met betrekking tot een schip dat niet in een Verdragsluitende Staat is teboekgesteld. Een Verdragsluitende Staat kan te allen tijde verzoeken om overleg met de Staat die de afgifte of waarmerking verricht, indien hij reden heeft aan te nemen dat de in het certificaat genoemde verzekeraar of degene die de garantie heeft gesteld financieel niet in staat is te voldoen aan de hem door dit Verdrag opgelegde verplichtingen.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">8</lidnr><al>Vorderingen tot vergoeding van schade door verontreiniging kunnen rechtstreeks worden ingesteld tegen de verzekeraar of persoon die financi&#xEB;le zekerheid stelt ter dekking van de aansprakelijkheid van de eigenaar wegens schade door verontreiniging. In dit geval kan de verweerder, zelfs indien de eigenaar overeenkomstig artikel V, tweede lid, niet gerechtigd is zijn aansprakelijkheid te beperken, zich beroepen op de in artikel V, eerste lid, omschreven beperking van aansprakelijkheid. Hij mag voorts zich beroepen op de verweermiddelen (anders dan het faillissement of de liquidatie van de eigenaar) waarop de eigenaar zelf een beroep zou hebben kunnen doen. Voorts kan de verweerder een beroep doen op het verweer dat de schade door verontreiniging het gevolg is van opzettelijk wangedrag van de eigenaar zelf, maar de verweerder kan zich niet beroepen op enig ander verweermiddel dat hij zou hebben kunnen aanvoeren in een door de eigenaar tegen hem aangespannen rechtsgeding. De verweerder heeft steeds het recht te vorderen dat de eigenaar mede in het geding wordt betrokken.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">9</lidnr><al>Gelden uit een verzekering of andere financi&#xEB;le zekerheid, welke ingevolge het eerste lid van dit artikel wordt in stand gehouden, zijn uitsluitend beschikbaar voor de voldoening van vorderingen ingevolge dit Verdrag.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">10</lidnr><al>Een Verdragsluitende Staat staat niet toe dat onder zijn vlag varende schepen waarop dit artikel van toepassing is, voor de handelsvaart worden gebezigd, tenzij een certificaat is afgegeven ingevolge het tweede of het twaalfde lid van dit artikel.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">11</lidnr><al>Onverminderd het in dit artikel bepaalde moet elke Verdragsluitende Staat er zorg voor dragen dat in zijn nationale wetgeving wordt voorgeschreven dat verzekering of andere zekerheid tot de in het eerste lid van dit artikel genoemde omvang verplicht is voor elk schip, waar ook teboekgesteld, dat een haven op zijn grondgebied binnenloopt of verlaat, dan wel aankomt bij of vertrekt van een buitengaats doch binnen zijn territoriale zee gelegen laad- of losinstallatie, wanneer het schip daadwerkelijk meer dan 2.000 ton olie in bulk als lading vervoert.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">12</lidnr><al>Is met betrekking tot een schip dat in eigendom toebehoort aan een Verdragsluitende Staat geen verzekering afgesloten of geen financi&#xEB;le zekerheid gesteld, dan zijn de desbetreffende bepalingen van dit artikel op dat schip niet van toepassing, maar het schip moet wel zijn voorzien van een certificaat, afgegeven door de bevoegde autoriteiten van de Staat waar het is teboekgesteld, houdende de verklaring dat het schip eigendom is van de Staat en dat de aansprakelijkheid voor het schip gedekt is binnen de grenzen van artikel V, eerste lid. Dit certificaat wordt zoveel mogelijk opgesteld volgens het in het tweede lid van dit artikel voorgeschreven model.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">VIII</nr>
</kop><al>Het recht op schadevergoeding krachtens dit Verdrag vervalt wanneer niet binnen drie jaar na de datum waarop de schade is ontstaan een rechtsvordering is ingesteld. In geen geval kan echter een rechtsvordering worden ingesteld nadat zes jaar zijn verstreken na de datum van het voorval dat de schade heeft veroorzaakt. Indien dit voorval wordt gevormd door een opeenvolging van feiten, loopt de termijn van zes jaar van de datum van het eerste feit.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">IX</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Indien een voorval schade door verontreiniging heeft veroorzaakt op het grondgebied van &#xE9;&#xE9;n of meer Verdragsluitende Staten, de territoriale zee of een gebied zoals bedoeld in artikel II daaronder begrepen, dan wel preventieve maatregelen zijn genomen ter voorkoming of beperking van schade door verontreiniging op dit grondgebied, de territoriale zee of het gebied daaronder begrepen, dan kunnen vorderingen tot schadevergoeding slechts worden ingesteld bij de rechter van die Verdragsluitende Staat of Staten. Van het instellen van zodanige vordering moet aan de verweerder binnen redelijke termijn kennis worden gegeven.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Iedere Verdragsluitende Staat draagt er zorg voor dat zijn gerechten bevoegd zijn kennis te nemen van deze vorderingen tot schadevergoeding.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>Nadat het fonds overeenkomstig het bepaalde in artikel V is gevormd, is de rechter van de Staat waar het fonds is gevormd bij uitsluiting bevoegd te beslissen in alle aangelegenheden betreffende de toedeling en verdeling van het fonds.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">X</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Beslissingen van een uit hoofde van artikel IX bevoegde rechter welke voor tenuitvoerlegging vatbaar zijn in de Staat waar zij zijn gegeven en waartegen geen gewoon rechtsmiddel meer openstaat worden erkend in elke andere Verdragsluitende Staat, tenzij:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>de beslissing is verkregen door bedrog; of</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>de verweerder niet binnen een redelijke termijn is verwittigd en niet behoorlijk in de gelegenheid is gesteld zijn zaak uiteen te zetten.</al></li></lijst></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Een beslissing welke ingevolge het eerste lid van dit artikel is erkend, is vatbaar voor tenuitvoerlegging in iedere Verdragsluitende Staat, zodra de in die Staat vereiste formaliteiten zijn vervuld. Deze formaliteiten mogen niet leiden tot een hernieuwd onderzoek van de zaak.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">XI</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>De bepalingen van dit Verdrag zijn niet van toepassing op oorlogsschepen of andere schepen in eigendom van of ge&#xEB;xploiteerd door een Staat ten tijde dat zij alleen worden gebruikt in dienst van de overheid voor andere dan handelsdoeleinden.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Met betrekking tot schepen die eigendom zijn van een Verdragsluitende Staat en die gebruikt worden voor handelsdoeleinden, kan elke Staat in rechte worden aangesproken voor de rechter die ingevolge artikel IX bevoegd is, en doet afstand van beroep op enig verweer dat is gegrond op zijn hoedanigheid van soevereine Staat.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">XII</nr>
</kop><al>Dit Verdrag gaat boven andere internationale overeenkomsten die op de datum waarop dit Verdrag is opengesteld voor ondertekening, van kracht zijn of openstaan voor ondertekening, bekrachtiging of toetreding, doch uitsluitend voor zover deze overeenkomsten daarmede in strijd zouden zijn; de bepalingen van dit Verdrag laten nochtans de uit bedoelde internationale overeenkomsten voortvloeiende verplichtingen van Verdragsluitende Staten tegenover niet-Verdragsluitende Staten onverlet.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Artikel</label>
								<nr>XII bis</nr>
								<titel> Overgangsbepalingen</titel>
							</kop>
							<al>De volgende overgangsbepalingen zijn van toepassing in het geval van een Staat die op het tijdstip van een voorval Partij is bij zowel dit Verdrag als het Aansprakelijkheidsverdrag, 1969:</al>
							<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." type="expliciet">
								<li>
									<li.nr>a.</li.nr>
									<al>wanneer een voorval schade door verontreiniging heeft veroorzaakt binnen de werkingssfeer van dit Verdrag wordt aan de aansprakelijkheid ingevolge dit Verdrag geacht te zijn voldaan indien, en voor zover, deze ook ontstaat ingevolge het Aansprakelijkheidsverdrag, 1969;</al>
								</li>
								<li>
									<li.nr>b.</li.nr>
									<al>wanneer een voorval schade door verontreiniging heeft veroorzaakt binnen de werkingssfeer van dit Verdrag en de Staat Partij is bij zowel dit Verdrag als het Internationaal Verdrag betreffende de instelling van een Internationaal Fonds voor vergoeding van schade door verontreiniging door olie, 1971, is van aansprakelijkheid waaraan nog moet worden voldaan na de toepassing van letter a van dit artikel, ingevolge dit Verdrag slechts sprake voor zover de schade door verontreiniging onvergoed blijft na toepassing van het genoemde Verdrag van 1971;</al>
									
									
								</li>
								<li>
									<li.nr>c.</li.nr>
									<al>bij de toepassing van artikel III, vierde lid, van dit Verdrag wordt de uitdrukking &#x201E;dit Verdrag&#x201D; zo uitgelegd dat daarmede wordt verwezen naar dit Verdrag of naar het Aansprakelijkheidsverdrag, 1969, al naar gelang passend is;</al>
								</li>
								<li>
									<li.nr>d.</li.nr>
									<al>bij de toepassing van artikel V, derde lid, van dit Verdrag wordt het totale bedrag van het te vormen fonds verlaagd met het bedrag waarmede aan de aansprakelijkheid geacht wordt te zijn voldaan overeenkomstig letter a van dit artikel.</al>
								</li>
							</lijst>
						</artikel>
						<artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Artikel</label>
								<nr>XII ter</nr>
								<titel> Slotbepalingen</titel>
							</kop>
							<al>De slotbepalingen van dit Verdrag zijn de artikelen 12 tot en met 18 van het Protocol van 1992 tot wijziging van het Aansprakelijkheidsverdrag, 1969. Verwijzingen in dit Verdrag naar Verdragsluitende Staten dienen te worden uitgelegd als verwijzingen naar de Verdragsluitende Staten bij dat Protocol.</al>
						</artikel><hoofdstuk><kop><titel>SLOTBEPALINGEN</titel></kop><artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Artikel</label><nr>12</nr><titel>Ondertekening, bekrachtiging, aanvaarding, goedkeuring en toetreding</titel></kop><lid>
								<lidnr>1</lidnr>
								<al>Dit Protocol staat open voor ondertekening te Londen van 15 januari 1993 tot en met 14 januari 1994 door alle Staten.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr>2</lidnr>
								<al>Onverminderd het bepaalde in het vierde lid kan een Staat Partij bij dit Protocol worden door:</al>
								<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." type="expliciet">
									<li>
										<li.nr>a.</li.nr>
										<al>ondertekening onder voorbehoud van bekrachtiging, aanvaarding of goedkeuring gevolgd door bekrachtiging, aanvaarding of goedkeuring; of</al>
									</li>
									<li>
										<li.nr>b.</li.nr>
										<al>toetreding.</al>
									</li>
								</lijst>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr>3</lidnr>
								<al>Bekrachtiging, aanvaarding, goedkeuring of toetreding geschiedt door nederlegging van een daartoe strekkende akte bij de Secretaris-Generaal van de Organisatie.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr>4</lidnr>
								<al>Een Verdragsluitende Staat bij het Internationaal Verdrag betreffende de instelling van een Internationaal Fonds voor vergoeding van schade door verontreiniging door olie, 1971, hierna te noemen het Fondsverdrag, 1971, kan dit Protocol slechts bekrachtigen, aanvaarden, goedkeuren of ertoe toetreden indien hij tegelijkertijd het Protocol van 1992 tot wijziging van dat Verdrag bekrachtigt, aanvaardt, goedkeurt of ertoe toetreedt, tenzij hij het Fondsverdrag, 1971, opzegt met ingang van de datum waarop dit Protocol voor die Staat in werking treedt.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr>5</lidnr>
								<al>Een Staat die Partij is bij dit Protocol maar geen Partij is bij het Aansprakelijkheidsverdrag, 1969, is gebonden door de bepalingen van het Aansprakelijkheidsverdrag, 1969, zoals gewijzigd bij dit Protocol, met betrekking tot andere Staten die hierbij Partij zijn, maar is niet gebonden door de bepalingen van het Aansprakelijkheidsverdrag, 1969, met betrekking tot Staten die daarbij Partij zijn.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr>6</lidnr>
								<al>Akten van bekrachtiging, aanvaarding, goedkeuring of toetreding die zijn nedergelegd nadat een wijziging van het Aansprakelijkheidsverdrag, 1969, zoals gewijzigd bij dit Protocol, in werking is getreden, worden geacht van toepassing te zijn op het aldus gewijzigde Verdrag, zoals gewijzigd door bedoelde wijziging.</al>
							</lid>
						</artikel><artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Artikel</label>
								<nr>13</nr>
								<titel>Inwerkingtreding</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr>1</lidnr>
								<al>Dit Protocol treedt in werking twaalf maanden na de datum waarop tien Staten, waaronder vier Staten met elk niet minder dan een miljoen brutotonnage van tankschepen, akten van bekrachtiging, aanvaarding, goedkeuring of toetreding hebben nedergelegd bij de Secretaris-Generaal van de Organisatie.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr>2</lidnr>
								<al>Iedere Verdragsluitende Staat bij het Fondsverdrag, 1971, kan evenwel, op het tijdstip van nederlegging van zijn akte van bekrachtiging, aanvaarding, goedkeuring of toetreding met betrekking tot dit Protocol, verklaren dat deze akte niet eerder van kracht wordt beschouwd voor de toepassing van dit artikel dan aan het einde van het tijdvak van zes maanden genoemd in artikel 31 van het Protocol van 1992 bij het Fondsverdrag, 1971. Een Staat die geen Verdragsluitende Staat bij het Fondsverdrag, 1971, is, doch die een akte van bekrachtiging, aanvaarding, goedkeuring of toetreding met betrekking tot het Protocol van 1992 tot wijziging van het Fondsverdrag, 1971, nederlegt, kan ook tegelijkertijd een verklaring overeenkomstig dit lid afleggen.</al>
								
								
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr>3</lidnr>
								<al>Iedere Staat die een verklaring overeenkomstig het voorgaande lid heeft afgelegd, kan deze te allen tijde intrekken door middel van een kennisgeving gericht aan de Secretaris-Generaal van de Organisatie. Een zodanige intrekking wordt van kracht op de datum waarop de kennisgeving wordt ontvangen, met dien verstande dat deze Staat geacht wordt zijn akte van bekrachtiging, aanvaarding, goedkeuring of toetreding met betrekking tot dit Protocol op die datum te hebben nedergelegd.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr>4</lidnr>
								<al>Ten aanzien van elke Staat die dit Protocol bekrachtigt, aanvaardt, goedkeurt of ertoe toetreedt nadat aan de in het eerste lid gestelde eisen voor inwerkingtreding is voldaan, treedt dit Protocol in werking twaalf maanden na de datum van nederlegging door die Staat van de daartoe strekkende akte.</al>
							</lid>
						</artikel><artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Artikel</label>
								<nr>14</nr>
								<titel>Herziening en wijziging</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr>1</lidnr>
								<al>De Organisatie kan een conferentie tot herziening of wijziging van het Aansprakelijkheidsverdrag, 1992, bijeenroepen.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr>2</lidnr>
								<al>De Organisatie roept een conferentie van de Verdragsluitende Staten bijeen tot herziening of wijziging van het Aansprakelijkheidsverdrag, 1992, op verzoek van ten minste een derde van de Verdragsluitende Staten.</al>
								
							</lid>
							</artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Artikel</label><nr>15</nr><titel>Wijzigingen van de beperkingsbedragen</titel></kop><lid>
								<lidnr>1</lidnr>
								<al>Op verzoek van ten minste een vierde van de Verdragsluitende Staten worden voorstellen tot wijziging van de aansprakelijkheidsgrenzen, neergelegd in artikel V, eerste lid, van het Verdrag, zoals gewijzigd bij dit Protocol, door de Secretaris-Generaal toegezonden aan alle Leden van de Organisatie en aan alle Verdragsluitende Staten.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr>2</lidnr>
								<al>Elke voorgestelde en zoals hierboven aangegeven toegezonden wijziging wordt voorgelegd aan de Juridische Commissie van de Organisatie ter overweging op een datum tenminste zes maanden na de datum van toezending.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr>3</lidnr>
								<al>Alle Verdragsluitende Staten bij het Aansprakelijkheidsverdrag, 1969, zoals gewijzigd bij dit Protocol, ongeacht of zij Lid van de Organisatie zijn, zijn gerechtigd deel te nemen aan de werkzaamheden van de Juridische Commissie ter overweging en aanneming van wijzigingen.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr>4</lidnr>
								<al>Wijzigingen worden aangenomen met een tweederde meerderheid van de Verdragsluitende Staten die aanwezig zijn en hun stem uitbrengen in de Juridische Commissie, welke is uitgebreid zoals bepaald in het derde lid, mits ten minste de helft van de Verdragsluitende Staten aanwezig is op het tijdstip van de stemming.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr>5</lidnr>
								<al>Wanneer de Commissie een voorstel tot wijziging van de grenzen bespreekt, houdt zij rekening met de ervaring opgedaan bij voorvallen en in het bijzonder met het bedrag van de daaruit voortvloeiende schade, met wijzigingen in geldswaarden, en de gevolgen van de voorgestelde wijziging voor de kosten van verzekering. Zij houdt voorts rekening met de samenhang van de grenzen van artikel V, eerste lid, van het Aansprakelijkheidsverdrag, 1969, zoals gewijzigd bij dit Protocol en die in artikel 4, vierde lid, van het Internationaal Verdrag betreffende de instelling van een Internationaal Fonds voor vergoeding van schade door verontreiniging door olie, 1992.</al>
								
							</lid>
							<lid><lidnr>6</lidnr><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." type="expliciet">
											<li><li.nr>a.</li.nr><al>Er mag geen wijziging van de aansprakelijkheidsgrenzen ingevolge dit artikel worden overwogen v&#xF3;&#xF3;r 15 januari 1998, en evenmin binnen vijf jaar vanaf de datum van inwerkingtreding van een voorgaande wijziging ingevolge dit artikel. Er kan geen wijziging ingevolge dit artikel worden overwogen alvorens dit Protocol in werking is getreden.</al></li><li>
												<li.nr>b.</li.nr>
												<al>Er mag geen grens zodanig worden verhoogd dat deze een bedrag overschrijdt dat overeenkomt met de grens vervat in het Aansprakelijkheidsverdrag, 1969, zoals gewijzigd bij dit Protocol, verhoogd met zes procent per jaar berekend op samengestelde basis vanaf 15 januari 1993.</al>
											</li>
											<li>
												<li.nr>c.</li.nr>
												<al>Er mag geen grens zodanig worden verhoogd, dat deze een bedrag overschrijdt dat overeenkomt met de grens vervat in het Aansprakelijkheidsverdrag, 1969, zoals gewijzigd bij dit Protocol, vermenigvuldigd met drie.</al>
											</li>
										</lijst></lid><lid>
								<lidnr>7</lidnr>
								<al>Elke wijziging aangenomen overeenkomstig het vierde lid wordt door de Organisatie ter kennis gebracht van alle Verdragsluitende Staten. De wijziging wordt geacht te zijn aanvaard aan het einde van een tijdvak van achttien maanden na de datum van kennisgeving, tenzij binnen dat tijdvak niet minder dan een vierde van de Staten die Verdragsluitende Staten waren op het tijdstip van aanneming van de wijziging door de Juridische Commissie de Organisatie hebben medegedeeld dat zij de wijziging niet aanvaarden, in welk geval de wijziging is verworpen en deze niet van kracht wordt.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr>8</lidnr>
								<al>Een wijziging die geacht wordt te zijn aanvaard overeenkomstig het zevende lid, treedt in werking achttien maanden na aanvaarding ervan.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr>9</lidnr>
								<al>Alle Verdragsluitende Staten zijn gebonden door de wijziging, tenzij zij ten minste zes maanden voordat de wijziging in werking treedt dit Protocol opzeggen overeenkomstig artikel 16, eerste en tweede lid. Deze opzegging wordt van kracht wanneer de wijziging in werking treedt.</al>
								
							</lid>
						<lid><lidnr>10</lidnr><al>Wanneer een wijziging door de Juridische Commissie is aangenomen, maar het tijdvak van achttien maanden voor de aanvaarding ervan nog niet is verstreken, is een Staat die gedurende dat tijdvak Verdragsluitende Staat wordt, door de wijziging gebonden indien deze in werking treedt. Een Staat die na dat tijdvak Verdragsluitende Staat wordt, is gebonden door een wijziging die overeenkomstig het zevende lid is aanvaard. In de gevallen bedoeld in dit lid wordt een Staat gebonden door een wijziging wanneer deze wijziging in werking treedt, of wanneer dit Protocol voor die Staat in werking treedt, indien deze datum later valt.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Artikel</label>
								<nr>16</nr>
								<titel>Opzegging</titel>
							</kop>
							<lid>
								<lidnr>1</lidnr>
								<al>Een Partij kan dit Protocol, na de datum waarop het voor die Partij in werking is getreden, te allen tijde opzeggen.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr>2</lidnr>
								<al>Opzegging geschiedt door nederlegging van een akte bij de Secretaris-Generaal van de Organisatie.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr>3</lidnr>
								<al>Een opzegging wordt van kracht twaalf maanden na de nederlegging van de akte van opzegging bij de Secretaris-Generaal van de Organisatie of na een langere termijn wanneer zulks in die akte is bepaald.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr>4</lidnr>
								<al>Wat de Partijen bij dit Protocol betreft, wordt opzegging door een van hen van het Aansprakelijkheidsverdrag, 1969, overeenkomstig artikel XVI daarvan niet op enigerlei wijze uitgelegd als een opzegging van het Aansprakelijkheidsverdrag, 1969, zoals gewijzigd bij dit Protocol.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr>5</lidnr>
								<al>Opzegging van het Protocol van 1992 tot wijziging van het Fondsverdrag, 1971, door een Staat die Partij blijft bij het Fondsverdrag, 1971, wordt geacht een opzegging te zijn van dit Protocol. Die opzegging wordt van kracht op de datum waarop de opzegging van het Protocol van 1992 tot wijziging van het Fondsverdrag, 1971, van kracht wordt overeenkomstig artikel 34 van dat Protocol.</al>
								
							</lid>
							</artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Artikel</label><nr status="officieel">17</nr><titel status="officieel">Depositaris</titel></kop><lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
								<al>Dit Protocol en alle ingevolge artikel 15 aanvaarde wijzigingen worden nedergelegd bij de Secretaris-Generaal van de Organisatie.</al>
							</lid>
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
								<al>De Secretaris-Generaal van de Organisatie:</al>
								<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
									<li>
										<li.nr>a.</li.nr>
										<al>stelt alle Staten die dit Protocol hebben ondertekend of ertoe zijn toegetreden in kennis van:</al>
									<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
									<li><li.nr>i. </li.nr><al>elke nieuwe ondertekening of nederlegging van een akte en de datum daarvan;</al></li><li>
										<li.nr>ii.</li.nr>
										<al>elke verklaring en kennisgeving ingevolge artikel 13, en elke verklaring en mededeling ingevolge artikel V, negende lid, van het Aansprakelijkheidsverdrag, 1992;</al>
										
									</li>
									<li>
												<li.nr>iii.</li.nr>
												<al>de datum van inwerkingtreding van dit Protocol;</al>
											</li><li>
										<li.nr>iv.</li.nr>
										<al>alle voorstellen tot wijziging van de aansprakelijkheidsgrenzen die zijn gedaan overeenkomstig artikel 15, eerste lid;</al>
										
									</li>
									<li><li.nr>v.</li.nr><al>alle wijzigingen die zijn aangenomen overeenkomstig artikel 15, vierde lid;</al></li><li>
										<li.nr>vi.</li.nr>
										<al>alle wijzigingen die ingevolge artikel 15, zevende lid, worden geacht te zijn aanvaard alsmede de datum waarop die wijzigingen in werking treden overeenkomstig het achtste en het negende lid van dat artikel;</al>
										
									</li>
									<li>
												<li.nr>vii.</li.nr>
												<al>de nederlegging van een akte van opzegging van dit Protocol, de datum van nederlegging en de datum waarop deze van kracht wordt;</al>
											</li>
											<li>
												<li.nr>viii.</li.nr>
												<al>alle opzeggingen die geacht worden te zijn gedaan ingevolge artikel 16, vijfde lid;</al>
											</li><li>
										<li.nr>ix.</li.nr>
										<al>alle mededelingen die ingevolge een artikel van dit Protocol vereist zijn;</al>
										
									</li>
								</lijst></li>
								<li>
												<li.nr>b.</li.nr>
												<al>zendt voor eensluidend gewaarmerkte afschriften van dit Protocol toe aan alle ondertekenende Staten en aan alle Staten die tot dit Protocol toetreden.</al>
											</li></lijst>
							</lid>
							
							<lid>
								<lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
								<al> Zodra dit Protocol in werking treedt, wordt de tekst door de Secretaris-Generaal van de Organisatie toegezonden aan het Secretariaat van de Verenigde Naties ter registratie en publikatie overeenkomstig artikel 102 van het Handvest der Verenigde Naties.</al>
							</lid>
						</artikel><artikel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>Artikel</label>
								<nr>18</nr>
								<titel>Talen</titel>
							</kop>
							<al>Dit Protocol is opgesteld in een enkel oorspronkelijk exemplaar in de Arabische, de Chinese, de Engelse, de Franse, de Russische en de Spaanse taal, zijnde alle teksten gelijkelijk authentiek.</al>
						</artikel></hoofdstuk><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">XIII</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Dit Verdrag staat open voor ondertekening tot 31 december 1970 en staat daarna open voor toetreding.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Lid-Staten van de Verenigde Naties of van een der Gespecialiseerde Organisaties of van de Internationale Organisatie voor Atoomenergie, dan wel Staten die partij zijn bij het Statuut van het Internationale Gerechtshof kunnen partij worden bij dit Verdrag door:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>ondertekening zonder voorbehoud van bekrachtiging, aanvaarding of goedkeuring;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>ondertekening onder voorbehoud van bekrachtiging, aanvaarding of goedkeuring, gevolgd door bekrachtiging, aanvaarding of goedkeuring; of</al></li><li><li.nr>(c)</li.nr><al>toetreding.</al></li></lijst></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">XIV</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Bekrachtiging, aanvaarding, goedkeuring of toetreding geschiedt door de nederlegging van een daartoe strekkende akte bij de Secretaris-Generaal van de Organisatie.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Alle akten van bekrachtiging, aanvaarding, goedkeuring of toetreding, nedergelegd na de inwerkingtreding van een wijziging op dit Verdrag ten aanzien van alle Verdragsluitende Staten, of na de voltooiing van alle maatregelen, vereist voor de inwerkingtreding van de wijziging ten aanzien van deze Verdragsluitende Staten, worden geacht van toepassing te zijn op het aldus gewijzigde Verdrag.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">XV</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Dit Verdrag treedt in werking op de negentigste dag na de datum waarop de Regeringen van acht Staten waaronder vijf Staten, elk met niet minder dan 1.000.000 B.R.T. tankertonnage, het hebben ondertekend zonder voorbehoud van bekrachtiging, aanvaarding of goedkeuring, dan wel akten van bekrachtiging, aanvaarding, goedkeuring of toetreding hebben nedergelegd bij de Secretaris-Generaal van de Organisatie.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Ten aanzien van elke Staat die dit Verdrag daarna bekrachtigt, aanvaardt, goedkeurt of ertoe toetreedt, treedt het Verdrag in werking op de negentigste dag na nederlegging door die Staat van de daartoe strekkende akte.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">XVI</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Een Verdragsluitende Staat mag dit Verdrag na de datum waarop het voor die Staat in werking is getreden te allen tijde opzeggen.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Opzegging geschiedt door nederlegging van een akte bij de Secretaris-Generaal van de Organisatie.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>Een opzegging wordt van kracht een jaar na de nederlegging van de akte van opzegging bij de Secretaris-Generaal van de Organisatie of na een langere termijn, wanneer zulks in die akte is bepaald.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">XVII</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>De Verenigde Naties, ingeval zij het gezagsorgaan zijn dat het beheer over een gebied uitoefent, of een Verdragsluitende Staat die verantwoordelijk is voor de internationale betrekkingen van een gebied, plegen zo spoedig mogelijk overleg met de daarvoor in aanmerking komende autoriteiten van een zodanig gebied, of nemen andere passende maatregelen ten einde dit Verdrag van toepassing te doen zijn op dat gebied en kunnen de Secretaris-Generaal van de Organisatie te allen tijde schriftelijk mededelen dat dit Verdrag ook op dat gebied van toepassing zal zijn.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Te rekenen van de datum van ontvangst van deze kennisgeving of van een andere in deze kennisgeving bepaalde datum, is dit Verdrag van toepassing op het daarin genoemde gebied.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>De Verenigde Naties of een Verdragsluitende Staat die een verklaring krachtens het eerste lid van dit artikel hebben afgelegd, kunnen te allen tijde na de datum waarop dit Verdrag aldus op een gebied van toepassing wordt, door middel van een schriftelijke kennisgeving aan de Secretaris-Generaal van de Organisatie verklaren dat dit Verdrag ophoudt van toepassing te zijn op het in de kennisgeving genoemde gebied.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr><al>Dit Verdrag houdt op van toepassing te zijn op het in de kennisgeving genoemde gebied een jaar na de datum van ontvangst van de kennisgeving door de Secretaris-Generaal van de Organisatie of na een langere termijn, wanneer zulks in die kennisgeving is bepaald.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">XVIII</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>De Organisatie kan een Conferentie tot herziening of wijziging van dit Verdrag bijeenroepen.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>De Organisatie roept een Conferentie van de Verdragsluitende Staten bijeen tot herziening of wijziging van dit Verdrag op het verzoek van ten minste een derde van de Verdragsluitende Staten.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">XIX</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Dit Verdrag wordt nedergelegd bij de Secretaris-Generaal van de Organisatie.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>De Secretaris-Generaal van de Organisatie:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>alle Staten die het Verdrag hebben ondertekend of daartoe zijn toegetreden mededeling van:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(i)</li.nr><al>elke nieuwe ondertekening of nederlegging van een akte en de datum daarvan:</al></li><li>
<li.nr>(ii)</li.nr><al>de nederlegging van een akte van opzegging van dit Verdrag en de datum van nederlegging;</al></li><li><li.nr>(iii)</li.nr><al>de uitbreiding van dit Verdrag tot een gebied ingevolge het eerste lid van artikel XVII en de be&#xEB;indiging van een zodanige uitbreiding ingevolge het bepaalde in het vierde lid van dat artikel, waarbij in beide gevallen de datum wordt aangegeven waarop dit Verdrag is uitgebreid tot dit gebied of waarop die uitbreiding zal eindigen;</al></li></lijst></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al> doet voor eensluidend gewaarmerkte afschriften van dit Verdrag toekomen aan alle ondertekenende Staten en aan alle Staten die tot dit Verdrag toetreden.</al></li></lijst></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Artikel</label><nr status="officieel"> XX</nr></kop><al>Zodra dit Verdrag in werking treedt wordt de tekst door de Secretaris-Generaal van de Organisatie toegezonden aan het Secretariaat van de Verenigde Naties ter registratie en publicatie overeenkomstig artikel 102 van het Handvest der Verenigde Naties.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Artikel</label><nr status="officieel"> XXI</nr></kop><al>Dit Verdrag is, in een enkel exemplaar, opgesteld in de Engelse en de Franse taal, zijnde beide teksten gelijkelijk authentiek. Offici&#xEB;le vertalingen in de Russische en Spaanse taal worden vervaardigd en nedergelegd bij het ondertekende origineel.</al></artikel></wettekst><wetsluiting status="goed"><slotformulering><al>GEDAAN te Londen, de zevenentwintigste november negentienhonderd tweennegentig.</al>
							<al>TEN BLIJKE WAARVAN de ondergetekenden, daartoe naar behoren gemachtigd door hun onderscheiden Regeringen, dit Protocol hebben ondertekend.</al>
							</slotformulering></wetsluiting></verdragtekst><verdragtekst><kop><label>BIJLAGE</label><titel>Certificaat van verzekering of andere financi&#xEB;le zekerheid ter zake
van wettelijke aansprakelijkheid voor schade door verontreiniging
door olie</titel></kop><vrije-tekst><tekst status="goed"><al>Afgegeven overeenkomstig de bepalingen van artikel VII van het
Internationaal Verdrag inzake de wettelijke aansprakelijkheid voor schade
door verontreiniging door olie, 1992.</al><table><tgroup align="left" char="" charoff="50" cols="4"><colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="*"/><colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="*"/><colspec colname="col3" colnum="3" colwidth="*"/><colspec colname="col4" colnum="4" colwidth="*"/><tbody valign="top"><row><entry colname="col1" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>Naam van het schip</al></entry><entry colname="col2" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>Onderscheidingsnummer of -letter</al></entry><entry colname="col3" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>Plaats van teboekstelling</al></entry><entry colname="col4" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>Naam en adres eigenaar</al></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table><al>Hiermede verklaart ondergetekende dat met betrekking tot het bovengnoemde schip een verzekeringspolis van kracht is of een andere financi&#xEB;le zekerheid is gesteld, die voldoet aan de vereisten van artikel VII van het Internationaal Verdrag inzake de wettelijke aansprakelijkheid voor schade door verontreiniging door olie, 1992.</al><al>Aard van de zekerheid.....................................................................................</al><al>Duur der zekerheid..........................................................................................</al><al>Naam en adres van de verzekeraar(s) en/of peroon die de zekerheid stelt</al><al>Naam..............................................................................................................</al><al>Adres..............................................................................................................</al><al>Dit certificaat is geldig tot.................................................................................</al><al>Afgegeven of gewaarmerkt door de Regeling van ......................................</al><al>(volledige aanduiding van de Staat)</al><al>Te................................................................................(Plaats)</al><al>de................................................................................(datum)</al><al>(Handtekening en hoedanigheid van de met de afgifte of waarmerking belaste ambtenaar)</al><tussenkop kopopmaak="cur">Toelichting</tussenkop><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>1.</li.nr><al>Indien gewenst kan bij de aanduiding van de Staat en verwijzing worden opgenomen naar de bevoegde overheidsinstantie van het land waar het certificaat wordt afgegeven.</al></li><li><li.nr>2.</li.nr><al>Indien het totale bedrag van de zekerheid uit meer dan &#xE9;&#xE9;n bron afkomstig is, moeten de uit elk daarvan afkomstige bedragen en de bronnen daarvan afzonderlijk worden vermeld.</al></li><li><li.nr>3.</li.nr><al>Indien de zekerheid is gesteld in meerdere vormen, moet elk daarvan worden vermeld.</al></li><li><li.nr>4.</li.nr><al>In de opgave &#x201E;Duur der zekerheid&#x201D; moet de datum worden vermeld waarop die zekerheid van kracht wordt.</al></li></lijst></tekst></vrije-tekst></verdragtekst></verdrag></wetgeving>
  	