<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE wetgeving SYSTEM "http://wetten.overheid.nl/dtd/bwb-plus-meta-1_61w.dtd">
<wetgeving bwb-id="BWBV0004346" dtdversie="2.0" id="10000038209" verdragnummer="003460" soort="verdrag"> 
  
  
  <intitule>Briefwisseling tussen de Nederlandse en de Indiase Regering inzake het ter beschikking stellen van kunstmest voor de Staat Maharashtra</intitule> 
   
  <verdrag tekst="authentiek" xml:lang="en"><verdragtekst>
<kop>
<label>Nr.</label>
<nr status="officieel">I</nr>

</kop><vrije-tekst><tekst status="goed"><tussenkop kopopmaak="cur">ROYAL NETHERLANDS EMBASSY</tussenkop><al>February 17, 1967</al><al>Excellency,</al><al>In view of the present difficulties with regard to the food situation in certain Indian States and with reference to the recent discussions between representatives of the Government of the Netherlands and the Government of India, I have the honour, on behalf of my Government, to propose the following:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>1.</li.nr><al>The Netherlands Government shall contribute towards the development of the food grain production in the talukas of Karmala, Madha and Sangola in the District of Sholapur of Maharashtra State by making available chemical fertilisers, urea: 1820 ton and double super phosphate: 300 ton, on C &amp; F basis at Bombay Port at a cost not exceeding N.F1. 800,000.</al><al>The fertilisers will be used for growing hybrid jowar on approximately 5000 acres at the general rate of N 100 lbs. and P<inf>2</inf>O<inf>5</inf> 60 lbs. per acre and the remaining quantity will be used on approximately 33000 acres of ordinary jowar at the rate of N 40 lbs, per acre. The fertilisers will be used only under conditions of assured irrigation.</al></li><li><li.nr>2.</li.nr><al>The Government of India will take all measures necessary for the clearance and temporary storage at the port of arrival.</al></li><li><li.nr>3.</li.nr><al>The Government of India will also establish procedures for exempting the Netherlands Government from duties and taxes, imposed in India, on the fertilisers.</al></li><li><li.nr>4.</li.nr><al>The Government of India will take all measures necessary to transport materials from Bombay to Sholapur, for the distribution of the fertilisers, for making available hybrid seed, plant protection equipment, pesticide and the credit needs of the farmers.</al></li><li><li.nr>5.</li.nr><al>The proceeds from sales of the above mentioned fertilisers will be used in the selected areas for the following purposes:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>a)</li.nr><al>land development (levelling and bunding for irrigation);</al></li><li><li.nr>b)</li.nr><al>purchase of diesel pumps for lift irrigation schemes; and</al></li><li><li.nr>c)</li.nr><al>setting up a seed-processing plant.</al></li></lijst></li><li><li.nr>6.</li.nr><al>The Government of India will also permit a Netherlands expert to visit the area during harvest time after the application of the fertilisers, to study and evaluate the impact of the project.</al></li><li><li.nr>7.</li.nr><al>If the foregoing is acceptable to the Government of India, I have the honour to propose that this letter and your reply to that effect shall constitute an agreement between the Government of the Netherlands and the Government of India which shall come into force on the date of your reply and shall terminate on the date on which both parties have fulfilled all obligations arising from it.</al></li></lijst><al>I avail myself of this opportunity to renew to you, Excellency, the assurance of my highest consideration.</al><al>(sd.) H. VAN RIJCKEVORSEL</al><al><nadruk type="cur">Ambassador of the Netherlands</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur">His Excellency,</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur">the Minister of External Affairs,</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur">Government of India,</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur">New Delhi.</nadruk></al></tekst></vrije-tekst></verdragtekst>
<verdragtekst>
<kop>
<label>Nr.</label>
<nr status="officieel">II</nr>
<titel status="officieel"/>
</kop><vrije-tekst><tekst status="goed"><tussenkop kopopmaak="cur">MINISTRY OF EXTERNAL AFFAIRS</tussenkop><tussenkop kopopmaak="cur"> NEW DELHI</tussenkop><al>No. B/2302/127/66</al><al>February 17, 1967</al><al>Excellency,</al><al>I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter dated 17th February 1967 addressed to the Minister for External Affairs, which reads as follows:</al><al><redactie type="extra">(zoals in Nr. I</redactie></al><al>I confirm that the proposals contained in the above letter are acceptable to the Government of India and that your letter, together with this reply, shall constitute an arrangement between the Government of India and the Government of the Netherlands, effective from the date of this reply.</al><al>Accept, Excellency, the assurances of my highest consideration.</al><al>Yours sincerely,</al>
<al>(sd.) A. N. MEHTA</al>
<al>(A. N. Mehta)</al>
<al><nadruk type="cur">Joint Secretary to the Government of India.</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur">His Excellency</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur">Jonkheer H. Th. A. M. van Rijckevorsel,</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur">Ambassador of the Netherlands,</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur">New Delhi.</nadruk></al></tekst></vrije-tekst></verdragtekst></verdrag> 
</wetgeving>
  	