<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE wetgeving SYSTEM "http://wetten.overheid.nl/dtd/bwb-plus-meta-1_61w.dtd">
<wetgeving bwb-id="BWBV0002104" dtdversie="2.0" id="10000015789" verdragnummer="011568" soort="verdrag">
  
  <intitule>Notawisseling houdende een verdrag tussen het Koninkrijk der Nederlanden
en het Technisch Centrum voor Landbouwsamenwerking en Plattelandsontwikkeling
inzake de tewerkstelling van gezinsleden die deel uitmaken van het huishouden
van de functionarissen van het Technisch Centrum voor Landbouwsamenwerking
en Plattelandsontwikkeling</intitule>
  
  <verdrag tekst="authentiek" xml:lang="en">
    <verdragtekst>
      
      
      <kop><titel status="officieel">Agreement between the Kingdom of the Netherlands and the
Technical Centre for Agricultural and Rural Cooperation regarding employment
opportunities of members of the families forming part of the household of
the officials of the Technical Centre for Agricultural and Rural Cooperation</titel></kop><vrije-tekst>
        <tekst status="goed">
          
          <tussenkop>Nr. I.</tussenkop>
          <al>Ministerie van Buitenlandse Zaken</al>
          <al>Treaties Division</al>
          <al>DJZ/VE-505/07</al>
          <al>The Hague, 15 June 2007</al>
          <al>The Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Kingdom of the Netherlands presents
its compliments to the Technical Centre for Agricultural and Rural Cooperation
and, with reference to the Agreement between the Government of the Kingdom
of the Netherlands and the Technical Centre for Agricultural and Rural Cooperation
of 7 August 1984, the Exchange of Notes of 22 November/1 December 2005 between
the Government of the Kingdom of the Netherlands and the Technical Centre
for Agricultural and Rural Cooperation and to the discussions between the
Ministry and the Technical Centre for Agricultural and Rural Cooperation regarding
employment opportunities of members of the families forming part of the household
of the officials of the Technical Centre for Agricultural and Rural Cooperation,
has the honour to propose the following: </al>
          <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>1.</li.nr><al>&#x2002;Members of the family forming part of the household of all categories
of officials in the service of the Technical Centre for Agricultural and Rural
Cooperation shall be authorised to engage in gainful employment in the Netherlands
for the duration of the term of office of the officials concerned.</al></li><li><li.nr>2.</li.nr><al>The following persons are members of the family forming part of
the household in the sense of paragraph 1:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
            <li>
              <li.nr>a)</li.nr>
              <al>the spouses or registered partners of officials
in the service of the Technical Centre for Agricultural and Rural Cooperation;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>b)</li.nr>
              <al>children of officials in the service of
the Technical Centre for Agricultural and Rural Cooperation who are under
the age of 18;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>c)</li.nr>
              <al>children of officials in the service of
the Technical Centre for Agricultural and Rural Cooperation who are aged 18
or over, but not older than 27, provided that they formed part of the official&#x2019;s
household prior to their first entry into the Netherlands and still form part
of this household, and that they are unmarried, financially dependent on the
official concerned and are attending fulltime education in the Netherlands;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>d)</li.nr>
              <al>children of officials in the service of
the Technical Centre for Agricultural and Rural Cooperation who are aged 18
or over, but not older than 23; they shall also be recognized as members of
the family forming part of the household if they are not studying as long
as they are unmarried and financially dependent on the official concerned.</al>
            </li>
          </lijst></li><li><li.nr>3.</li.nr><al>Persons mentioned in paragraph 2 who obtain gainful employment
shall enjoy no immunity from criminal, civil or administrative jurisdiction
with respect to matters arising in the course of or in connection with such
employment. However, any measures of execution shall be taken without infringing
the inviolability of their person or of their residence, if they are entitled
to such inviolability.</al></li><li><li.nr>4.</li.nr><al>In case of the insolvency of a person aged under 18 with respect
to a claim arising out of a gainful employment of that person, the immunity
of the official in the service of the Technical Centre for Agricultural and
Rural Cooperation of whose family the person concerned is a member shall be
waived for the purpose of settlement of the claim, in accordance with the
provisions of the applicable Technical Centre for Agricultural and Rural Cooperation
agreements.</al></li><li><li.nr>5.</li.nr><al>The employment referred to in paragraph 1 shall be in accordance
with Netherlands legislation, including fiscal and social security legislation,
unless any other applicable international legal instrument provides otherwise. </al></li></lijst>
          
          
          
          
          
          <al>If this proposal is acceptable to the Technical Centre for Agricultural
and Rural Cooperation, the Ministry proposes that this Note and the Technical
Centre for Agricultural and Rural Cooperation&#x2019;s affirmative reply to
it shall together constitute an Agreement between the Kingdom of the Netherlands
and the Technical Centre for Agricultural and Rural Cooperation. This Agreement,
the French and English texts of which are equally authentic, shall enter into
force on the date of receipt of the Technical Centre for Agricultural and
Rural Cooperation&#x2019;s reply by the Ministry.</al>
          <al>The Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Kingdom of the Netherlands avails
itself of this opportunity to renew to the Technical Centre for Agricultural
and Rural Cooperation the assurances of its highest consideration.</al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">The Technical Centre for Agricultural and Rural Cooperation</nadruk>
          </al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">Wageningen</nadruk>
          </al>
          
          
          
          
          
   
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
        </tekst>
      </vrije-tekst>
    </verdragtekst>
  <verdragtekst><kop><label>Nr.</label><nr status="officieel">II</nr></kop><vrije-tekst><tekst status="goed"><al>TECHNICAL CENTRE FOR AGRICULTURAL AND</al>
          <al>RURAL COOPERATION</al>
          <al>ASBHRD/1440/149/07/IID</al>
          <al>Wageningen, 20 June 2007</al>
          <al>The Technical Centre for Agricultural and Rural Cooperation presents its
compliments to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Kingdom of the Netherlands
and has the honour to acknowledge receipt of the Ministry&#x2019;s Note DJZ/VE-505/07
of 15 June 2007, which reads as follows:</al>
          <al><redactie type="extra">Zoals in nr. I</redactie></al>
          <al>The Technical Centre for Agricultural and Rural Cooperation has the honour
to inform the Ministry of Foreign Affairs that the proposal is acceptable
to the Technical Centre for Agricultural and Rural Cooperation. The Technical
Centre for Agricultural and Rural Cooperation accordingly agrees that the
Ministry&#x2019;s Note and this reply shall constitute an Agreement between
the Technical Centre for Agricultural and Rural Cooperation and the Kingdom
of the Netherlands. This Agreement shall enter into force on the date of receipt
of the Technical Centre for Agricultural and Rural Cooperation&#x2019;s reply
by the Ministry. </al>
          <al>The Technical Centre for Agricultural and Rural Cooperation avails itself
of this opportunity to renew to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of the Kingdom
of the Netherlands the assurances of its highest consideration.</al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">Ministry of Foreign Affairs</nadruk>
          </al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">The Hague</nadruk>
          </al></tekst></vrije-tekst></verdragtekst></verdrag>
  
</wetgeving>
  	