<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE wetgeving SYSTEM "http://wetten.overheid.nl/dtd/bwb-plus-meta-1_61w.dtd">
<wetgeving bwb-id="BWBV0002862" dtdversie="2.0" id="10000023369" verdragnummer="011776" soort="verdrag">
  
  <intitule>Document van de Staten die Partij zijn bij het Verdrag inzake conventionele strijdkrachten in Europa</intitule>
  
  
  
  <verdrag tekst="authentiek" xml:lang="en">
    <verdragtekst>
      <kop><titel status="officieel">Document of the States Parties to the Treaty on Conventional
Armed Forces in Europe</titel></kop><aanhef><preambule><al>The Republic of Armenia, the Republic of Azerbaijan, the Republic of Belarus,
the Kingdom of Belgium, the Republic of Bulgaria, Canada, the Czech Republic,
the Kingdom of Denmark, the French Republic, the Republic of Georgia, the
Federal Republic of Germany, the Hellenic Republic, the Republic of Hungary,
the Republic of Iceland, the Italian Republic, the Republic of Kazakhstan,
the Grand Duchy of Luxembourg, the Republic of Moldova, the Kingdom of the
Netherlands, the Kingdom of Norway, the Republic of Poland, the Portuguese
Republic, Romania, the Russian Federation, the Slovak Republic, the Kingdom
of Spain, the Republic of Turkey, Ukraine, the United Kingdom of Great Britain
and Northern Ireland and the United States of America, which are the States
Parties to the Treaty on Conventional Armed Forces in Europe of November 19,
1990, hereinafter referred to as the States Parties,</al>
          <al>Committed to meeting the objectives and requirements of the Treaty on
Conventional Armed Forces in Europe of November 19, 1990, hereinafter referred
to as the Treaty, while responding to the historic changes which have occurred
in Europe since the Treaty was signed,</al>
          <al>Recalling in this context the undertaking in paragraph 4 of the Joint
Declaration of Twenty-Two States signed in Paris on November 19, 1990, to
maintain only such military capabilities as are necessary to prevent war and
provide for effective defence and to bear in mind the relationship between
military capabilities and doctrines, and confirming their commitment to that
undertaking,</al>
          <al>Having met together at a joint Extraordinary Conference chaired by the
Hellenic Republic in Vienna on February 5, 1993, pursuant to Article XXI,
paragraph 2, of the Treaty and Section VII, paragraph 4 of the Concluding
Act,</al>
          <al>Have agreed as follows:</al></preambule></aanhef><wettekst><artikel status="goed"><kop><nr status="officieel">1</nr></kop><al>The understandings, notifications, confirmations and commitments contained
or referred to in this Document and its Annexes shall be deemed as fulfilling
the requirements necessary in order for the Czech Republic and the Slovak
Republic fully to exercise the rights and fulfill the obligations as set forth
in the Treaty and its associated documents.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><nr status="officieel">2</nr></kop><al> In this context, the States Parties note the Agreement Between the
Government of the Czech Republic and the Government of the Slovak Republic,
of January 12, 1993, on the Principles and Procedures for Implementing the
Treaty on Conventional Armed Forces in Europe and the Concluding Act of the
Negotiation on Personnel Strength of Conventional Armed Forces in Europe and
the Protocols to that Agreement, as transmitted on January 20, 1993 by the
Czech Republic to all States Parties to the Treaty. In this regard, Articles
I, II (paragraph 2), III (paragraphs 1&#x2013;3), and Articles IV&#x2013;VII
of that Agreement, the Protocol on Maximum Levels for Holdings of Conventional
Armaments and Equipment Limited by the Treaty of the Czech Republic and the
Slovak Republic, the Protocol concerning Armoured Vehicle Launched Bridges
in Active Units, the Protocol on Conventional Armament and Equipment Limited
by the Treaty Designated for Conversion for Non-Military Purposes, and the
Protocol on Active and Passive Declared Site Inspection Quotas for the First
Phase of the Reduction Period to that Agreement, and paragraphs 2 and 3 of
the Protocol on the Reduction Liability to that Agreement contain necessary
confirmations, information, and commitments.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><nr status="officieel">3</nr></kop><al>The States Parties note the notifications by the Czech Republic and
the Slovak Republic listed in the Annex to this Document on Notifications
Related to the Treaty.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><nr status="officieel">4</nr></kop><al>The States Parties confirm the understandings specified in the Annex
to this Document on Understandings Related to the Treaty.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><nr status="officieel">5</nr></kop><al>The States Parties confirm all decisions and recommendations adopted
by the Joint Consultative Group related to the Treaty.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><nr status="officieel">6</nr></kop><al>This Document in no way alters the rights and obligations of the States
Parties as set forth in the Treaty and its associated documents. </al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><nr status="officieel">7</nr></kop><al>This Document shall enter into force upon signature by all the States
Parties.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><nr status="officieel">8</nr></kop><al>This Document, together with its Annexes, which are integral to it,
in all the official languages of the Conference on Security and Cooperation
in Europe, shall be deposited with the Government of the Kingdom of the Netherlands,
as the designated Depositary for the Treaty, which shall circulate true copies
of this Document to all the States Parties.</al></artikel></wettekst>
    </verdragtekst>
  <verdragtekst><kop><titel status="officieel">Annex on notifications related to the Treaty</titel></kop><vrije-tekst>
        <divisie opmaak="default"><kop><label>A.</label><titel status="officieel">The States Parties note the following notifications from the Czech
Republic as transmitted on January 29, 1993:</titel></kop><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>1.</li.nr><al>Maximum level for holdings of conventional armament and equipment limited
by the Treaty;</al></li><li><li.nr>2.</li.nr><al>Reduction liability in the categories of conventional armament and
equipment limited by the Treaty;</al></li><li><li.nr>3.</li.nr><al>Number of battle tanks and armoured combat vehicles designated for
conversion for non-military purposes;</al></li><li><li.nr>4.</li.nr><al>List of the points of entry/exit;</al></li><li><li.nr>5.</li.nr><al>Lists of inspectors and transport crew members;</al></li><li><li.nr>6.</li.nr><al>Diplomatic clearance number;</al></li><li><li.nr>7.</li.nr><al>Official languages;</al></li><li><li.nr>8.</li.nr><al>Passive inspection quota for the first year of reduction period;</al></li><li><li.nr>9.</li.nr><al>Active inspection quota for the first year of reduction period (revised
February 1, 1993);</al></li><li><li.nr>10.</li.nr><al>Counting of the aircraft destructed by accident;</al></li><li><li.nr>11.</li.nr><al>Armaments and equipment limited by the Treaty and retained outside
the territory of the Czech Republic (revised February 1, 1993);</al></li><li><li.nr>12.</li.nr><al>List of reduction sites of the Czech Republic;</al></li><li><li.nr>13.</li.nr><al>Aggregate number of armament and equipment limited by the Treaty used
exclusively for purpose of research and development;</al></li><li><li.nr>14.</li.nr><al>Number of armament and equipment limited by the Treaty awaiting export/re-export;
and</al></li><li><li.nr>15.</li.nr><al>Number and types of conventional armament and equipment removed from
service and reduced during previous 12 months.</al></li></lijst></divisie><tekst status="goed">
          
          

          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          <al>The States Parties also note that, by its Note Verbale of January 29,
1993, the Czech Republic informed &#x201C;all Delegations to the Joint Consultative
Group that the data of Ministry of Defence, General Staff, Military Command
West, Military Command Middle and of all the formations and units subordinated
to them contained in the Exchange of Information submitted by the Czech and
Slovak Federal Republic on December 15, 1922 are valid for Armed Forces of
the Czech Republic until superseded by a subsequent exchange of information
of the Czech Republic.</al>
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
        </tekst>
      <divisie opmaak="default"><kop><label>B.</label><titel status="officieel">The States Parties note the following notifications from the Slovak
Republic as transmitted on January 29, 1993 (1&#x2013;11) and February 4, 1993
(12 and 13):</titel></kop><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>1.</li.nr><al>Maximum levels for holdings of conventional armaments and equipment
and numbers of national personnel limits limited by the Treaty (revised February
2, 1993);</al></li><li><li.nr>2.</li.nr><al>Reduction liability in the categories of conventional armaments and
equipment limited by the Treaty (revised February 2, 1993);</al></li><li><li.nr>3.</li.nr><al>Number of battle tanks and armoured combat vehicles designated for
conversion for non-military purposes;</al></li><li><li.nr>4.</li.nr><al>List of the points of entry/exit into and out of the territory of the
Slovak Republic (revised February 2, 1993);</al></li><li><li.nr>5.</li.nr><al>List of inspectors;</al></li><li><li.nr>6.</li.nr><al>Standing diplomatic clearance number;</al></li><li><li.nr>7.</li.nr><al>Official languages;</al></li><li><li.nr>8.</li.nr><al>Passive inspection quota for the first year of reduction period;</al></li><li><li.nr>9.</li.nr><al>Active inspection quota for the first year of reduction period (revised
February 2, 1993);</al></li><li><li.nr>10.</li.nr><al>Numbers of conventional armaments and equipment limited by the Treaty
awaiting export/re-export and retained outside the territory of the Slovak
Republic (revised February 2, 1993);</al></li><li><li.nr>11.</li.nr><al>Numbers and types of conventional armaments and equipment removed
from service and reduced during previous 12 months;</al></li><li><li.nr>12.</li.nr><al>Aggregate number of conventional armaments and equipment limited by
the Treaty used exclusively for the purpose of research and development; and</al></li><li><li.nr>13.</li.nr><al>Numbers of conventional armaments and equipment limited by the Treaty
and retained outside the territory of the Slovak Republic.</al></li></lijst></divisie><tekst status="goed"><al>The States Parties also note that, by its Note Verbale of January 29,
1993, the Slovak Republic informed &#x201C;all Delegations to the Joint Consultative
Group that the data of Military Command East and of all formations and units
subordinated to it contained in the Exchange of Information submitted by the
Czech and Slovak Federal Republic on December 15, 1992 are valid for Armed
Forces of the Slovak Republic until next exchange of information of the Slovak
Republic in March 1993."</al></tekst></vrije-tekst></verdragtekst></verdrag>
</wetgeving>
  	