<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE wetgeving SYSTEM "http://wetten.overheid.nl/dtd/bwb-plus-meta-1_61w.dtd">
<wetgeving bwb-id="BWBV0002755" dtdversie="2.0" id="10000022299" verdragnummer="011123" soort="verdrag"><intitule>Notawisseling tussen de Regering van het Koninkrijk der Nederlanden en de Regering van de Unie van Socialistische Sowjet-Republieken betreffende luchtdiensten</intitule><verdrag tekst="authentiek" xml:lang="en"><verdragtekst xml:lang="en"><kop><label/></kop><vrije-tekst><divisie opmaak="default"><kop><nr status="officieel">1</nr></kop><al>As from April 1, 1984, Aeroflot will be allowed to overfly Netherlands territory without landing or with a technical landing with any number of scheduled flights to/from points in Europe and to/from points beyond in USA, Canada, Mexico, Jamaica, Nicaragua, Cuba, Peru, Bolivia, Brazil, Venezuela, Panama, Columbia with any type of subsonic aircraft.</al></divisie><divisie opmaak="default"><kop><nr status="officieel">2</nr></kop><al>As from the same date KLM will be allowed to overfly USSR territory through the Tashkent route without landing or with a technical landing with any number of scheduled flights to/from points in Pakistan, India, Maldives, Sri Lanka, Bangladesh, Malaysia, Singapore, Thailand, Indonesia, Australia, New Zealand, Philippines, Hong Kong with any type of subsonic aircraft.</al></divisie><divisie opmaak="default"><kop><nr status="officieel">3</nr></kop><al>Additional points beyond in other countries than listed under 1 and 2 above may be established between the aeronautical authorities of both Parties.</al></divisie><divisie opmaak="default"><kop><nr status="officieel">4</nr></kop><al>Requests by Aeroflot and KLM for overflying with their non-scheduled flights without landing or with a technical landing in the territory of the other party along the routes meant in I and 2 will be favourably considered by the respective authorities.</al></divisie></vrije-tekst></verdragtekst></verdrag></wetgeving>
  	