<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE wetgeving SYSTEM "http://wetten.overheid.nl/dtd/bwb-plus-meta-1_61w.dtd">
<wetgeving bwb-id="BWBV0005865" dtdversie="2.0" id="10000053399" verdragnummer="007251" soort="verdrag">
  
  <intitule>Notawisseling houdende een overeenkomst tussen de Nederlandse en de Nieuw-Zeelandse Regering betreffende de wederzijdse afschaffing van visa</intitule>
  
  <verdrag status="goed" tekst="authentiek" xml:lang="en">
    <verdragtekst xml:lang="en">
      <kop>
        <label>Nr.</label>
        <nr status="officieel">I</nr>
      </kop>
      <vrije-tekst>
        <tekst status="goed">
          <al>MINISTRY OF EXTERNAL AFFAIRS WELLINGTON</al>
          <al>Wellington, 3 March 1949</al>
          <al>Sir,</al>
          <al>I have the honour to refer to various discussions concerning arrangements to permit of freedom of travel between our two countries and to suggest than an agreement in the following terms be concluded for the mutual abolition of visas for travel between New Zealand and the Netherlands: --</al>
          <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
            <li>
              <li.nr>&#x201C;(1)</li.nr>
              <al>Netherlands nationals shall be free to travel to New Zealand by any route without the necessity of obtaining a visa in advance provided they are furnished with valid Netherlands passports.</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>&#x201C;(2)</li.nr>
              <al>New Zealand citizens shall be free to travel to the Netherlands by any route without the necessity of obtaining a visa in advance provided they are furnished with valid New Zealand passports.</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>&#x201C;(3)</li.nr>
              <al>It is understood that the waiver of the visa requirement does not exempt Netherlands nationals and New Zealand citizens travelling respectively to New Zealand and to the Netherlands from the necessity of complying with the New Zealand and the Netherlands laws and regulations concerning the entry, residence (temporary or permanent) and employment or occupation of foreigners, and that travellers who are unable to satisfy the Immigration authorities that they comply with these laws and regulations are liable to be refused leave to enter or land.</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>&#x201C;(4)</li.nr>
              <al>As regards travel by Netherlands nationals to New Zealand Island Territories and the trust Territory of Western Samoa, visas will not be required but it will be necessary for travellers to comply with the laws and regulations concerning the entry, residence (temporary or permanent) and employment or occupation of foreigners in the Island Territories or the Trust Territory of Western Samoa as the case may be. Travellers who are unable to satisfy the Immigration authorities that they comply with these regulations are liable to be refused leave to enter or land.</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>&#x201C;(5)</li.nr>
              <al>As regards travel to Netherlands overseas territories, it is understood that visas will continue to be required.&#x201D;</al>
            </li>
          </lijst>
          <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
            <li>
              <li.nr>2.</li.nr>
              <al>If the Netherlands Government are prepared to accept the foregoing provisions, I have the honour to suggest that the present note, and your reply in similar terms, should be regarded as placing on record the agreement between the two Governments, which will take effect on 1 April 1949.</al>
            </li>
          </lijst>
          <al>I have, &amp;c.,</al>
          <al>P. FRASER,</al>
          <al> Minister of External Affairs</al>
          <al><nadruk type="cur">Mr. J.B.D. Pennink</nadruk></al>
          <al><nadruk type="cur">Legation of the Netherlands</nadruk></al>
        </tekst>
      </vrije-tekst>
    </verdragtekst>
    <verdragtekst xml:lang="en">
      <kop>
        <label>Nr.</label>
        <nr status="officieel">II</nr>
      </kop>
      <vrije-tekst>
        <tekst status="goed">
          <al>LEGATION OF THE NETHERLANDS WELLINGTON</al>
          <al>Wellington, 3 March 1949</al>
          <al>Sir,</al>
          <al>I have the honour to refer to your <intref status="actief" doc="1.0:v:BWBV0005865&amp;verdragtekst=I">note of 3 March 1949</intref>, concerning arrangements to permit freedom of travel between our countries and suggesting that an agreement in the following terms be concluded for the mutual abolition of visas for travel between New Zealand and the Netherlands: --</al>
          <al>
            <redactie type="extra">(Zoals in Nota Nr. I)</redactie>
          </al>
          <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
            <li>
              <li.nr>2.</li.nr>
              <al>I have the honour to inform you that the Netherlands Government are prepared to put into force the foregoing provisions and that they consider <intref status="actief" doc="1.0:v:BWBV0005865&amp;verdragtekst=I">your letter</intref> and my present reply as constituting between the two Governments an agreement which is to come into force on April first, 1949.</al>
            </li>
          </lijst>
          <al>I have, &amp;c.</al>
          <al>J.B.D. PENNINK,</al>
          <al> Minister for the Netherlands</al>
          <al><nadruk type="cur">Mr. Peter Fraser</nadruk></al>
          <al><nadruk type="cur">Ministry of External Affairs</nadruk></al>
        </tekst>
      </vrije-tekst>
    </verdragtekst>
  </verdrag>
</wetgeving>
  	