<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE wetgeving SYSTEM "http://wetten.overheid.nl/dtd/bwb-plus-meta-1_61w.dtd">
<wetgeving bwb-id="BWBV0004179" dtdversie="2.0" id="10000036539" sleutel="V3378" verdragnummer="003201" soort="verdrag"> 
  
  
  <intitule>Briefwisseling tussen de Regering van het Koninkrijk der Nederlanden en de Supreme Allied Commander Europe betreffende het verlenen van immuniteit aan de Commandant en de plaatsvervangend Commandant van Allied Forces Central Europe (AFCENT)</intitule> 
   
  <verdrag tekst="authentiek" xml:lang="en">
    
    
  
<verdragtekst><kop><label>Nr.</label><nr status="officieel">I</nr></kop><vrije-tekst><tekst status="goed"><al>Brussels, November 27, 1968</al><al>no. 6393</al><al>My dear General,</al><al>With reference to Article VII, paragraph 2, of the Agreement between the Kingdom of the Netherlands and the Supreme Headquarters Allied Powers, Europe, on the special conditions applicable to the establishment and operation of International Military Headquarters within the European territory of the Kingdom of the Netherlands, signed at Paris on 25 May 1964, I have the honour to inform you that the Netherlands Government is willing to grant the immunity referred to in Article VII, paragraph 1, of the said Agreement to the Commander-in-Chief and the Deputy Commander-in-Chief of AFCENT.</al><al>I would be most grateful if you would let me know whether you can agree to this proposal.</al><al>Yours sincerely,</al>
<al>(s.) H. N. BOON,</al>
<al>Permanent Representative of the</al><al>Netherlands to the North</al><al>Atlantic Council.</al>
<al><nadruk type="cur">General Lyman L. Lemnitzer</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur"> Supreme Allied Commander, Europe,</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur"> SHAPE,</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur"> Belgium</nadruk> </al></tekst></vrije-tekst></verdragtekst><verdragtekst><kop><label>Nr.</label><nr status="officieel">II</nr></kop><vrije-tekst><tekst status="goed"><al>SUPREME ALLIED</al><al>COMMANDER EUROPE</al><al>27 December 1968</al><al>Dear Mr. Ambassador:</al><al>In reply to your letter of 27 November 1968 concerning Article VII, paragraphs of the agreement between the Kingdom of The Netherlands and the Supreme Headquarters Allied Powers Europe, on the establishment and operation of International Military Headquarters within European Territory of the Kingdom of The Netherlands, I agree to the proposal of The Netherlands Government whereby the immunity referred to in Article VII, paragraph 1 of the said agreement shall be granted to the Commander-in-Chief and to the Deputy Commander-in-Chief of AFCENT.</al><al>Sincerely,</al>
<al>(s.) L. L. LEMNITZER</al>
<al>General, U.S. Army</al><al>Supreme Allied Commander</al>
<al><nadruk type="cur">His Excellency Dr. H. N. Boon</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur"> Permanent Representative to</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur"> The North Atlantic Council</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur">Boulevard Leopold III</nadruk></al><al><nadruk type="cur">Brussels 39</nadruk> </al></tekst></vrije-tekst></verdragtekst></verdrag> 
</wetgeving>
  	