<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE wetgeving SYSTEM "http://wetten.overheid.nl/dtd/bwb-plus-meta-1_61w.dtd">
<wetgeving bwb-id="BWBV0005680" dtdversie="2.0" id="10000051549" verdragnummer="007056" soort="verdrag">
  
  
  
  <intitule>Protocol inzake de toelating van Pakistan tot de Overeenkomst van Parijs van 14 januari 1946 betreffende herstelbetalingen
</intitule>
  
  
  
<verdrag publicatie="nee" status="goed" tekst="authentiek" xml:lang="en"><verdragtekst><kop><titel status="officieel">PROTOCOL</titel></kop><vrije-tekst><tekst status="goed"><al>The Governments of Albania, The United States of America,
Australia, Belgium, Canada, Denmark, Egypt, France, The United
Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland, Greece, India,
Luxembourg, Norway, New Zealand, The Netherlands, Czechoslovakia,
The Union of South Africa and Yugoslavia, having taken
note of the Arrangement of the 22 January 1948 under which the
Governments of the Dominion of India and the Dominion of
Pakistan have agreed to the apportionment between them, in the
following manner, of the reparation percentage shares alloted to the
Government of India under Article 1 B of the Paris Agreement of
14 January 1946:</al><table><tgroup align="left" char="" charoff="50" cols="5"><colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="*"/><colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="*"/><colspec colname="col03" colnum="3" colwidth="1.33*"/><colspec colname="col3" colnum="4" colwidth="*"/><colspec colname="col5" colnum="5" colwidth="1.33*"/><tbody valign="top"><row><entry colname="col1" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>India:</al></entry><entry colname="col2" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>Category A </al></entry><entry colname="col03" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>1.65</al></entry><entry colname="col3" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>Category B  </al></entry><entry colname="col5" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>2.39</al></entry></row><row><entry colname="col1" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>Pakistan:</al></entry><entry colname="col2" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>Category A </al></entry><entry colname="col03" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>0.35</al></entry><entry colname="col3" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>Category B  </al></entry><entry colname="col5" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>0.51</al></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table><al>Having noted that the Government of the Dominion of India and
the Government of the Dominion of Pakistan have agreed that the
value of Reparation assets in Category B allocated to the Government
of India up to and including 14 August 1947, and amounting,
subject to such accounting adjustments by the Inter Allied Reparations Agency as may become necessary, to RM 10.900.000, will be
considered to have been apportioned in the following manner:</al><table><tgroup align="left" char="" charoff="50" cols="2"><colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="*"/><colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="*"/><tbody valign="top"><row><entry colname="col1" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>Dominion of India:</al></entry><entry colname="col2" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>RM. 8.983.000</al></entry></row><row><entry colname="col1" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>Dominion of Pakistan:</al></entry><entry colname="col2" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>RM. 1.917.000</al></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table><al>it being understood that the above apportionment is susceptible of
adjustment by mutual agreement between the Governments of the
Dominions of India and Pakistan.</al><al>Having noted that the Government of the Dominion of India and
the Government of the Dominion of Pakistan have agreed that the
value of Reparation Assets in Category B allocated to the Government
of India between 15 August 1947, and 22 January 1948, and
amounting, subject to such accounting adjustments by the Inter Allied
Reparation Agency as may become necessary, to RM. 1.068.000,
will be considered to have been allocated to the Government of the
Dominion of India, it being understood that the above allocation is
susceptible of adjustment by mutual agreement between the Governments
of the Dominions of India and Pakistan.</al><al>Have agreed as follows:</al><al>Upon the signature of the present Protocol by the Governments
Signatories of the Paris Agreement and by the Government of the
Dominion of Pakistan, the Dominion of Pakistan shall be deemed to
have been a Government Signatory of the Paris Agreement, as from
the date of the entry into force of the said Agreement, with corresponding
rights and obligations, and to have adhered to the unanimous
resolutions of the Paris Conference on Reparation. The
Governments of the Dominion of India and the Dominion of
Pakistan shall respectively be entitled to receive the following reparation
shares:</al><table><tgroup align="left" char="" charoff="50" cols="5"><colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="*"/><colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="*"/><colspec colname="col03" colnum="3" colwidth="1.33*"/><colspec colname="col3" colnum="4" colwidth="*"/><colspec colname="col5" colnum="5" colwidth="1.33*"/><tbody valign="top"><row><entry colname="col1" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>India: </al></entry><entry colname="col2" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>Category A </al></entry><entry colname="col03" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>1.65</al></entry><entry colname="col3" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>Category B  </al></entry><entry colname="col5" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>2.39</al></entry></row><row><entry colname="col1" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>Pakistan:</al></entry><entry colname="col2" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>Category A </al></entry><entry colname="col03" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>0.35</al></entry><entry colname="col3" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>Category B  </al></entry><entry colname="col5" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>0.51</al></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table><al>In witness thereof, the undersigned, duly authorised by their respective
Governments, have signed in Brussels the present Protocol, in
the English and French languages, the two texts being equally
authentic, in a single original which shall be annexed to the Paris
Agreement and deposited in the Archives of the Government of the
French Republic, a certified copy thereof being furnished by that
Government to each Signatory Government, and a certified copy of
the Paris Agreement to the Government of the Dominion of
Pakistan.</al></tekst></vrije-tekst></verdragtekst></verdrag><verdrag status="goed" tekst="vertaling" xml:lang="nl"><verdragtekst><kop><titel status="officieel">PROTOCOL</titel></kop><vrije-tekst><tekst status="goed"><al>De Regeringen van Albani&#xEB;, de Verenigde Staten van Amerika,
Australi&#xEB;, Belgi&#xEB;, Canada, Denemarken, Egypte, Frankrijk, het
Verenigd Koninkrijk Groot Brittanni&#xEB; en Noord-lerland, Griekenland,
India, Luxemburg, Noorwegen, Nieuw-Zeeland, Nederland,
Tsjecho Slowakije, de Zuid-Afrikaanse Unie en Joego-Slavi&#xEB;, kennis
genomen hebbende van de Overeenkomst van 22 Januari 1948,
waarbij de Regeringen van het Dominion India en het Dominion
Pakistan overeenstemming hebben bereikt inzake de verdeling tussen
hen, op de hiernavolgende wijze, van de percentages in de herstelbetalingen,
toegekend aan de Regering van India onder artikel 1 B
van de Parijs Overeenkomst van 14 Januari 1946:</al><table><tgroup align="left" char="" charoff="50" cols="5"><colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="*"/><colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="*"/><colspec colname="col03" colnum="3" colwidth="1.33*"/><colspec colname="col3" colnum="4" colwidth="*"/><colspec colname="col5" colnum="5" colwidth="1.33*"/><tbody valign="top"><row><entry colname="col1" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>India:</al></entry><entry colname="col2" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>Categorie A </al></entry><entry colname="col03" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>1,65</al></entry><entry colname="col3" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>Categorie B  </al></entry><entry colname="col5" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>2,39</al></entry></row><row><entry colname="col1" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>Pakistan:</al></entry><entry colname="col2" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>Categorie A </al></entry><entry colname="col03" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>0,35</al></entry><entry colname="col3" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>Categorie B  </al></entry><entry colname="col5" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>0,51</al></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table><al>Er van kennis genomen hebbende, dat de Regering van het Dominion
India en de Regering van het Dominion Pakistan zijn overeengekomen, dat de waarde der herstelbetalingsgoederen in Categorie B,
toegewezen aan de Regering van India tot en met 14 Augustus 1947,
en bedragende, behoudens zodanige wijzigingen in de berekening
door de Intergeallieerde Organisatie voor Herstelbetalingen als noodzakelijk
mochten blijken, RM 10.900.000, geacht zal worden op de
volgende wijze te zijn toegedeeld:</al><table><tgroup align="left" char="" charoff="50" cols="2"><colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="*"/><colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="*"/><tbody valign="top"><row><entry colname="col1" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>Dominion India:</al></entry><entry colname="col2" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>RM. 8.983.000</al></entry></row><row><entry colname="col1" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>Dominion Pakistan:</al></entry><entry colname="col2" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>RM. 1.917.000</al></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table><al>met dien verstande, dat de bovenstaande verdeling door onderlinge
overeenkomst tussen de Regeringen van de Dominions India en
Pakistan kan worden gewijzigd;</al><al>Er van kennis genomen hebbende, dat de Regering van het Dominion
India en de Regering van het Dominion Pakistan zijn overeengekomen,
dat de waarde der herstelbetalingsgoederen in Categorie
B, toegewezen aan de Regering van India tussen 15 Augustus
1947 en 22 Januari 1948, en bedragende, behoudens zodanige wijzigingen
in de berekening door de Intergeallieerde Organisatie voor
Herstelbetalingen als noodzakelijk mochten blijken, RM 1.068.000,
geacht zal worden te zijn toegewezen aan de Regering van het
Dominion India, met dien verstande, dat de bovengenoemde toewijzing
door onderlinge overeenkomst tussen de Regeringen van de
Dominions India en Pakistan kan worden gewijzigd;</al><al>Zijn het volgende overeengekomen:
</al><al>Na ondertekening van het onderhavige Protocol door de Regeringen,
welke de Parijse Overeenkomst hebben ondertekend, en door
de Regering van het Dominion Pakistan, zal het Dominion Pakistan
geacht worden een Regering, welke de Parijse Overeenkomst heeft
ondertekend, te zijn geweest vanaf de datum van inwerkingtreding
van genoemde Overeenkomst, met alle daaraan verbonden rechten
en verplichtingen, en de eenstemmige resoluties van de Parijse Conferentie
over Herstelbetalingen te hebben ondersteund. De Regeringen
van het Dominion India en het Dominion Pakistan zullen onderscheidenlijk
gerechtigd zijn de volgende aandelen in de herstelbetalingen
te ontvangen:</al><table><tgroup align="left" char="" charoff="50" cols="5"><colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colwidth="*"/><colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colwidth="*"/><colspec colname="col03" colnum="3" colwidth="1.33*"/><colspec colname="col3" colnum="4" colwidth="*"/><colspec colname="col5" colnum="5" colwidth="1.33*"/><tbody valign="top"><row><entry colname="col1" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>India:</al></entry><entry colname="col2" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>Categorie A </al></entry><entry colname="col03" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>1,65</al></entry><entry colname="col3" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>Categorie B  </al></entry><entry colname="col5" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>2,39</al></entry></row><row><entry colname="col1" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>Pakistan:</al></entry><entry colname="col2" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>Categorie A </al></entry><entry colname="col03" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>0,35</al></entry><entry colname="col3" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>Categorie B  </al></entry><entry colname="col5" morerows="0" rotate="0"><al>0,51</al></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table><al>Ten blijke waarvan de ondergetekenden, door hun onderscheidene
Regeringen behoorlijk gemachtigd, het onderhavige in de Engelse en
Franse taal opgesteld Protocol, waarvan beide teksten gelijkelijk
rechtsgeldig zijn, te Brussel hebben getekend in een enkel exemplaar,
hetwelk toegevoegd zal worden aan de Parijse Overeenkomst en zal
worden bewaard in de archieven van de Regering der Franse Republiek,
welke Regering aan iedere ondertekenende Regering een gewaarmerkt
afschrift hiervan zal doen toekomen, benevens een gewaarmerkt
afschrift van de Parijse Overeenkomst aan de Regering
van het Dominion Pakistan.</al></tekst></vrije-tekst></verdragtekst></verdrag></wetgeving>
  	