<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE wetgeving SYSTEM "http://wetten.overheid.nl/dtd/bwb-plus-meta-1_61w.dtd">
<wetgeving bwb-id="BWBV0001955" dtdversie="2.0" id="10000014259" verdragnummer="007395" soort="verdrag">
  
  <intitule>Briefwisseling tussen de Regering van het Koninkrijk der Nederlanden en het Internationale Monetaire Fonds houdende een verdrag inzake de verlening van privileges en immuniteiten aan de Residerend Vertegenwoordiger van het Internationale Monetaire Fonds op de Nederlandse Antillen</intitule>
  
  <verdrag tekst="authentiek" xml:lang="en">
    <verdragtekst>
      
      <kop>
        <label>Nr.</label><nr status="officieel">I</nr>
      </kop>
      <vrije-tekst>
        <tekst status="goed">
          <al>INTERNATIONAL MONETARY FUND WASHINGTON, D.C. 20431</al>
          
          <al>October 4, 1996 </al>
          <al>Dear Mr. Minister:</al>
          <al>In reference to the assignment of a Resident Representative by the International
Monetary Fund (hereinafter the IMF) to the Netherlands Antilles, I would appreciate
your confirmation of the following understandings:</al>
          <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>1.</li.nr><al>The Kingdom of the Netherlands, on behalf of the Netherlands Antilles,
acknowledges the application of the immunities and privileges of the IMF as
specified in the Articles of Agreement of the IMF (27  December 1945) and
the UN Convention on Privileges and Immunities of the Specialized Agencies
(21 November 1947).</al></li><li><li.nr>2.</li.nr><al>The Kingdom of the Netherlands, on behalf of the Netherlands Antilles,
in accordance with the laws and regulations of the Netherlands Antilles, acknowledges
the agreement by the Kingdom of the Netherlands to accord:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
            <li>
              <li.nr>a)</li.nr>
              <al>to the Resident Representative and to members
of his family forming part of his household, if they are not nationals of
the Kingdom of the Netherlands, the same privileges and immunities as are
accorded to chiefs of diplomatic missions accredited to the Kingdom of the
Netherlands; and</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>b)</li.nr>
              <al>to the Resident Representative, members
of his family forming part of his household, and his private servants the
same repatriation facilities in the event of serious crises as are accorded
to chiefs of diplomatic missions accredited to the Kingdom of the Netherlands;
and</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>c)</li.nr>
              <al>to the Resident Representative's private
servants, if they are not nationals of or permanent residents in the Kingdom
of the Netherlands:</al>
            <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
            <li>
              <li.nr>(i)</li.nr>
              <al>exemption from dues and taxes on the emoluments
they receive by reason of their employment, and</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>(ii)</li.nr>
              <al>the privileges and immunities customarily
accorded by the Kingdom to private servants of chiefs of diplomatic missions
accredited to the Kingdom.</al>
            </li>
          </lijst></li>
          </lijst></li><li><li.nr>3.</li.nr><al> The Kingdom of the Netherlands, on behalf of the Netherlands Antilles,
agrees to:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
            <li>
              <li.nr>a)</li.nr>
              <al>permit entry of and grant exemption from
all customs duties, taxes, and related charges other than charges for storage,
cartage, and similar services, on:</al>
            <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
            <li>
              <li.nr>(i)</li.nr>
              <al>articles for official use of the office
of the Resident Representative; and</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>(ii)</li.nr>
              <al>articles for personal use of the Resident
Representative or members of his family forming part of his household, including
his personal baggage, one automobile, and articles intended for his establishment.</al>
            </li>
          </lijst></li>
          <li>
              <li.nr>b)</li.nr>
              <al>exempt items falling under paragraph 3a)
above from all local taxation.</al>
            </li></lijst></li><li><li.nr>4.</li.nr><al> The Kingdom of the Netherlands, on behalf of the Netherlands Antilles,
agrees to:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
            <li>
              <li.nr>a)</li.nr>
              <al>provide suitable office space and secretarial
assistance for the Resident Representative; and</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>b)</li.nr>
              <al>take reasonable measures to secure the office
and home of the Resident Representative and to protect him, members of his
family forming part of his household, and private servants from physical harm.</al>
            </li>
          </lijst></li><li><li.nr>5.</li.nr><al>The Kingdom of the Netherlands, on behalf of the Netherlands Antilles,
agrees to assist in and facilitate the opening and operation of a Resident
Representative office insofar as such assistance and facilitation are within
the jurisdiction or control of the Netherlands Antilles.</al></li></lijst>
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          <al>I have the honor to propose that this letter and your affirmative answer
shall constitute an Agreement between the International Monetary Fund and
the Kingdom of the Netherlands, on behalf of the Netherlands Antilles, which
shall enter into force on the date of receipt of your reply.</al>
          <al>Sincerely yours, </al>
          <al>(sd.) M. CAMDESSUS   </al>
          <al>Michel Camdessus </al>
          <al>Managing Director</al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">The Minister of Foreign Affairs </nadruk>
          </al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">Kingdom of the Netherlands </nadruk>
          </al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">2500 EB The Hague </nadruk>
          </al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">The Netherlands</nadruk>
          </al>
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
        </tekst>
      </vrije-tekst>
    </verdragtekst>
  <verdragtekst><kop><label>Nr.</label><nr status="officieel">II</nr></kop><vrije-tekst><tekst status="goed"><tussenkop>MINISTER FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS</tussenkop><al>The Hague, 11 October 1996 </al><al>I should like to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of 4 October 1996,
which reads as follows:</al><al><redactie type="extra">(Zoals in Nr. I</redactie></al><al>On behalf of the Government of the Kingdom of the Netherlands, I have
the honour to confirm that your letter and this letter in reply shall constitute
an Agreement between the Kingdom of the Netherlands and the International
Monetary Fund, which shall enter into force as of today.</al><al>(sd) H. A. F. M. O. VAN MIERLO    </al><al>Hans van Mierlo </al><al>Minister for Foreign Affairs of </al><al>the Kingdom of the Netherlands</al><al>
            <nadruk type="cur">To Mr M. Camdessus </nadruk>
          </al><al>
            <nadruk type="cur">Managing Director </nadruk>
          </al><al>
            <nadruk type="cur">International Monetary Fund </nadruk>
          </al><al>
            <nadruk type="cur">Washington</nadruk>
          </al></tekst></vrije-tekst></verdragtekst></verdrag>
  
</wetgeving>
  	