<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE wetgeving SYSTEM "http://wetten.overheid.nl/dtd/bwb-plus-meta-1_61w.dtd">
<wetgeving bwb-id="BWBV0001391" id="10000004099" verdragnummer="009150" soort="verdrag">
  <intitule>Notawisseling tussen de Nederlandse Regering en de Regering van het
    Verenigd Koninkrijk van Groot-Brittanni&#xEB; en Noord-Ierland houdende een
    verdrag inzake voorrechten en immuniteiten te verlenen aan
    verbindingsofficieren die vanwege de Regering van het Verenigd Koninkrijk
    van Groot-Brittanni&#xEB; en Noord-Ierland bij Europol te 's-Gravenhage
    worden tewerkgesteld</intitule>
  
  <verdrag tekst="authentiek" xml:lang="en">
    <verdragtekst>
      
      <kop>
        <label>Nr.</label><nr>I</nr>
      </kop>
      <vrije-tekst>
        <tekst status="goed">
          <tussenkop>ROYAL NETHERLANDS EMBASSY</tussenkop>
          
          <al>38 Hyde Park Gate</al><al> London SW7 5DP</al><al/><al>The Royal Netherlands Embassy presents its compliments to the
            Foreign and Commonwealth Office and has the honour to propose with
            reference to article 41, paragraph 2 of the Convention based on
            Article K.3 of the Treaty on European Union, on the establishment of
            a European Police Office (Europol Convention, 26 July 1995) that the
            privileges and immunities necessary for the proper performance of
            the tasks of the Liaison Officers at Europol be agreed upon as set
            out in the Attachment.</al>
          <al>If this proposal is acceptable to the Foreign and Commonwealth
            Office, the Embassy proposes that this note and the affirmative note
            of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs shall constitute an Agreement
            between the Kingdom of the Netherlands and the United Kingdom of
            Great Britain and Northern Ireland, which shall enter into force on
            the first day of the month following the day on which both Parties
            have informed each other in writing that the legal requirements for
            entry into force have been complied with.</al>
          <al>The Royal Netherlands Embassy avails itself of this opportunity to
            renew to the Foreign and Commonwealth Office the assurances of its
            highest consideration.</al>
          <al/><al>London, 9 December 1998 </al>
          <al/><al>
            <nadruk type="cur">The Foreign and Commonwealth Office</nadruk>
          </al><al>
            <nadruk type="cur">London SW1</nadruk>
          </al>
          
          
        </tekst>
      </vrije-tekst>
    </verdragtekst>
  <verdragtekst><kop><label>Attachment</label></kop><wettekst><artikel status="goed"><kop><nr status="officieel">1</nr><titel status="officieel">Definitions</titel></kop>
          <al>In this Agreement:</al>
          <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
            <li>
              <li.nr>a)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x201C;Liaison Officer&#x201D; means: any official seconded to Europol
                in accordance with Article 5 of the Europol Convention;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>b)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x201C;Government&#x201D; means the Government of the Kingdom of the Netherlands;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>c)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x201C;Host State authorities&#x201D; means such State, municipal or
                other authorities of the Kingdom of the Netherlands as may be
                appropriate in the context of and in accordance with the laws
                and customs applicable in the Kingdom of the Netherlands;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>d)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x201C;Member State&#x201D; means the United Kingdom of Great Britain
                and Northern Ireland;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>e)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x201C;Archives of the Liaison Officer&#x201D; means all records,
                correspondence, documents, manuscripts, computer and media data,
                photographs, films, video and sound recordings belonging to or
                held by the Liaison Officer, and any other similar material
                which in the unanimous opinion of the Member State and the
                Government forms part of the archives of the Liaison Officer.</al>
            </li>
          </lijst>
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          </artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><nr>2</nr><titel>Privileges and immunities</titel></kop>
          <lid><lidnr>1</lidnr><al>Subject to the provisions of this Agreement, the Liaison
            Officer and members of his family who form part of his household and
            do not possess Dutch nationality, shall enjoy in and vis-&#xE0;-vis the
            Kingdom of the Netherlands the same privileges and immunities as are
            conferred on members of the diplomatic staff by the Vienna
            Convention on Diplomatic Relations of 18 April 1961.</al></lid><lid><lidnr>2</lidnr><al>The immunity granted to persons mentioned in paragraph 1 of
            this Article shall not extend to either:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
            <li>
              <li.nr>(i)</li.nr>
              <al>civil action by a third party for damages, including personal
                injury or death, arising from a traffic accident caused by any
                such person, and is without prejudice to Article 32 of the
                Europol Convention; or</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>(ii)</li.nr>
              <al>criminal and civil jurisdiction over acts performed outside
                the course of their official duties. </al>
            </li>
          </lijst></lid><lid><lidnr>3</lidnr><al>The obligations of Sending States and their personnel that
            apply under the Vienna Convention to members of the diplomatic
            staff, shall apply to the persons referred to in paragraph 1 of this Article.</al></lid>
          
          
          </artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><nr>3</nr><titel>Entry, stay and departure</titel></kop>
          <lid><lidnr>1</lidnr><al>The Government shall facilitate, if necessary, the entry, stay
            and departure of the Liaison Officer and members of his family
            forming part of the household.</al></lid><lid><lidnr>2</lidnr><al> This Article shall not prevent the requirement of reasonable
            evidence to establish that persons claiming the treatment provided
            for under this Article come within the classes described in
            paragraph 1 of this Article.</al></lid><lid><lidnr>3</lidnr><al> Visas which may be required by persons referred to in this
            Article shall be granted without charge and as promptly as possible.</al></lid>
          
          </artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><nr>4</nr><titel>Employment</titel></kop>
          <al>Members of the family forming part of the household of the Liaison
            Officer not having the nationality of an EU Member State shall be
            exempt from the obligation to obtain working permits for the
            duration of the secondment of the Liaison Officer.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><nr>5</nr><titel>Inviolability of archives</titel></kop>
          <al>The archives of the Liaison Officer wherever located and by
            whomsoever held shall be inviolable.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><nr>6</nr><titel>Personal Protection</titel></kop>
          <al>The Host State authorities shall, if so requested by the Member
            State, take all reasonable steps in accordance with their national
            laws to ensure the necessary safety and protection of the Liaison
            Officer, as well as members of his family who form part of his
            household, whose security is endangered due to the performance of
            the tasks of the Liaison Officer at Europol.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><nr>7</nr><titel>Facilities and immunities in respect of communication</titel></kop><lid><lidnr>1</lidnr><al>The Government shall permit the Liaison Officer to communicate
            freely and without a need for special permission, for all official
            purposes, and shall protect the right of the Liaison Officer to do
            so. The Liaison Officer shall have the right to use codes and to
            dispatch and receive official correspondence and other official
            communications by courier or in sealed bags which shall be subject
            to the same privileges and immunities as diplomatic couriers and bags.</al></lid>
          <lid><lidnr>2</lidnr><al> The Liaison Officer shall, as far as may be compatible with the
            International Telecommunications Convention of 6 November 1982, for
            his official communications enjoy treatment not less favourable than
            that accorded by the Kingdom of the Netherlands to any international
            organisation or government, in the matter of priorities for
            communication by mail, cable, telegraph, telex, radio, television,
            telephone, fax, satellite, or other means.</al></lid>
          </artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><nr>8</nr><titel>Notification</titel></kop>
          <lid><lidnr>1</lidnr><al> The Member State shall promptly notify the Government of the
            name of the Liaison Officer, his arrival and his final departure or
            the termination of his secondment as well as the arrival and final
            departure of the members of the family forming part of the household
            and, where appropriate, the fact that a person has ceased to form
            part of the household.</al></lid><lid><lidnr>2</lidnr><al> The Government shall issue to the Liaison Officer and members
            of his family forming part of the household, an identification card
            bearing the photograph of the holder. This card shall serve to
            identify the holder in relation to all Host State authorities.</al></lid>
          </artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><nr>9</nr><titel>Settlement of Disputes</titel></kop>
          <lid><lidnr>1</lidnr><al> Any dispute between the Member State and the Government
            concerning the interpretation or application of this Agreement, or
            any question affecting the Liaison Officer or the relationship
            between the Member State and the Government which is not settled
            amicably, shall be referred for final decision to a tribunal of
            three arbitrators, at the request of the Member State or the
            Government. Each party shall appoint one arbitrator. The third, who
            shall be chairman of the tribunal, is to be chosen by the first two arbitrators.</al></lid><lid><lidnr>2</lidnr><al> If one of the parties fails to appoint an arbitrator within two
            months following a request from the other party to make such an
            appointment, the other party may request the President of the Court
            of Justice of the European Communities or in his absence the
            Vice-President, to make such an appointment.</al></lid><lid><lidnr>3</lidnr><al> Should the first two arbitrators fail to agree upon the third
            within two months following their appointment, either party may
            request the President of the Court of Justice of the European
            Communities, or in his absence the Vice-President, to make such appointment.</al></lid><lid><lidnr>4</lidnr><al> Unless the parties agree otherwise, the tribunal shall
            determine its own procedure.</al></lid><lid><lidnr>5</lidnr><al> The tribunal shall reach its decision by a majority of votes.
            The Chairman shall have a casting vote. The decision shall be final
            and binding on the Parties to the dispute. </al></lid>
          
          
          
          
          </artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><nr>10</nr><titel>Territorial scope</titel> </kop>
          <al>With respect to the Kingdom of the Netherlands, this Agreement
            shall apply to the part of the Kingdom in Europe only.</al></artikel></wettekst></verdragtekst><verdragtekst><kop><label>Nr.</label><nr>II</nr></kop><vrije-tekst><tekst status="goed">
          <tussenkop>FOREIGN AND COMMONWEALTH OFFICE</tussenkop>
          <al>London, SW1</al><al/><al>TXA 402/001/99</al><al>Note No A76/99</al>
          <al/><al>The Foreign and Commonwealth Office presents its compliments to
            the Embassy of the Kingdom of the Netherlands, and has the honour to
            confirm receipt of the Embassy's Note of 9 December 1998 which
            reads as follows:</al>
          <al><redactie type="extra">(Zoals in Nr. I)</redactie></al>
          <al>The Foreign and Commonwealth Office has the honour to inform the
            Embassy of the Kingdom of the Netherlands that the proposal set out
            in the Embassy's Note is acceptable to the Government of the
            United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland and that the
            Embassy's Note, and this reply, shall constitute an Agreement
            between the two Governments, which shall enter into force on the
            first day of the month following the day on which both Parties have
            informed each other in writing that the legal requirements for entry
            into force have been complied with.</al>
          <al>The Foreign and Commonwealth Office avails itself of this
            opportunity to renew to the Embassy of the Kingdom of the
            Netherlands the assurances of its highest consideration.</al>
          <al/><al>9 March 1999 </al></tekst></vrije-tekst></verdragtekst></verdrag>
</wetgeving>
  	