<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE wetgeving SYSTEM "http://wetten.overheid.nl/dtd/bwb-plus-meta-1_61w.dtd">
<wetgeving bwb-id="BWBV0004541" dtdversie="2.0" id="10000040159" verdragnummer="004527" soort="verdrag"> 
  
  <alias-titels><alias-titel>Protocol to the European Code of Social Security</alias-titel></alias-titels>
  <intitule>Protocol bij de Europese Code inzake Sociale Zekerheid</intitule> 
   
  <verdrag status="goed" tekst="authentiek" xml:lang="en">
<verdragtekst>
					<kop>
						<titel status="officieel">Protocol to the European Code of Social Security</titel>
					</kop>
					<aanhef>
						<preambule>
							<al>
								<nadruk type="cur">Preamble</nadruk></al>
							<al>The member States of the Council of Europe, signatory hereto,</al>
							<al>Being resolved to establish a higher level of social security than that provided for in the provisions of the European Code of Social Security signed at Strasbourg on the 16th April 1964 (hereinafter referred to as &#x201C;the Code&#x201D;);</al>
							<al>Desirous that all member States of the Council should strive to achieve such higher level, with due regard to economic considerations in their respective countries,</al>
							
						</preambule>
					<afkondiging><al>Have agreed on the following provisions which have been prepared with the collaboration of the International Labour Office:</al></afkondiging></aanhef>
					<wettekst>
						<afdeling status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>SECTION</label>
								<nr status="officieel">I</nr>
							</kop>
							
						<structuurtekst status="goed"><al><redactie type="vervanging">Wijzigt de Europese Code inzake sociale zekerheid; Straatsburg, 16 april 1964.</redactie></al></structuurtekst></afdeling>
						<afdeling status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>SECTION</label>
								<nr status="officieel">II</nr>
							</kop>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<nr status="officieel">1</nr>
								</kop>
								<al>No member State of the Council of Europe shall sign or ratifiy this Protocol without having simultaneously or previously signed or ratified the European Code of Social Security.</al>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<nr status="officieel">2</nr>
								</kop>
								<al>No State shall accede to this Protocol without having simultaneously or previously acceded to the European Code of Social Security.</al>
							</artikel>
						</afdeling>
						<afdeling status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>SECTION</label>
								<nr status="officieel">III</nr>
							</kop>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<nr status="officieel">1</nr>
								</kop>
								<al>This Protocol shall be open to signature by the member States. It shall be subject to ratification. Instruments of ratification shall be deposited with the Secretary-General, provided that the Committee of Ministers in appropriate cases has previously given an affirmative decision as provided for in Section IV, paragraph 4.</al>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<nr status="officieel">2</nr>
								</kop>
								<al>This Protocol shall enter into force one year after the date of the deposit of the third instrument of ratification.</al>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<nr status="officieel">3</nr>
								</kop>
								<al>As regards any Signatory ratifying subsequently, this Protocol shall enter into force one year after the date of deposit of its instrument of ratification.</al>
							</artikel>
						</afdeling>
						<afdeling status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>SECTION</label>
								<nr status="officieel">IV</nr>
							</kop>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<nr status="officieel">1</nr>
								</kop>
								<al>Any Signatory wishing to avail itself of the provisions of Article 2, paragraph 2 of the Code as amended by the Protocol shall, before ratification, submit to the Secretary-General a report showing to what extent its system of social security is in conformity with the provisions of this Protocol.</al>
								<al>Such report shall include a statement of:</al>
								<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
									<li>
										<li.nr>(a)</li.nr>
										<al>the relevant laws and regulations; and</al>
									</li>
									<li>
										<li.nr>(b)</li.nr>
										<al>evidence of compliance with the statistical conditions specified in the following provisions of the Code as amended by this Protocol:</al>
										<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
											<li>
												<li.nr>(i)</li.nr>
												<al>Articles 9 (<nadruk type="cur">a</nadruk>), (<nadruk type="cur">b</nadruk>) or (<nadruk type="cur">c</nadruk>); 15 (<nadruk type="cur">a</nadruk>) or (<nadruk type="cur">b</nadruk>); 21 (<nadruk type="cur">a</nadruk>); 27 (<nadruk type="cur">a</nadruk>) or (<nadruk type="cur">b</nadruk>); 33; 41 (<nadruk type="cur">a</nadruk>) or (<nadruk type="cur">b</nadruk>); 48 (<nadruk type="cur">a</nadruk>) or (<nadruk type="cur">b</nadruk>); 55 (<nadruk type="cur">a</nadruk>) or <nadruk type="cur">b</nadruk>); 61 (<nadruk type="cur">a</nadruk>) or (<nadruk type="cur">b</nadruk>), as regards the number of persons protected;</al>
											</li>
											<li>
												<li.nr>(ii)</li.nr>
												<al>Articles 44, 65, 66 or 67, as regards the rates of benefit;</al>
											</li>
											<li>
												<li.nr>(iii)</li.nr>
												<al>Article 24, paragraph 2, as regards duration of unemployment benefit; and</al>
											</li>
											<li>
												<li.nr>(iv)</li.nr>
												<al>Article 70, paragraph 2, as regards the proportion of the financial resources constituted by the insurance contributions of employees protected; and</al>
											</li>
										</lijst>
									</li>
									<li>
										<li.nr>(c)</li.nr>
										<al>all elements which the Signatory wishes to be taken into acount, in accordance with Article 2, paragraphs 2 and 3 of the Code as amended by this Protocol.</al>
									</li>
								</lijst>
								<al>Such evidence shall, as far as possible, be presented in such general order and manner as may be suggested by the Committee.</al>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<nr status="officieel">2</nr>
								</kop>
								<al>The Signatory shall furnish to the Secretary-General, if so requested by him, further information on the manner in which its system of social security is in conformity with the provisions of this Protocol.</al>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<nr status="officieel">3</nr>
								</kop>
								<al>Such report and further information shall be examined by the Committee which shall take into account the provisions of Article 2, paragraph 3 of the Code. The Committee shall submit to the Committee of Ministers a report containing its conclusions.</al>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<nr status="officieel">4</nr>
								</kop>
								<al>The Committee of Ministers shall, by a two-thirds majority in accordance with Article 20, paragraph (<nadruk type="cur">d</nadruk>) of the Statute of the Council of Europe, decide whether the system of social security of such Signatory is in conformity with the requirements of this Protocol.</al>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<nr status="officieel">5</nr>
								</kop>
								<al>If the Committee of Ministers decides that the said social security scheme is not in conformity with the provisions of this Protocol, it shall so inform the Signatory concerned and may make recommendations as to how such conformity may be effected.</al>
							</artikel>
						</afdeling>
					</wettekst>
					<wetsluiting status="goed">
						<slotformulering>
							<al>IN WITNESS WHEREOF the undersigned, being duly authorised thereto, have signed this Protocol.</al>
							<al>DONE at Strasbourg, this 16th day of April 1964 in French and English, both texts being equally authoritative, in a single copy which shall remain deposited in the archives of the Council of Europe, and of which the Secretary-General shall send certified copies to each of the signatory and acceding States and to the Director-General of the International Labour Office.</al>
							
						</slotformulering>
					</wetsluiting>
				</verdragtekst>
				<verdragtekst><kop><titel status="officieel"/></kop><vrije-tekst><tekst status="goed"><al><redactie type="vervanging">Wijzigt de Europese Code inzake sociale zekerheid; Straatsburg, 16 april 1964.</redactie></al></tekst></vrije-tekst></verdragtekst></verdrag> 
<verdrag status="goed" tekst="vertaling" xml:lang="nl"><verdragtekst>
					<kop>
						<titel status="officieel">Protocol bij de Europese Code inzake Sociale Zekerheid</titel>
					</kop>
					<aanhef>
						<preambule>
							<al>
								<nadruk type="cur">Preambule</nadruk></al>
							<al>De Staten die dit Protocol hebben ondertekend, Leden van de Raad van Europa,</al>
							<al>Besloten hebbende een hoger sociaal zekerheidsniveau vast te stellen dan dat waarin de bepalingen van de op 16 april 1964 te Straatsburg ondertekende Europese Code inzake Sociale Zekerheid (hierna te noemen &#x201E;de Code&#x201D;) voorzien;</al>
							<al>Geleid door de wens dat alle Lid-Staten van de Raad naar het bereiken van dit hogere peil zullen streven, daarbij rekening houdende met overwegingen van economische aard in hun onderscheiden landen,</al>
							
						</preambule>
					<afkondiging><al>Zijn de volgende bepalingen, die zijn opgesteld met medewerking van het Internationale Arbeidsbureau, overeengekomen:</al></afkondiging></aanhef>
					<wettekst>
						<titeldeel status="vervallen">
							<kop>
								<label>TITEL</label>
								<nr status="officieel">I</nr>
							</kop>
							<structuurtekst status="goed"><al><redactie type="vervanging">Wijzigt de Europese Code inzake sociale zekerheid; Straatsburg, 16 april 1964.</redactie></al></structuurtekst>
							
							
						</titeldeel>
						<titeldeel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>TITEL</label>
								<nr status="officieel">II</nr>
							</kop>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<nr status="officieel">1</nr>
								</kop>
								<al>Geen Lid-Staat van de Raad van Europa kan dit Protocol ondertekenen of bekrachtigen zonder gelijktijdig of tevoren de Europese Code inzake sociale zekerheid te hebben ondertekend of bekrachtigd.</al>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<nr status="officieel">2</nr>
								</kop>
								<al>Geen Staat kan tot dit Protocol toetreden zonder gelijktijdig of te voren tot de Europese Code inzake sociale zekerheid te zijn toegetreden.</al>
							</artikel>
						</titeldeel>
						<titeldeel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>TITEL</label>
								<nr status="officieel">III</nr>
							</kop>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<nr status="officieel">1</nr>
								</kop>
								<al>Dit Protocol staat open voor ondertekening door de Lid-Staten. Het moet worden bekrachtigd. De akten van bekrachtiging worden nedergelegd bij de Secretaris-Generaal, mits het Comit&#xE9; van Ministers in daarvoor in aanmerking komende gevallen te voren een bevestigende beslissing heeft genomen als bedoeld in lid 4 van Titel IV.</al>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<nr status="officieel">2</nr>
								</kop>
								<al>Dit Protocol treedt in werking &#xE9;&#xE9;n jaar na het tijdstip van nederlegging van de derde akte van bekrachtiging.</al>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<nr status="officieel">3</nr>
								</kop>
								<al>Ten aanzien van elke ondertekenende Staat die dit Protocol op een later tijdstip bekrachtigt, treedt het in werking &#xE9;&#xE9;n jaar na het tijdstip van nederlegging van zijn akte van bekrachtiging.</al>
							</artikel>
						</titeldeel>
						<titeldeel status="goed">
							<kop>
								<label>TITEL</label>
								<nr status="officieel">IV</nr>
							</kop>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<nr status="officieel">1</nr>
								</kop>
								<al>Elke ondertekenende Staat die zich wenst te beroepen op de bepalingen van artikel 2, lid 2, van de Code, als bij dit Protocol gewijzigd, legt, alvorens tot bekrachtiging over te gaan, aan de Secretaris-Generaal een verslag over, waaruit blijkt in hoeverre zijn stelsel van sociale zekerheid in overeenstemming is met de bepalingen van dit Protocol.</al>
								<al>Dit verslag moet een verklaring bevatten aangaande:</al>
								<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
									<li>
										<li.nr>(a)</li.nr>
										<al>de ter zake bestaande wetgeving en</al>
									</li>
									<li>
										<li.nr>(b)</li.nr>
										<al>gegevens waaruit blijkt dat is voldaan aan de statistische voorwaarden neergelegd in de volgende bepalingen van de Code, als bij dit Protocol gewijzigd:</al>
										<lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
											<li>
												<li.nr>(i)</li.nr>
												<al>de artikelen 9 (<nadruk type="cur">a</nadruk>), (<nadruk type="cur">b</nadruk>) of (<nadruk type="cur">c</nadruk>); 15 (<nadruk type="cur">a</nadruk>) of (<nadruk type="cur">b</nadruk>); 21 (<nadruk type="cur">a</nadruk>); 27 <nadruk type="cur">a</nadruk>) of (<nadruk type="cur">b</nadruk>); 33; 41 (<nadruk type="cur">a</nadruk>) of (<nadruk type="cur">b</nadruk>); 48 (<nadruk type="cur">a</nadruk>) of (<nadruk type="cur">b</nadruk>); 55 (<nadruk type="cur">a</nadruk>) of (<nadruk type="cur">b</nadruk>); 61 (<nadruk type="cur">a</nadruk>) of (<nadruk type="cur">b</nadruk>) wat het aantal beschermde personen betreft;</al>
											</li>
											<li>
												<li.nr>(ii)</li.nr>
												<al>de artikelen 44, 65, 66 of 67, wat de bedragen der uitkeringen betreft;</al>
											</li>
											<li>
												<li.nr>(iii)</li.nr>
												<al>artikel 24, lid 2, wat de duur van de uitkering bij werkloosheid betreft; en</al>
											</li>
											<li>
												<li.nr>(iv)</li.nr>
												<al>artikel 70, lid 2, wat betreft het aandeel in de inkomsten voortkomende uit de verzekeringspremies van de beschermde loontrekkenden; en</al>
											</li>
										</lijst>
									</li>
									<li>
										<li.nr>(c)</li.nr>
										<al>alle elementen waarmede, op verlangen van de ondertekenende Regering, rekening moet worden gehouden, overeenkomstig de leden 2 en 3 van artikel 2 van de Code, als bij dit Protocol gewijzigd.</al>
									</li>
								</lijst>
								<al>Voor zover mogelijk dienen deze gegevens te worden verstrekt op de wijze en in de volgorde aangegeven door de Commissie.</al>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<nr status="officieel">2</nr>
								</kop>
								<al> De betrokken ondertekenende Regering verstrekt de Secretaris-Generaal op diens verzoek verdere gegevens omtrent de punten waarop haar stelsel van sociale zekerheid in overeenstemming is met de bepalingen van dit Protocol.</al>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<nr status="officieel">3</nr>
								</kop>
								<al>Genoemd verslag en deze verdere gegevens worden bestudeerd door de Commissie, die daarbij de bepalingen van artikel 2, lid 3, van de Code in acht neemt. De Commissie legt aan het Comit&#xE9; van Ministers een verslag over, waarin haar conclusies zijn vervat.</al>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<nr status="officieel">4</nr>
								</kop>
								<al>Met een meerderheid van twee derde van het aantal uitgebrachte stemmen beslist het Comit&#xE9; van Ministers overeenkomstig het bepaalde in artikel 20, sub (<nadruk type="cur">d</nadruk>) van het Statuut van de Raad van Europa, of het stelsel van sociale zekerheid van de ondertekenende Staat in overeenstemming is met de bepalingen van dit Protocol.</al>
							</artikel>
							<artikel status="goed">
								<kop>
									<nr status="officieel">5</nr>
								</kop>
								<al>Indien het Comit&#xE9; van Ministers van oordeel is dat het bedoelde stelsel van sociale zekerheid niet in overeenstemming is met de bepalingen van dit Protocol, verwittigt zij de betrokken ondertekenende Staat hiervan en kan deze aanbevelingen doen omtrent de wijze waarop dit stelsel alsnog met deze bepalingen in overeenstemming kan worden gebracht.</al>
							</artikel>
						</titeldeel>
					</wettekst>
					<wetsluiting status="goed">
						<slotformulering>
							<al>TEN BLIJKE WAARVAN de ondergetekenden, daartoe behoorlijk gemachtigd, dit Protocol hebben ondertekend.</al>
							<al>GEDAAN te Straatsburg, de 16de april 1964, in de Franse en de Engelse taal, zijnde beide teksten gelijkelijk gezaghebbend, in &#xE9;&#xE9;n exemplaar, dat zal worden nedergelegd in het archief van de Raad van Europa en waarvan de Secretaris-Generaal voor eensluidend gewaarmerkte afschriften doet toekomen aan elk van de ondertekenende en toetredende Staten, alsmede aan de Directeur-Generaal van het Internationale Arbeidsbureau.</al>
							
						</slotformulering>
					</wetsluiting>
				</verdragtekst>
				<verdragtekst>
					<kop>
						
						
						<titel status="officieel"/>
						
					</kop>
					<vrije-tekst><tekst status="goed"><al><redactie type="vervanging">Wijzigt de Europese Code inzake sociale zekerheid; Straatsburg, 16 april 1964.</redactie></al></tekst></vrije-tekst>
				</verdragtekst></verdrag></wetgeving>
  	