<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE wetgeving SYSTEM "http://wetten.overheid.nl/dtd/bwb-plus-meta-1_61w.dtd">
<wetgeving bwb-id="BWBV0004933" dtdversie="2.0" id="10000044079" verdragnummer="007229" soort="verdrag"> 
  
  <alias-titels><alias-titel>Convention concerning equal remuneration for men and women workers for work of equal value</alias-titel></alias-titels>
  <intitule>Verdrag betreffende gelijke beloning van mannelijke en vrouwelijke arbeidskrachten voor arbeid van gelijke waarde</intitule>
  
  <verdrag status="goed" tekst="authentiek" xml:lang="en"><verdragtekst>
<kop>
<titel status="officieel">Convention concerning equal remuneration for men and women workers for work of equal value</titel>
</kop><aanhef><preambule><al>The General Conference of the International Labour Organisation,</al><al>Having been convened at Geneva by the Governing Body of the International Labour Office, and having met in its Thirty-fourth Session on 6 June 1951, and</al><al>Having decided upon the adoption of certain proposals with regard to the principle of equal remuneration for men and women workers for work of equal value, which is the seventh item on the agenda of the session, and</al><al>Having determined that these proposals shall take the form of an international Convention,</al></preambule><afkondiging><al>adopts this twenty-ninth day of June of the year one thousand nine hundred and fifty-one the following Convention, which may be cited as the Equal Remuneration Convention, 1951:</al></afkondiging></aanhef><wettekst><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">1</nr>
</kop><al>For the purpose of this Convention&#x2014;</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>the term &#x201C;remuneration&#x201D; includes the ordinary, basic or minimum wage or salary and any additional emoluments whatsoever payable directly or indirectly, whether in cash or in kind, by the employer to the worker and arising out of the worker's employment;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>the term &#x201C;equal remuneration for men and women workers for work of equal value&#x201D; refers to rates of remuneration established without discrimination based on sex.</al></li></lijst></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">2</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Each Member shall, by means appropriate to the methods in operation for determining rates of remuneration, promote and, in so far as is consistent with such methods, ensure the application to all workers of the principle of equal remuneration for men and women workers for work of equal value.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>This principle may be applied by means of&#x2014;</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>national laws or regulations;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>legally established or recognised machinery for wage determination;</al></li><li><li.nr>(c)</li.nr><al>collective agreements between employers and workers; or</al></li><li><li.nr>(d)</li.nr><al>a combination of these various means.</al></li></lijst></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">3</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Where such action will assist in giving effect to the provisions of this Convention measures shall be taken to promote objective appraisal of jobs on the basis of the work to be performed.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>The methods to be followed in this appraisal may be decided upon by the authorities responsible for the determination of rates of remuneration, or, where such rates are determined by collective agreements, by the parties thereto.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>Differential rates between workers which correspond, without regard to sex, to differences, as determined by such objective appraisal, in the work to be performed shall not be considered as being contrary to the principle of equal remuneration for men and women workers for work of equal value.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">4</nr>
</kop><al>Each Member shall co-operate as appropriate with the employers' and workers' organisations concerned for the purpose of giving effect to the provisions of this Convention.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">5</nr>
</kop><al>The formal ratifications of this Convention shall be communicated to the Director-General of the International Labour Office for registration.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">6</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>This Convention shall be binding only upon those Members of the International Labour Organisation whose ratifications have been registered with the Director-General.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>It shall come into force twelve months after the date on which the ratifications of two Members have been registered with the Director-General.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>Thereafter, this Convention shall come into force for any Member twelve months after the date on which its ratification has been registered.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Article</label><nr status="officieel">7</nr></kop><lid><lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Declarations communicated to the Director-General of the International Labour Office in accordance with paragraph 2 of Article 35 of the Constitution of the International Labour Organisation shall indicate&#x2014;</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>the territories in respect of which the Member concerned undertakes that the provisions of the Convention shall be applied without modification;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>the territories in respect of which it undertakes that the provisions of the Convention shall be applied subject to modifications, together with details of the said modifications;</al></li><li><li.nr>(c)</li.nr><al>the territories in respect of which the Convention is inapplicable and in such cases the grounds on which it is inapplicable;</al></li><li><li.nr>(d)</li.nr><al>the territories in respect of which it reserves its decisions pending further consideration of the position.</al></li></lijst></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>The undertakings referred to in subparagraphs (<nadruk type="cur">a</nadruk>) and (<nadruk type="cur">b</nadruk>) of paragraph 1 of this Article shall be deemed to be an integral part of the ratification and shall have the force of ratification.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>Any Member may at any time by a subsequent declaration cancel in whole or in part any reservation made in its original declaration in virtue of subparagraphs (<nadruk type="cur">b), (c</nadruk>) or (<nadruk type="cur">d</nadruk>) of paragraph 1 of this Article.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr><al>Any Member may, at any time at which the Convention is subject to denunciation in accordance with the provisions of Article 9, communicate to the Director-General a declaration modifying in any other respect the terms of any former declaration and stating the present position in respect of such territories as it may specify.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">8</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Declarations communicated to the Director-General of the International Labour Office in accordance with paragraphs 4 or 5 of Article 35 of the Constitution of the International Labour Organisation shall indicate whether the provisions of the Convention will be applied in the territory concerned without modification or subject to modifications; when the declaration indicates that the provisions of the Convention will be applied subject to modifications, it shall give details of the said modifications.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>The Member, Members or international authority concerned may at any time by a subsequent declaration renounce in whole or in part the right to have recourse to any modification indicated in any former declaration.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>The Member, Members or international authority concerned may, at any time at which this Convention is subject to denunciation in accordance with the provisions of Article 9, communicate to the Director-General a declaration modifying in any other respect the terms of any former declaration and stating the present position in respect of the application of the Convention.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">9</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>A Member which has ratified this Convention may denounce it after the expiration of ten years from the date on which the Convention first comes into force, by an act communicated to the Director-General of the International Labour Office for registration. Such denunciation shall not take effect until one year after the date on which it is registered.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Each Member which has ratified this Convention and which does not, within the year following the expiration of the period of ten years mentioned in the preceding paragraph, exercise the right of denunciation provided for in this Article, will be bound for another period of ten years and, thereafter, may denounce this Convention at the expiration of each period of ten years under the terms provided for in this Article.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop><label>Article</label><nr status="officieel">10</nr></kop><lid><lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>The Director-General of the International Labour Office shall notify all Members of the International Labour Organisation of the registration of all ratifications, declarations and denunciations communicated to him by the Members of the Organisation.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>When notifying the Members of the Organisation of the registration of the second ratification communicated to him, the Director-General shall draw the attention of the Members of the Organisation to the date upon which the Convention will come into force.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">11</nr>
</kop><al>The Director-General of the International Labour Office shall communicate to the Secretary-General of the United Nations for registration in accordance with Article 102 of the Charter of the United Nations full particulars of all ratifications, declarations and acts of denunciation registered by him in accordance with the provisions of the preceding articles.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">12</nr>
</kop><al>At such times as it may consider necessary the Governing Body of the International Labour Office shall present to the General Conference a report on the working of this Convention and shall examine the desirability of placing on the agenda of the Conference the question of its revision in whole or in part.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">13</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Should the Conference adopt a new Convention revising this Convention in whole or in part, then, unless the new Convention otherwise provides&#x2014;</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>(a)</li.nr><al>the ratification by a Member of the new revising Convention shall <nadruk type="cur">ipso jure</nadruk> involve the immediate denunciation of this Convention, notwithstanding the provisions of Article 9 above, if and when the new revising Convention shall have come into force;</al></li><li><li.nr>(b)</li.nr><al>as from the date when the new revising Convention comes into force this Convention shall cease to be open to ratification by the Members.</al></li></lijst></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>This Convention shall in any case remain in force in its actual form and content for those Members which have ratified it but have not ratified the revising Convention.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Article</label>
<nr status="officieel">14</nr>
</kop><al>The English and French versions of the text of this Convention are equally authoritative.</al></artikel></wettekst></verdragtekst></verdrag><verdrag status="goed" tekst="vertaling" xml:lang="nl"><verdragtekst>
<kop>
<titel status="officieel">Verdrag betreffende gelijke beloning van mannelijke en vrouwelijke arbeidskrachten voor arbeid van gelijke waarde</titel>
</kop><aanhef><preambule><al>De Algemene Conferentie van de Internationale Arbeidsorganisatie,</al><al>Door de Raad van Beheer van het Internationaal Arbeidsbureau bijeengeroepen te Gen&#xE8;ve, en aldaar bijeengekomen in haar vier en dertigste zitting op 6 Juni 1951,</al><al>Besloten hebbende verschillende voorstellen aan te nemen betreffende gelijke beloning van mannelijke en vrouwelijke arbeidskrachten voor arbeid van gelijke waarde, welk onderwerp het zevende punt van de agenda der zitting vormt,</al><al>Besloten hebbende, dat deze voorstellen de vorm zullen aannemen van een internationaal Verdrag,</al></preambule><afkondiging><al>neemt heden, de negen en twintigste Juni negentienhonderd een en vijftig, het volgende Verdrag aan, hetwelk kan worden aangehaald als het &#x201E;Verdrag betreffende gelijke beloning, 1951&#x201D;:</al></afkondiging></aanhef><wettekst><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">1</nr>
</kop><al>In dit Verdrag:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>a.</li.nr><al>omvat de term &#x201E;beloning&#x201D; het gewone, basis- of minimumloon of salaris en alle bijkomende emolumenten, die direct of indirect door de werkgever in geld of in natura aan de werknemer uitgekeerd worden en voortvloeien uit de dienstbetrekking van de werknemer;</al></li><li><li.nr>b.</li.nr><al>heeft de term &#x201E;gelijke beloning van mannelijke en vrouwelijke arbeidskrachten voor arbeid van gelijke waarde&#x201D; betrekking op bezoldigingstarieven, die vastgesteld zijn zonder onderscheid op grond van het geslacht.</al></li></lijst></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">2</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Elk Lid dient door middelen, die passen bij de in gebruik zijnde methoden voor de vaststelling van de lonen, de toepassing van het beginsel van gelijke beloning van mannelijke en vrouwelijke arbeidskrachten voor arbeid van gelijke waarde ten aanzien van alle werknemers te bevorderen, en, in de mate als in overeenstemming met deze middelen is, een zodanige toepassing te waarborgen.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Dit beginsel kan toegepast worden door middel van:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>a.</li.nr><al>nationale wetten of regelingen;</al></li><li><li.nr>b.</li.nr><al>wettelijk vastgestelde of erkende stelsels voor het vaststellen van de bezoldiging;</al></li><li><li.nr>c.</li.nr><al>collectieve arbeidsovereenkomsten tussen werkgevers en werknemers;</al></li><li><li.nr>d.</li.nr><al>een combinatie van de verschillende bovengenoemde middelen.</al></li></lijst></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">3</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Wanneer een dergelijke handelwijze dienstig is voor het ten uitvoer leggen van de bepalingen van dit Verdrag dienen maatregelen genomen te worden om een objectieve waardering van beroepen op basis van het te verrichten werk te bevorderen.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>De te volgen methoden bij deze waardering kunnen bepaald worden door de autoriteiten, die verantwoordelijk zijn voor de vaststelling van bezoldigingstarieven, of, wanneer deze tarieven vastgesteld zijn bij collectieve arbeidsovereenkomsten, door de betrokken partijen.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>Tariefsverschillen die, ongeacht het geslacht, voortvloeien uit bij een dergelijke objectieve waardering vastgestelde verschillen in het te verrichten werk, mogen niet als strijdig met het beginsel van gelijke beloning van mannelijke en vrouwelijke arbeidskrachten voor arbeid van gelijke waarde beschouwd worden.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">4</nr>
</kop><al>Elk Lid dient op gepaste wijze samen te werken met de betrokken organisaties van werkgevers en werknemers teneinde uitvoering te geven aan de bepalingen van dit Verdrag.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">5</nr>
</kop><al>De formele bekrachtigingen van dit Verdrag zullen worden medegedeeld aan de Directeur-Generaal van het Internationaal Arbeidsbureau en door hem worden geregistreerd.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">6</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Dit Verdrag zal slechts verbindend zijn voor de leden van de Internationale Arbeidsorganisatie, wier bekrachtiging door de Directeur-Generaal is geregistreerd.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Dit Verdrag zal in werking treden twaalf maanden nadat de bekrachtigingen van twee Leden door de Directeur-Generaal zijn geregistreerd.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>Vervolgens zal dit Verdrag voor ieder der Leden in werking treden twaalf maanden na de datum, waarop zijn bekrachtiging is geregistreerd.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">7</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Verklaringen, gezonden aan de Directeur-Generaal van het Internationaal Arbeidsbureau overeenkomstig lid 2 van artikel 35 van het Statuut van de Internationale Arbeidsorganisatie, moeten aangeven:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>a.</li.nr><al>de gebieden, ten aanzien waarvan het betrokken Lid zich verbindt de bepalingen van het Verdrag ongewijzigd toe te passen;</al></li><li><li.nr>b.</li.nr><al>de gebieden, ten aanzien waarvan het zich verbindt de bepalingen van het Verdrag met wijzigingen toe te passen, en waarin die wijzigingen bestaan;</al></li><li><li.nr>c.</li.nr><al>de gebieden, waar het Verdrag niet toegepast kan worden, en in die gevallen de redenen waarom;</al></li><li><li.nr>d.</li.nr><al>de gebieden, waarvoor het zich zijn beslissing voorbehoudt, hangende nader onderzoek van de omstandigheden.</al></li></lijst></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>De verplichtingen, bedoeld onder <nadruk type="cur">a</nadruk> en <nadruk type="cur">b</nadruk> van het eerste lid van dit artikel, zullen geacht worden een integrerend deel van de bekrachtiging uit te maken en zullen dezelfde rechtskracht hebben.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>Elk Lid kan te allen tijde bij een nadere verklaring geheel of gedeeltelijk afstand doen van enig voorbehoud, krachtens het bepaalde onder <nadruk type="cur">b, c</nadruk> of <nadruk type="cur">d</nadruk> van het eerste lid van dit artikel vervat in zijn oorspronkelijke verklaring.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr><al>Elk Lid kan op elk tijdstip waarop dit Verdrag overeenkomstig het bepaalde in artikel 9 kan worden opgezegd, aan de Directeur-Generaal een verklaring doen toekomen, waarbij in enig ander opzicht de inhoud van een vorige verklaring gewijzigd wordt en de toestand ten aanzien van bepaalde aangegeven gebieden medegedeeld wordt.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">8</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Verklaringen, gezonden aan de Directeur-Generaal van het Internationaal Arbeidsbureau overeenkomstig de leden 4 of 5 van artikel 35 van het Statuut van de Internationale Arbeidsorganisatie, moeten aangeven of de bepalingen van het Verdrag al of niet gewijzigd zullen worden toegepast in het betrokken gebied; indien de verklaring aangeeft dat de bepalingen van het Verdrag met wijzigingen zullen worden toegepast moet zij bijzonderheden van de genoemde wijzigingen geven.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Het betrokken Lid, dan wel de betrokken Leden of internationale autoriteit kunnen te allen tijde bij een latere verklaring geheel of gedeeltelijk afstand doen van het recht om een beroep te doen op een wijziging, in een vorige verklaring medegedeeld.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr><al>Het betrokken Lid, dan wel de betrokken Leden of internationale autoriteit kunnen op elk tijdstip, waarop dit Verdrag overeenkomstig het bepaalde in artikel 9 opgezegd kan worden, aan de Directeur-Generaal een verklaring doen toekomen, waarbij in enig ander opzicht de inhoud van een vorige verklaring gewijzigd wordt en de huidige toestand ten aanzien van de toepassing van het Verdrag medegedeeld wordt.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">9</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Een Lid, dat dit Verdrag bekrachtigd heeft, kan het opzeggen na verloop van een termijn van tien jaren na de datum, waarop dit Verdrag in werking is getreden, middels een verklaring, toegezonden aan de Directeur-Generaal van het Internationaal Arbeidsbureau en door deze geregistreerd. De opzegging treedt eerst in werking een jaar nadat zij is geregistreerd.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Ieder Lid, dat dit Verdrag heeft bekrachtigd en niet binnen een jaar na het verloop van de termijn van tien jaren, bedoeld in het vorige lid, gebruik maakt van het recht tot opzegging, voorzien in dit artikel, zal voor een nieuwe termijn van tien jaren gebonden zijn en zal daarna dit Verdrag kunnen opzeggen na verloop van elke termijn van tien jaren onder de voorwaarden bedoeld in dit artikel.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">10</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>De Directeur-Generaal van het Internationaal Arbeidsbureau dient aan alle Leden van de Internationale Arbeidsorganisatie kennis te geven van de registratie van alle bekrachtigingen, verklaringen en opzeggingen, welke hem door de Leden der Organisatie zijn medegedeeld.</al></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Bij de kennisgeving van de tweede hem medegedeelde bekrachtiging aan de Leden der Organisatie dient de Directeur-Generaal de aandacht van de Leden te vestigen op de datum, waarop het Verdrag in werking zal treden.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">11</nr>
</kop><al>De Directeur-Generaal van het Internationaal Arbeidsbureau zal volledige bijzonderheden omtrent alle bekrachtigingen, verklaringen en opzeggingen, welke hij geregistreerd heeft overeenkomstig de bepalingen van de voorgaande artikelen, doen toekomen aan de Secretaris-Generaal van de Verenigde Naties ter registratie overeenkomstig artikel 102 van het Handvest der Verenigde Naties.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">12</nr>
</kop><al>De Raad van Beheer van het Internationaal Arbeidsbureau dient, wanneer hij zulks nodig moge oordelen, verslag uit te brengen aan de Algemene Conferentie over de toepassing van dit Verdrag en te onderzoeken of het wenselijk is de gehele of gedeeltelijke herziening ervan op de agenda der Conferentie te plaatsen.</al></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">13</nr>
</kop><lid>
<lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr><al>Indien de Conferentie een nieuw Verdrag aanneemt, houdende gehele of gedeeltelijke herziening van het onderhavige Verdrag, zal, tenzij het nieuwe Verdrag anders bepaalt:</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet"><li><li.nr>a.</li.nr><al>de bekrachtiging door een Lid van het nieuwe Verdrag, houdende herziening, ipso jure onmiddellijke opzegging van het onderhavige Verdrag ten gevolge hebben, niettegenstaande het bepaalde in artikel 9, indien en zodra het nieuwe Verdrag, houdende herziening, in werking getreden zal zijn;</al></li><li><li.nr>b.</li.nr><al>met ingang van de datum, waarop het nieuwe Verdrag, houdende herziening, in werking treedt, het onderhavige Verdrag niet langer door de Leden bekrachtigd kunnen worden.</al></li></lijst></lid><lid><lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr><al>Het onderhavige Verdrag zal echter in elk geval naar huidige vorm en inhoud van kracht blijven voor die Leden, die het bekrachtigd hebben en die het nieuwe Verdrag, houdende herziening, niet bekrachtigen.</al></lid></artikel><artikel status="goed"><kop>
<label>Artikel</label>
<nr status="officieel">14</nr>
</kop><al>De Engelse en de Franse tekst van dit Verdrag zijn gelijkelijk authentiek.</al></artikel></wettekst></verdragtekst></verdrag></wetgeving>
  	