<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE wetgeving SYSTEM "http://wetten.overheid.nl/dtd/bwb-plus-meta-1_61w.dtd">
<wetgeving bwb-id="BWBV0001665" id="10000001919" verdragnummer="010869" soort="verdrag">
  <intitule>Briefwisseling houdende een verdrag tussen het Koninkrijk der
    Nederlanden en de Organisatie der Verenigde Naties voor Onderwijs,
    Wetenschap en Cultuur (UNESCO) betreffende de conferentie van 3 tot en met 7
    mei 2004 op Aruba</intitule>
  
  <verdrag tekst="authentiek" xml:lang="en">
    <verdragtekst>
      
      <kop>
        <label>Nr.</label><nr>I</nr>
      </kop>
      <vrije-tekst>
        <tekst status="goed">
          
          <al>UNESCO</al><al> Paris, 22 March 2004</al>
          <al>DG/7/04.078</al>
          <al>Subject: Agreement between the Government of the Kingdom of the
            Netherlands and the United Nations Educational, Scientific and
            Cultural Organization concerning the Director-General's
            Consultation with National Commissions of Latin America and the
            Caribbean for the Preparation of the Draft Programme and Budget for
            2006-2007 (33 C/5) and the 13th Quadrennial and Statutory Meeting of
            National Commissions of the Region</al>
          <al>(Oranjestad, Aruba, 3-7 May 2004)</al>
          <al>Sir,</al>
          <al>I have the honour to refer to the letter from H. E. Mr Nelson
            Oduber, Prime Minister of Aruba, dated 3 September 2003, addressed
            to Mr Francisco Jos&#xE9; Lacayo Paraj&#xF3;n, Director UNESCO Office in
            Havana (Cuba), by which the Government of Aruba kindly offered to
            host the Director-General's Consultation with National
            Commissions of Latin America and the Caribbean for the preparation
            of the Draft Programme and Budget for 2006-2007 (33C/5) and the 13th
            Quadrennial and Statutory Meeting of National Commissions of the
            Region. I wish to express once again my sincere thanks to the
            Government of Aruba for this offer, which I accept on behalf of the Organization.</al>
          <lijst><li><li.nr>A.</li.nr><al>Nature and scope of the meeting</al><al>The meeting is being convened within the framework of
            UNESCO's Approved Programme and Budget for 2004-2005 (paragraph
            18014 of document 32 C/5), adopted by the General Conference at its
            32nd session.</al></li><li><li.nr>B.</li.nr><al>Participation</al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
            <li>
              <li.nr>(i)</li.nr>
              <al>Chief participants</al>
            <al>The chief participants will be representatives of National
                Commissions for UNESCO of the Latin America and the Caribbean Region.</al></li>
          <li>
              <li.nr>(ii)</li.nr>
              <al>Other participants</al>
            <al>The Director-General may extend invitations to organizations
                of the United Nations system and other inter-governmental organizations.</al></li><li>
              <li.nr>(iii)</li.nr>
              <al>Observers</al>
            <al>The Director-General may request international
                non-governmental organizations and non-governmental
                organizations to send representatives.</al></li></lijst></li></lijst>
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          <al>The total number of participants, including representatives,
            observers and members of the UNESCO Secretariat, is expected to be
            approximately 65 persons.</al>
          <al>I have the honour to submit for your consideration the customary
            proposals regarding arrangements for the holding of the meeting.</al>
          <lijst><li><li.nr>I.</li.nr><al>
            <nadruk type="vet">Place and date of the meeting</nadruk>
          </al><al>The meeting shall take place in Oranjestad, Aruba, from 3 to 7 May
            2004 at Wyndham Aruba Resort, 4 Diamond Resort, Aruba.</al></li><li><li.nr>II.</li.nr><al>
            <nadruk type="vet">Organization of the meeting</nadruk>
          </al><al>The responsibility for the technical and material organization of
            the meeting shall be shared by the competent host authorities and
            UNESCO, on the basis of the attached statement of requirements.</al>
          <al>However, nothing in the provisions of this letter shall prevent
            the two parties from mutually agreeing to make such adjustments as
            may be desirable to ensure the proper organization of the meeting.</al>
          <al>In order to facilitate the organization of the meeting, the
            Government of Aruba shall, upon signature of the present Agreement,
            designate a senior official to be responsible, on its behalf and
            with due authority, for liaison with the Secretariat of UNESCO and
            for the installation and operation of the various services to be
            provided at the place of the meeting. All matters concerning the
            technical and material organization of this meeting may from then on
            be handled through the liaison officer thus appointed.</al></li><li><li.nr>III.</li.nr><al>
            <nadruk type="vet">Privileges and immunities</nadruk>
          </al><al>The Government of Aruba shall apply, in all matters relating to
            this meeting, the provisions of the Convention on the Privileges and
            Immunities of the Specialized Agencies of the United Nations. In
            particular, the Government shall ensure that no restriction is
            placed upon the entry into, sojourn in, and departure from Aruba of
            all persons, of whatever nationality, entitled to attend the meeting
            by virtue of a decision of the appropriate authorities of UNESCO and
            in accordance with the Organization's relevant rules and
            regulations, provided that the general conditions governing entry
            are fulfilled.</al></li><li><li.nr>IV.</li.nr><al>
            <nadruk type="vet">Damages and accidents</nadruk>
          </al><al>As long as the premises reserved for the meeting are at the
            disposal of UNESCO, the Government of Aruba shall bear the risk of
            damage to the premises, facilities and furniture and shall assume
            all responsibility and liability for accidents that may occur to
            persons present therein. The authorities of Aruba shall adopt
            appropriate measures to ensure the protection, particularly against
            fire and other risks, of the above-mentioned premises, facilities
            and furniture and persons. The Government of Aruba may also claim
            from UNESCO compensation for any damage to persons and property
            caused by the fault of staff members or agents of the Organization. </al></li></lijst>
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          <al>If, as I hope, the above proposals are acceptable to you, I should
            appreciate receiving your Government's acceptance by letter or
            telefax on the above responsibilities at your earliest convenience. </al>
          <al>This letter and your reply will constitute the Agreement covering
            the Meeting.</al>
          <al>Accept, Sir, the assurances of my highest consideration.</al>
          <al>KO&#xCF;CHIRO MATSUURA</al>
          <al>Director-General of</al>
          <al>UNESCO</al>
          <al>7, Place Fontenoy</al>
          <al>75007 Paris</al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">His Excellency</nadruk>
          </al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">L. P. van Vliet </nadruk>
          </al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">Ambassador Extraordinary and Plenipotentiary</nadruk>
          </al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">Permanent Delegate of the Netherlands to UNESCO</nadruk>
          </al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">7, rue Ebl&#xE9;</nadruk>
          </al>
          
        </tekst>
      </vrije-tekst>
    </verdragtekst>
  <verdragtekst><kop><titel status="redactioneel">Attachment</titel></kop><vrije-tekst><tekst status="goed"><tussenkop><nadruk type="vet">The Director-General's consultation with National
            Commissions of Latin America and the Caribbean for the Preparation
            of the Draft Programme and Budget for 2006&#x2013;2007 (33 C/5) and the
            13th Quadrennial and Statutory Meeting of National Commissions of
            the Region</nadruk></tussenkop>
          <tussenkop>Oranjestad, Aruba, 3&#x2013;7 May 2004</tussenkop>
          <tussenkop><nadruk type="vet">Statement of Requirements</nadruk></tussenkop>
          <lijst><li><li.nr>I.</li.nr><al>
            <nadruk type="vet">BASIS FOR EVALUATION</nadruk>
          </al><table frame="none"><tgroup cols="2"><colspec colname="col1" colnum="1" colsep="0" colwidth="60mm" rowsep="0"/><colspec colname="col2" colnum="2" colsep="0" colwidth="60mm" rowsep="0"/><tbody><row><entry colname="col1" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>Place of the meeting:</al></entry><entry colname="col2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al> Wyndham Aruba Resort, </al></entry></row><row><entry colname="col1" colsep="0" rowsep="0"/><entry colname="col2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>Oranjestad, Aruba</al></entry></row><row><entry colname="col1" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>Date:</al></entry><entry colname="col2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al> 3&#x2013;7 May 2004</al></entry></row><row><entry colname="col1" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>Duration:</al></entry><entry colname="col2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al> 5 calendar days</al></entry></row><row><entry colname="col1" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al>Approximate number of participants:</al></entry><entry colname="col2" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><al> 65</al></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></table></li><li><li.nr>II.</li.nr><al>
            <nadruk type="vet">RESPONSIBILITIES OF UNESCO</nadruk>
          </al><lijst><li><li.nr>1.</li.nr><al>Preliminary arrangements and technical coordination with host authorities</al></li><li><li.nr>2.</li.nr><al>Preparation and dispatch of invitations and working documents</al></li><li><li.nr>3.</li.nr><al>Secretariat of the meeting</al></li><li><li.nr>4.</li.nr><al>Transport (international air tickets) for participants and Secretariat</al></li><li><li.nr>5.</li.nr><al>Production and distribution of the final report</al></li></lijst></li><li><li.nr>III.</li.nr><al>
            <nadruk type="vet">RESPONSIBILITIES OF ARUBA</nadruk>
          </al><al>All costs to be borne by UNESCO.</al><lijst><li><li.nr>1.</li.nr><al><nadruk type="cur">Services and facilities:</nadruk>
          </al><lijst><li><li.nr>a)</li.nr><al>The Government of Aruba will make the necessary arrangements
                for a speedy entry visa procedure for persons in need of a visa
                for entry to Aruba and participating in the meeting, provided
                they hold an official invitation of UNESCO (the list must be
                communicated in due course by UNESCO)</al></li><li><li.nr>b)</li.nr><al>Official telephone communications, international faxes and
                Internet access from the offices of the Secretariat of the
                meeting for the duration of the meeting</al></li></lijst></li><li><li.nr>2.</li.nr><al><nadruk type="cur">Premises:</nadruk>
          </al><lijst><li><li.nr>a)</li.nr><al>Meeting room for plenary sessions, equipped for simultaneous interpretation</al></li><li><li.nr>b)</li.nr><al>An office for the Secretariat of the meeting</al></li><li><li.nr>c)</li.nr><al>A counter for reception of participants and distribution of documents</al></li><li><li.nr>d)</li.nr><al>5 smaller meeting rooms for one day, for Cluster Meetings,
                with the respective capacity:</al><lijst><li><li.nr>&#x25CF;</li.nr><al>one for 10 places</al></li><li><li.nr>&#x25CF;</li.nr><al>one for 23 places</al></li><li><li.nr>&#x25CF;</li.nr><al>one for 11 places</al></li><li><li.nr>&#x25CF;</li.nr><al>one for 11 places</al></li><li><li.nr>&#x25CF;</li.nr><al>one for 13 places</al></li></lijst></li></lijst></li><li><li.nr>3.</li.nr><al><nadruk type="cur">Furniture and equipment:</nadruk>
          </al><lijst><li><li.nr>a)</li.nr><al>Furniture for the above-mentioned premises, including
                computers, printers and internal and external telephone connections</al></li><li><li.nr>b)</li.nr><al>Equipment for simultaneous interpretation in 2 languages
                (cabins, channels, microphones, headphones)</al></li><li><li.nr>c)</li.nr><al>Photocopy machines with adequate supplies and technical assistance</al></li><li><li.nr>d)</li.nr><al>A set of name-plates for the members of the meeting (the list
                will be communicated in due course by UNESCO)</al></li><li><li.nr>e)</li.nr><al>Stationery for seats with table (notepads, pencils, etc.)</al></li><li><li.nr>f)</li.nr><al>65 meeting briefcases or folders</al></li><li><li.nr>g)</li.nr><al>One screen, one overhead projector, one projector</al></li></lijst></li><li><li.nr>4.</li.nr><al><nadruk type="cur">Staff:</nadruk>
          </al><lijst><li><li.nr>a)</li.nr><al>1 receptionist, bilingual English/Spanish</al></li><li><li.nr>b)</li.nr><al>Technicians for interpretation, photocopying</al></li><li><li.nr>c)</li.nr><al>3 meeting room assistants</al></li><li><li.nr>d)</li.nr><al>3 secretaries, bilingual English/Spanish</al></li></lijst></li><li><li.nr>5.</li.nr><al><nadruk type="cur">Reservation of accommodation:</nadruk>
          </al><lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
            <li>
              <li.nr>a)</li.nr>
              <al>Advance reservation of a sufficient number of suitable hotel
                rooms for all participants and observers, at their own expense </al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>b)</li.nr>
              <al>Arrangements for the reception at the airport upon arrival and
                on departure (assistance with entry formalities, luggage
                clearance, etc.), of persons officially attending the meeting
                and transportation for them between their points of arrival and
                departure and their hotels</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>c)</li.nr>
              <al>Protocol service at the airport for arrival and departure of
                ministers and other senior officials</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>d)</li.nr>
              <al>Appropriate transportation for participants between their
                hotels and other official events connected with the Conference,
                as necessary</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>e)</li.nr>
              <al>Advance distribution of detailed information on local
                conditions and arrangements</al>
            </li>
          </lijst></li><li><li.nr>6.</li.nr><al>Official Reception in the evening of the opening day.</al></li></lijst></li></lijst>
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          
          </tekst></vrije-tekst></verdragtekst><verdragtekst><kop><label>Nr.</label><nr>II</nr></kop><vrije-tekst><tekst status="goed">
          <al>Permanent Delegation of the Netherlands to UNESCO</al>
          <al>HV/Aruba</al>
          <al>Paris, 3 May 2004 </al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="vet">Agreement concerning the Consultation with
              NatComs of Latin America and the Caribbean, Aruba, 3-7 May 2004</nadruk>
          </al>
          <al>Sir,</al>
          <al>I have the honor to refer to your <intref status="actief" doc="1.0:v:BWBV0001665&amp;verdragtekst=I">letter DG/7/04.078 of 22 March
            2004</intref>, relating to an agreement to be concluded between the
            Government of the Kingdom of the Netherlands and the United Nations
            Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization (UNESCO)concerning
            the Director-General's Consultation with National Commissions
            of Latin America and the Caribbean for the Preparation of the Draft
            Programme and Budget for 2006-2007 (33 C/5) and the 13th Quadrennial
            and Statutory Meeting of National Commissions of the Region, which
            is scheduled to be held in Oranjestad, Aruba, from 3 to 7 May 2004,
            which reads as follows:</al>
          
          <al><redactie type="extra">(Zoals in Nr. I)</redactie></al><al>I am authorized by the Government of the Kingdom of the
            Netherlands to state that it agrees to the proposals regarding the
            organization of the Meeting and to state that the Government of the
            Kingdom of the Netherlands considers your letter and my reply as
            together constituting an Agreement between the Government of the
            Kingdom of the Netherlands and UNESCO in respect of the
            Director-General's Consultation with National Commissions of
            Latin America and the Caribbean for the Preparation of the Draft
            Programme and Budget for 2006-2007 (33 C/5) and the 13th Quadrennial
            and Statutory Meeting of National Commissions of the Region, which
            shall enter into force on the date of this reply and shall remain in
            force for the duration of the Meeting and for such additional period
            as is necessary for its preparation and winding up, the total
            duration of this Agreement, however, not to exceed one year.</al>
          <al>Please accept, Sir, the assurances of my highest consideration.</al>
          <al>L. P. VAN VLIET</al>
          <al>Ambassador Extraordinary and Plenipotentiary</al>
          <al>Permanent Delegate of the Netherlands to UNESCO </al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">His Excellency</nadruk>
          </al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">Ko&#xEF;chiro Matsuura </nadruk>
          </al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">Director-General of UNESCO</nadruk>
          </al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">7, Place Fontenoy</nadruk>
          </al>
          <al>
            <nadruk type="cur">75007 Paris</nadruk>
          </al>
          </tekst></vrije-tekst></verdragtekst><verdragtekst><kop><titel status="redactioneel">Attachment</titel></kop><vrije-tekst><tekst status="goed"><al><redactie type="extra">(Zoals in Nr. I)</redactie></al></tekst></vrije-tekst></verdragtekst></verdrag>
</wetgeving>
  	