<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE wetgeving SYSTEM "http://wetten.overheid.nl/dtd/bwb-plus-meta-1_61w.dtd">
<wetgeving bwb-id="BWBV0001382" id="10000003429" verdragnummer="007920" soort="verdrag">
  <intitule>Verdrag inzake de privileges en immuniteiten van het Internationale
    Hof voor het recht van de zee</intitule>
  
  
  <verdrag tekst="authentiek" xml:lang="en">
    <verdragtekst>
      <kop>
        <titel>Agreement on the Privileges and Immunities of the International
          Tribunal for the Law of the Sea</titel>
      </kop>
      <aanhef>
        <preambule>
          <al>The States Parties to the present Agreement,</al>
          <al>Considering that the <extref status="actief" doc="1.0:v:BWBV0003172" compleet="nee">United Nations Convention on the Law of the
            Sea</extref> establishes the International Tribunal for the Law of the Sea,</al>
          <al>Recognizing that the Tribunal should enjoy such legal capacity,
            privileges and immunities as are necessary for the exercise of its functions,</al>
          <al>Recalling that the Statute of the Tribunal provides, in article
            10, that the Members of the Tribunal, when engaged on the business
            of the Tribunal, shall enjoy diplomatic privileges and immunities,</al>
          <al>Recognizing that persons participating in proceedings and
            officials of the Tribunal should enjoy such privileges and
            immunities as are necessary for the independent exercise of their
            functions in connection with the Tribunal,</al>
          
        </preambule>
      <afkondiging><al>Have agreed as follows:</al></afkondiging></aanhef>
      <wettekst>
        
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">1</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Use of terms</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>For the purposes of this Agreement:</al>
          <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
            <li>
              <li.nr>a)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x201C;Convention&#x201D; means the <extref status="actief" doc="1.0:v:BWBV0003172" compleet="nee">United Nations Convention on the
                Law of the Sea</extref> of 10 December 1982;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>b)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x201C;Statute&#x201D; means the <extref status="actief" doc="1.0:v:BWBV0003172&amp;verdragtekst=VI" compleet="nee">Statute of the International Tribunal
                for the Law of the Sea</extref> in annex VI to the Convention;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>c)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x201C;States Parties&#x201D; means States Parties to this Agreement;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>d)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x201C;Tribunal&#x201D; means the International Tribunal for the Law
                of the Sea;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>e)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x201C;Member of the Tribunal&#x201D; means an elected member of the
                Tribunal or a person chosen under <extref status="actief" doc="1.0:v:BWBV0003172&amp;artikel=17" compleet="nee">article 17 of the Statute</extref> for
                the purpose of a particular case;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>f)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x201C;Registrar&#x201D; means the Registrar of the Tribunal and
                includes any official of the Tribunal acting as Registrar;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>g)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x201C;officials of the Tribunal&#x201D; means the Registrar and other
                members of the staff of the Registry;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>h)</li.nr>
              <al>&#x201C;Vienna Convention&#x201D; means the <extref status="actief" doc="1.0:v:BWBV0004345" compleet="nee">Vienna Convention on
                Diplomatic Relations</extref> of 18 April 1961. </al>
            </li>
          </lijst>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr>2</nr>
            <titel>Juridical personality of the Tribunal</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>The Tribunal shall possess juridical personality. It shall have
            the capacity:</al>
          <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
            <li>
              <li.nr>a)</li.nr>
              <al>to contract;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>b)</li.nr>
              <al>to acquire and dispose of immovable and movable property;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>c)</li.nr>
              <al>to institute legal proceedings.</al>
            </li>
          </lijst>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr>3</nr>
            <titel>Inviolability of the premises of the Tribunal</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>The premises of the Tribunal shall be inviolable, subject to such
            conditions as may be agreed with the State Party concerned.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr>4</nr>
            <titel>Flag and emblem</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>The Tribunal shall be entitled to display its flag and emblem at
            its premises and on vehicles used for official purposes.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr>5</nr>
            <titel>Immunity of the Tribunal, its property, assets and funds</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr>1</lidnr>
            <al> The Tribunal shall enjoy immunity from legal process, except
              insofar as in any particular case it has expressly waived its
              immunity. </al>
          <al>It is, however, understood that no waiver of immunity shall extend
            to any measure of execution.</al></lid>
          
          <lid>
            <lidnr>2</lidnr>
            <al> The property, assets and funds of the Tribunal, wherever
              located and by whomsoever held, shall be immune from search,
              requisition, confiscation, seizure, expropriation or any other
              form of interference, whether by executive, administrative,
              judicial or legislative action.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr>3</lidnr>
            <al> To the extent necessary to carry out its functions, the
              property, assets and funds of the Tribunal shall be exempt from
              restrictions, regulations, controls and moratoria of any nature.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr>4</lidnr>
            <al> The Tribunal shall have insurance coverage against third-party
              risks in respect of vehicles owned or operated by it, as required
              by the laws and regulations of the State in which the vehicle is operated.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr>6</nr>
            <titel>Archives</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>The archives of the Tribunal, and all documents belonging to it or
            held by it, shall be inviolable at all times and wherever they may
            be located. The State Party where the archives are located shall be
            informed of the location of such archives and documents.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr>7</nr>
            <titel>Exercise of the functions of the Tribunal outside the Headquarters</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>In the event that the Tribunal considers it desirable to sit or
            otherwise exercise its functions elsewhere than at its Headquarters,
            it may conclude with the State concerned an arrangement concerning
            the provision of the appropriate facilities for the exercise of its functions.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr>8</nr>
            <titel>Communications</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr>1</lidnr>
            <al> For the purposes of its official communications and
              correspondence, the Tribunal shall enjoy in the territory of each
              State Party, insofar as is compatible with the international
              obligations of the State concerned, treatment not less favourable
              than that which the State Party accords to any intergovernmental
              organization or diplomatic mission in the matter of priorities,
              rates and taxes applicable to mail and the various forms of
              communication and correspondence.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr>2</lidnr>
            <al> The Tribunal may use all appropriate means of communication and
              make use of codes or cipher for its official communications or
              correspondence. The official communications and correspondence of
              the Tribunal shall be inviolable.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr>3</lidnr>
            <al> The Tribunal shall have the right to dispatch and receive
              correspondence and other materials or communications by courier or
              in sealed bags, which shall have the same privileges, immunities
              and facilities as diplomatic couriers and bags.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr>9</nr>
            <titel>Exemption from taxes, customs duties and import or  export restrictions</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr>1</lidnr>
            <al> The Tribunal, its assets, income and other property, and its
              operations and transactions shall be exempt from all direct taxes;
              it is understood, however, that the Tribunal shall not claim
              exemption from taxes which are no more than charges for public
              utility services.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr>2</lidnr>
            <al> The Tribunal shall be exempt from all customs duties, import
              turnover taxes and prohibitions and restrictions on imports and
              exports in respect of articles imported or exported by the
              Tribunal for its official use.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr>3</lidnr>
            <al> Goods imported or purchased under such an exemption shall not
              be sold or otherwise disposed of in the territory of a State
              Party, except under conditions agreed with the Government of that
              State Party. The Tribunal shall also be exempt from all customs
              duties, import turnover taxes, prohibitions and restrictions on
              imports and exports in respect of its publications.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr>10</nr>
            <titel>Reimbursement of duties and/or taxes</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr>1</lidnr>
            <al> The Tribunal shall not, as a general rule, claim exemption from
              duties and taxes which are included in the price of movable and
              immovable property and taxes paid for services rendered.
              Nevertheless, when the Tribunal for its official use makes major
              purchases of property and goods or services on which duties and
              taxes are charged or are chargeable, States Parties shall make
              appropriate administrative arrangements for the exemption of such
              charges or reimbursement of the amount of duty and/or tax paid.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr>2</lidnr>
            <al> Goods purchased under such an exemption or reimbursement shall
              not be sold or otherwise disposed of, except in accordance with
              the conditions laid down by the State Party which granted the
              exemption or reimbursement. No exemption or reimbursement shall be
              accorded in respect of charges for public utility services
              provided to the Tribunal.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr>11</nr>
            <titel>Taxation</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr>1</lidnr>
            <al> The salaries, emoluments and allowances paid to Members and
              officials of the Tribunal shall be exempt from taxation.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr>2</lidnr>
            <al> Where the incidence of any form of taxation depends upon
              residence, periods during which such Members or officials are
              present in a State for the discharge of their functions shall not
              be considered as periods of residence if such Members or officials
              are accorded diplomatic privileges, immunities and facilities.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr>3</lidnr>
            <al> States Parties shall not be obliged to exempt from income tax
              pensions or annuities paid to former Members and former officials
              of the Tribunal.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr>12</nr>
            <titel>Funds and freedom from currency restrictions</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr>1</lidnr>
            <al> Without being restricted by financial controls, regulations or
              financial moratoriums of any kind, while carrying out its activities:</al>
            <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
              <li>
                <li.nr>a)</li.nr>
                <al>the Tribunal may hold funds, currency of any kind or gold
                  and operate accounts in any currency;</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>b)</li.nr>
                <al>the Tribunal shall be free to transfer its funds, gold or
                  its currency from one country to another or within any country
                  and to convert any currency held by it into any other currency;</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>c)</li.nr>
                <al>the Tribunal may receive, hold, negotiate, transfer, convert
                  or otherwise deal with bonds and other financial securities.</al>
              </li>
            </lijst>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr>2</lidnr>
            <al> In exercising its rights under paragraph 1, the Tribunal shall
              pay due regard to any representations made by any State Party
              insofar as it is considered that effect can be given to such
              representations without detriment to the interests of the Tribunal.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">13</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Members of the Tribunal</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al> Members of the Tribunal shall, when engaged on the business of
              the Tribunal, enjoy the privileges, immunities, facilities and
              prerogatives accorded to heads of diplomatic missions in
              accordance with the <extref status="actief" doc="1.0:v:BWBV0004345" compleet="nee">Vienna Convention</extref>.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al> Members of the Tribunal and members of their families forming
              part of their households shall be accorded every facility for
              leaving the country where they may happen to be and for entering
              and leaving the country where the Tribunal is sitting. On journeys
              in connection with the exercise of their functions, they shall in
              all countries through which they may have to pass enjoy all the
              privileges, immunities and facilities granted by these countries
              to diplomatic agents in similar circumstances.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al> If Members of the Tribunal, for the purpose of holding
              themselves at the disposal of the Tribunal, reside in any country
              other than that of which they are nationals or permanent
              residents, they shall, together with the members of their families
              forming part of their households, be accorded diplomatic
              privileges, immunities and facilities during the period of their
              residence there.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr>
            <al> Members of the Tribunal shall be accorded, together with
              members of their families forming part of their households, the
              same repatriation facilities in time of international crises as
              are accorded to diplomatic agents under the <extref status="actief" doc="1.0:v:BWBV0004345" compleet="nee">Vienna Convention</extref>.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">5</lidnr>
            <al> Members of the Tribunal shall have insurance coverage against
              third-party risks in respect of vehicles owned or operated by
              them, as required by the laws and regulations of the State in
              which the vehicle is operated.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">6</lidnr>
            <al> Paragraphs 1 to 5 of this article shall apply to Members of the
              Tribunal even after they have been replaced if they continue to
              exercise their functions in accordance with <extref status="actief" doc="1.0:v:BWBV0003172&amp;artikel=5" compleet="nee">article 5, paragraph
              3, of the Statute</extref>.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">7</lidnr>
            <al> In order to secure, for Members of the Tribunal, complete
              freedom of speech and independence in the discharge of their
              functions, the immunity from legal process in respect of words
              spoken or written and all acts done by them in discharging their
              functions shall continue to be accorded, notwithstanding that the
              persons concerned are no longer Members of the Tribunal or
              performing those functions.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">14</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Officials</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al> The Registrar shall, when engaged on the business of the
              Tribunal, be accorded diplomatic privileges, immunities and facilities.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al> Other officials of the Tribunal shall enjoy in any country
              where they may be on the business of the Tribunal, or in any
              country through which they may pass on such business, such
              privileges, immunities and facilities as are necessary for the
              independent exercise of their functions. In particular, they shall
              be accorded:</al>
            <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
              <li>
                <li.nr>a)</li.nr>
                <al>immunity from personal arrest or detention and from seizure
                  of their personal baggage;</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>b)</li.nr>
                <al>the right to import free of duty their furniture and effects
                  at the time of first taking up their post in the country in
                  question and to re-export the same free of duty to their
                  country of permanent residence;</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>c)</li.nr>
                <al>exemption from inspection of personal baggage, unless there
                  are serious grounds for believing that the baggage contains
                  articles not for personal use or articles the import or export
                  of which is prohibited by the law or controlled by the
                  quarantine regulations of the State Party concerned; an
                  inspection in such a case shall be conducted in the presence
                  of the official concerned;</al>
              </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>d)</li.nr>
              <al>immunity from legal process in respect of words spoken or
                written and all acts done by them in discharging their
                functions, which immunity shall continue even after they have
                ceased to exercise their functions;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>e)</li.nr>
              <al>immunity from national service obligations;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>f)</li.nr>
              <al>together with members of their families forming part of their
                household, exemption from immigration restrictions or alien
                registration; </al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>g)</li.nr>
              <al>the same privileges in respect of currency and exchange
                facilities as are accorded to the officials of comparable rank
                forming part of diplomatic missions to the Government concerned;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>h)</li.nr>
              <al>together with members of their families forming part of their
                household, the same repatriation facilities in time of
                international crises as are accorded to diplomatic agents under
                the <extref status="actief" doc="1.0:v:BWBV0004345" compleet="nee">Vienna Convention</extref>.</al>
            </li></lijst>
          </lid>
          
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al> The officials of the Tribunal shall be required to have
              insurance coverage againinst third-party risks in respect of
              vehicles owned or operated by them, as required by the laws and
              regulations of the State in which the vehicle is operated.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr>
            <al> The Tribunal shall communicate to all States Parties the
              categories of officials to which the provisions of this article
              shall apply. The names of the officials included in these
              categories shall from time to time be communicated to all States Parties.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">15</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Experts appointed under <extref status="actief" doc="1.0:v:BWBV0003172&amp;artikel=289" compleet="nee">article 289 of the Convention</extref></titel>
          </kop>
          <al>Experts appointed under <extref status="actief" doc="1.0:v:BWBV0003172&amp;artikel=289" compleet="nee">article 289 of the Convention</extref> shall be
            accorded, during the period of their missions, including the time
            spent on journeys in connection with their missions, such
            privileges, immunities and facilities as are necessary for the
            independent exercise of their functions. In particular, they shall
            be accorded:</al>
          <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
            <li>
              <li.nr>a)</li.nr>
              <al>immunity from personal arrest or detention and from seizure of
                their personal baggage;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>b)</li.nr>
              <al>exemption from inspection of personal baggage, unless there
                are serious grounds for believing that the baggage contains
                articles not for personal use or articles the import or export
                of which is prohibited by law or controlled by the quarantine
                regulations of the State Party concerned; an inspection in such
                a case shall be conducted in the presence of the expert concerned;</al>
            </li>
          <li>
              <li.nr>c)</li.nr>
              <al>immunity from legal process in respect of words spoken or
                written and acts done by them in discharging their functions,
                which immunity shall continue even after they have ceased to
                exercise their functions;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>d)</li.nr>
              <al>inviolability of documents and papers;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>e)</li.nr>
              <al>exemption from immigration restrictions or alien registration;</al>
            </li><li>
              <li.nr>f)</li.nr>
              <al>the same facilities in respect of currency and exchange
                restrictions as are accorded to representatives of foreign
                Governments on temporary official missions;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>g)</li.nr>
              <al>such experts shall be accorded the same repatriation
                facilities in time of international crises as are accorded to
                diplomatic agents under the <extref status="actief" doc="1.0:v:BWBV0004345" compleet="nee">Vienna Convention</extref>. </al>
            </li></lijst>
          
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">16</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Agents, counsel and advocates</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al> Agents, counsel and advocates before the Tribunal shall be
              accorded, during the period of their missions, including the time
              spent on journeys in connection with their missions, the
              privileges, immunities and facilities necessary for the
              independent exercise of their functions. In particular, they shall
              be accorded:</al>
            <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
              <li>
                <li.nr>a)</li.nr>
                <al>immunity from personal arrest or detention and from seizure
                  of their personal baggage;</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>b)</li.nr>
                <al>exemption from inspection of personal baggage, unless there
                  are serious grounds for believing that the baggage contains
                  articles not for personal use or articles the import or export
                  of which is prohibited by law or controlled by the quarantine
                  regulations of the State Party concerned; an inspection in
                  such a case shall be conducted in the presence of the agent,
                  counsel or advocate concerned;</al>
              </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>c)</li.nr>
              <al>immunity from legal process in respect of words spoken or
                written and all acts done by them in discharging their
                functions, which immunity shall continue even after they have
                ceased to exercise their functions;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>d)</li.nr>
              <al>inviolability of documents and papers;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>e)</li.nr>
              <al>the right to receive papers or correspondence by courier or in
                sealed bags;</al>
            </li>
            <li>
              <li.nr>f)</li.nr>
              <al>exemption from immigration restrictions or alien registration;</al>
            </li><li>
              <li.nr>g)</li.nr>
              <al>the same facilities in respect of their personal baggage and
                in respect of currency or exchange restrictions as are accorded
                to representatives of foreign Governments on temporary official missions;</al>
            </li><li>
              <li.nr>h)</li.nr>
              <al>the same repatriation facilities in time of international
                crises as are accorded to diplomatic agents under the <extref status="actief" doc="1.0:v:BWBV0004345" compleet="nee">Vienna Convention</extref>.</al>
            </li></lijst>
          </lid>
          
          
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al> Upon receipt of notification from parties to proceedings before
              the Tribunal as to the appointment of an agent, counsel or
              advocate, a certification of the status of such representative
              shall be provided under the signature of the Registrar and limited
              to a period reasonably required for the proceedings.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">3</lidnr>
            <al> The competent authorities of the State concerned shall accord
              the privileges, immunities and facilities provided for in this
              article upon production of the certification referred to in
              paragraph 2.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">4</lidnr>
            <al> Where the incidence of any form of taxation depends upon
              residence, periods during which such agents, counsel or advocates
              are present in a State for the discharge of their functions shall
              not be considered as periods of residence.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr>17</nr>
            <titel>Witnesses, experts and persons performing missions</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr>1</lidnr>
            <al> Witnesses, experts and persons performing missions by order of
              the Tribunal shall be accorded, during the period of their
              missions, including the time spent on journeys in connection with
              their missions, the privileges, immunities and facilities provided
              for in article 15, subparagraphs a) to f).</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr>2</lidnr>
            <al> Witnesses, experts and such persons shall be accorded
              repatriation facilities in time of international crises.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr>18</nr>
            <titel>Nationals and permanent residents</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>Except insofar as additional privileges and immunities may be
            granted by the State Party concerned, and without prejudice to
            article 11, a person enjoying immunities and privileges under this
            Agreement shall, in the territory of the State Party of which he or
            she is a national or permanent resident, enjoy only immunity from
            legal process and inviolability in respect of words spoken or
            written and all acts done by that person in the discharge of his or
            her duties, which immunity shall continue even after the person has
            ceased to exercise his or her functions in connection with the Tribunal.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr>19</nr>
            <titel>Respect for laws and regulations</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr>1</lidnr>
            <al> Privileges, immunities, facilities and prerogatives as provided
              for in articles 13 to 17 of this Agreement are granted not for the
              personal benefit of the individuals themselves but in order to
              safeguard the independent exercise of their functions in
              connection with the Tribunal.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr>2</lidnr>
            <al> Without prejudice to their privileges and immunities, it is the
              duty of all persons referred to in articles 13 to 17 to respect
              the laws and regulations of the State Party in whose territory
              they may be on the business of the Tribunal or through whose
              territory they may pass on such business. They also have a duty
              not to interfere in the internal affairs of that State.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">20</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Waiver</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al> Inasmuch as the privileges and immunities provided for in this
              Agreement are granted in the interests of the good administration
              of justice and not for the personal benefit of the individuals
              themselves, the competent authority has the right and the duty to
              waive the immunity in any case where, in its opinion, the immunity
              would impede the course of justice and can be waived without
              prejudice to the administration of justice.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al> For this purpose, the competent authority in the case of
              agents, counsel and advocates representing or designated by a
              State which is a party to proceedings before the Tribunal will be
              the State concerned. In the case of other agents, counsel and
              advocates, the Registrar, experts appointed under <extref status="actief" doc="1.0:v:BWBV0003172&amp;artikel=289" compleet="nee">article 289 of
              the Convention</extref> and witnesses, experts and persons performing
              missions, the competent authority will be the Tribunal. In the
              case of other officials of the Tribunal, the competent authority
              will be the Registrar, acting with the approval of the President
              of the Tribunal.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr status="officieel">21</nr>
            <titel status="officieel">Laissez-passer and visas</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">1</lidnr>
            <al> The States Parties shall recognize and accept the United
              Nations laissez-passer issued to Members and officials of the
              Tribunal or experts appointed under <extref status="actief" doc="1.0:v:BWBV0003172&amp;artikel=289" compleet="nee">article 289 of the Convention</extref>
              as a valid travel document.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr status="officieel">2</lidnr>
            <al> Applications for visas (where required) from the Members of the
              Tribunal and the Registrar shall be dealt with as speedily as
              possible. Applications for visas from all other persons holding or
              entitled to hold laissez-passer referred to in paragraph 1 of this
              Article and from persons referred to in articles 16 and 17, when
              accompanied by a certificate that they are travelling on the
              business of the Tribunal, shall be dealt with as speedily as possible.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr>22</nr>
            <titel>Freedom of movement</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>No administrative or other restrictions shall be imposed on the
            free movement of Members of the Tribunal, as well as other persons
            mentioned in articles 13 to 17, to and from the Headquarters of the
            Tribunal or the place where the Tribunal is sitting or otherwise
            exercising its functions.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr>23</nr>
            <titel>Maintenance of security and public order</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr>1</lidnr>
            <al> If the State Party concerned considers it necessary to take,
              without prejudice to the independent and proper working of the
              Tribunal, measures necessary for the security or for the
              maintenance of public order of the State Party in accordance with
              international law, it shall approach the Tribunal as rapidly as
              circumstances allow in order to determine by mutual agreement the
              measures necessary to protect the Tribunal.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr>2</lidnr>
            <al> The Tribunal shall cooperate with the Government of such State
              Party to avoid any prejudice to the security or public order of
              the State Party resulting from its activities.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr>24</nr>
            <titel>Cooperation with the authorities of States Parties</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>The Tribunal shall cooperate at all times with the appropriate
            authorities of States Parties to facilitate the execution of their
            laws and to prevent any abuse in connection with the privileges,
            immunities, facilities and prerogatives referred to in this Agreement.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr>25</nr>
            <titel>Relationship with special agreements</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>Insofar as the provisions of this Agreement and the provisions of
            any special agreement between the Tribunal and a State Party relate
            to the same subject matter, the two provisions shall, whenever
            possible, be treated as complementary, so that both provisions shall
            be applicable and neither provision shall narrow the effect of the
            other; but in case of conflict the provision of the special
            agreement shall prevail.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr>26</nr>
            <titel>Settlement of disputes</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr>1</lidnr>
            <al> The Tribunal shall make suitable provisions for the settlement of:</al>
            <lijst level="single" nr-sluiting="." start="1" type="expliciet">
              <li>
                <li.nr>a)</li.nr>
                <al>disputes arising out of contracts and other disputes of a
                  private law character to which the Tribunal is a party;</al>
              </li>
              <li>
                <li.nr>b)</li.nr>
                <al>disputes involving any person referred to in this Agreement
                  who by reason of his official position enjoys immunity, if
                  such immunity has not been waived.</al>
              </li>
            </lijst>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr>2</lidnr>
            <al> All disputes arising out of the interpretation or application
              of this Agreement shall be referred to an arbitral tribunal unless
              the parties have agreed to another mode of settlement. If a
              dispute arises between the Tribunal and a State Party which is not
              settled by consultation, negotiation or other agreed mode of
              settlement within three months following a request by one of the
              parties to the dispute, it shall at the request of either party be
              referred for final decision to a panel of three arbitrators: one
              to be chosen by the Tribunal, one to be chosen by the State Party
              and the third, who shall be Chairman of the panel, to be chosen by
              the first two arbitrators. If either party has failed to make its
              appointment of an arbitrator within two months of the appointment
              of an arbitrator by the other party, the Secretary-General of the
              United Nations shall make such appointment. Should the first two
              arbitrators fail to agree upon the appointment of the third
              arbitrator within three months following the appointment of the
              first two arbitrators the third arbitrator shall be chosen by the
              Secretary-General of the United Nations upon the request of the
              Tribunal or the State Party.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr>27</nr>
            <titel>Signature</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>This Agreement shall be open for signature by all States and shall
            remain open for signature at United Nations Headquarters for
            twenty-four months from 1 July 1997.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr>28</nr>
            <titel>Ratification</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>This Agreement is subject to ratification. The instruments of
            ratification shall be deposited with the Secretary-General of the
            United Nations.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr>29</nr>
            <titel>Accession</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>This Agreement shall remain open for accession by all States. The
            instruments of accession shall be deposited with the
            Secretary-General of the United Nations.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr>30</nr>
            <titel>Entry into force</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr>1</lidnr>
            <al> This Agreement shall enter into force 30 days after the date of
              deposit of the tenth instrument of ratification or accession.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr>2</lidnr>
            <al> For each State which ratifies this Agreement or accedes thereto
              after the deposit of the tenth instrument of ratification or
              accession, this Agreement shall enter into force on the thirtieth
              day following the deposit of its instrument of ratification or accession.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr>31</nr>
            <titel>Provisional application</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>A State which intends to ratify or accede to this Agreement may at
            any time notify the depositary that it will apply this Agreement
            provisionally for a period not exceeding two years. </al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr>32</nr>
            <titel>Ad hoc application</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>Where a dispute has been submitted to the Tribunal in accordance
            with the Statute, any State not a party to this Agreement which is a
            party to the dispute may, ad hoc for the purposes and duration of
            the case relating thereto, become a party to this Agreement by the
            deposit of an instrument of acceptance. Instruments of acceptance
            shall be deposited with the Secretary-General of the United Nations
            and shall become effective on the date of deposit.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr>33</nr>
            <titel>Denunciation</titel>
          </kop>
          <lid>
            <lidnr>1</lidnr>
            <al> A State Party may, by written notification addressed to the
              Secretary-General of the United Nations, denounce this Agreement.
              The denunciation shall take effect one year after the date of
              receipt of the notification, unless the notification specifies a
              later date.</al>
          </lid>
          <lid>
            <lidnr>2</lidnr>
            <al> The denunciation shall not in any way affect the duty of any
              State Party to fulfil any obligation embodied in this Agreement to
              which it would be subject under international law independently of
              this Agreement.</al>
          </lid>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr>34</nr>
            <titel>Depositary</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>The Secretary-General of the United Nations shall be the
            depositary of this Agreement.</al>
        </artikel>
        <artikel status="goed">
          <kop>
            <label>Article</label>
            <nr>35</nr>
            <titel>Authentic texts</titel>
          </kop>
          <al>The Arabic, Chinese, English, French, Russian and Spanish texts of
            this Agreement are equally authentic.</al>
          
        </artikel>
      </wettekst>
      <wetsluiting status="goed">
        <slotformulering>
          <al>IN WITNESS WHEREOF, the undersigned Plenipotentiaries, being duly
            authorized thereto, have signed this Agreement.</al>
          <al>OPENED FOR SIGNATURE at New York, this first day of July, one
            thousand nine hundred and ninety-seven, in a single original, in the
            Arabic, Chinese, English, French, Russian and Spanish languages.</al>
        </slotformulering>
      </wetsluiting>
    </verdragtekst>
  </verdrag>
  
  
  
</wetgeving>
  	